[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a standard used for paging system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) POCSAG",
            "b) ERMES",
            "c) IS-95",
            "d) FLEX"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS-95 is a standard used for cellular system which is based on code division multiple access (CDMA). POCSAG (Post Office Code Standard Advisory Group), ERMES (European Radio Messaging System) and FLEX are the protocols used in paging system."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Paging system uses which mode of transmission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full duplex",
            "b) Simplex",
            "c) Half Duplex",
            "d) Duplex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Simplex systems communicate in only one way. For the paging systems, messages received are not acknowledged and thus they use simplex mode of transmission. "
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "The information sent by paging system is known as a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Note",
            "b) Line",
            "c) Message",
            "d) Page"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Page is concise information sent by a paging system to the subscribers of entire service area."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which type of message cannot be sent with the help of paging system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alphanumeric message",
            "b) Video message",
            "c) Voice message",
            "d) Numeric message"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The message sent by a paging system can be numeric, alphanumeric or voice depending upon the type of service."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "What is a paging access number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An e mail id",
            "b) A username",
            "c) A toll free telephone number",
            "d) A registration number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Paging access number is a telephone number which is used to send the information to the subscriber."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which type of transmission technique is employed by paging system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simulcasting",
            "b) Multicasting",
            "c) Unicasting",
            "d) Hybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Simulcast is a reliable technique used by paging system by transmitting the same paging signal from multiple paging transmitters at approximately equal times."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the property of paging system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asymmetric communication",
            "b) Light weight",
            "c) High cost",
            "d) Wide area coverage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One of the main reasons for the increased users of paging system was its less cost. But as the prices of cellular system declined, the users of paging system also decreased. "
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Which of the following properties describes the transmitters and receivers in paging system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High complexity and high power transmitter, high complexity and high power receivers",
            "b) Low complexity and low power transmitter, low complexity and low power receivers",
            "c) Low complexity and low power transmitter, high complexity and high power receivers",
            "d) High complexity and high power transmitter, low complexity and low power receivers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High power of transmitters helps paging signal to easily penetrate the building and low power receivers allow long usage time and light weight batteries."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "What is a pager in the paging system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A transmitter",
            "b) A receiver",
            "c) A transceiver",
            "d) An equalizer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A pager is a wireless device which receives the page, i.e. numeric, alphanumeric or voice message sent by the transmitter."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Who introduced the paging system for the first time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Al Gross",
            "b) Teri Pall",
            "c) Alexander Graham Bell",
            "d) Martin Cooper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: AL Gross introduced the first paging system during world war in 1949."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a protocol used for cordless telephone system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PACS",
            "b) ERMES",
            "c) IS-95",
            "d) FLEX"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PACS (Personal Access Communication System) is a protocol used for cordless telephone system. ERMES and FLEX are used by paging system. And IS-95 is used for cellular system."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "In which frequency range do the cordless phones mostly work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43-50 MHz",
            "b) 88-108 MHz",
            "c) 540-1600 KHz",
            "d) 200-540 KHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cordless phones mostly operate in the frequency range of 43-50 MHz. The frequency range of FM is 88-108 MHz and for AM is 540-1600 KHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the drawback for cordless telephones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wireless technology",
            "b) Limited coverage area",
            "c) Mobile",
            "d) Security"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cordless telephone systems are wireless, but they have a disadvantage of limited coverage area with cell size of approx. 300 m. Being digital, they have very less chance of eaves dropping."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a fully digital cordless system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CT0",
            "b) CT1",
            "c) CT1+",
            "d) DECT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Digital enhanced cordless telecommunication (DECT) is a fully digital system established in 1991. CT0, Ct1, Ct1+ were analog systems established in 1980, 1984 and 1987 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of local wireless system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) Cordless telephone system",
            "c) UMTS",
            "d) EDGE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GSM, UMTS and EDGE covers worldwide area whereas cordless system has vey less coverage area."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a standard for cordless telephony?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CT-2",
            "b) DECT",
            "c) UMTS",
            "d) PHS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CT-2 is a cordless telephone standard used in Europe and Asia. DECT and PHS (Personal Handyphone System) are cordless telephone standards used in Europe and Japan respectively. UMTS is a cellular system standard."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "What is the range of cell diameter of DECT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 m",
            "b) 2 km",
            "c) 10 km",
            "d) 70 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DECT has the cell diameter of 300 m from the base station while GSM is designed for outdoor use with a cell diameter of 70 km."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Which of the following standard of cordless telephone system is also approved as a 3G standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PHS",
            "b) PACS",
            "c) DECT",
            "d) CT2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DECT fulfills the IMT 2000 requirements and is approved as a 3G standard by ITU (International Telecommunication Union)."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Cordless telephone system will not work under which of the following criteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Within a home",
            "b) Within a building",
            "c) Within campus",
            "d) Within a city"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cordless telephones are used in homes, in offices, on campus, at trade shows. But due to their limited coverage they cannot cover a whole city."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of DECT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multimedia processing",
            "b) Cordless private branch exchange",
            "c) Wireless local loop",
            "d) Home cordless phones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Users in a neighborhood served by a telephone company wired local loop can be connected by a cordless phone that exchanges signals with a neighborhood antenna."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of cellular telephone system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accommodate a large number of users",
            "b) Large geographic area",
            "c) Limited frequency spectrum",
            "d) Large frequency spectrum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cellular systems accommodate a large number of users within a limited frequency spectrum over a large geographic area."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "What is the responsibility of MSC in cellular telephone system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Connection of mobile to base stations",
            "b) Connection of mobile to PSTN",
            "c) Connection of base station to PSTN",
            "d) Connection of base station to MSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mobile Switching Center (MSC) is responsible for connecting all mobiles to the PSTN (Public Switched Telephone Network) in a cellular system."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Who has the responsibility of billing and system maintenance function in cellular system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base Station",
            "b) PSTN",
            "c) MSC",
            "d) Mobile system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mobile switching center (MSC) accommodates 100,000 subscribers and 5,000 simultaneous conversations at a time and handles all billing and system maintenance functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "What is the function of FVC (Forward Voice Channel)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voice transmission from base station to mobiles",
            "b) Voice transmission from mobile to base station",
            "c) Initiating mobile calls",
            "d) Broadcast all traffic request for all mobile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FVC (Forward Voice Channel) and RVC (Reverse Voice Channel) are responsible for voice transmission. FVC is used for voice transmission from base station to mobile and RVC is used for voice transmission from mobile to base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which two channels are responsible for initiating mobile calls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FVC and FCC",
            "b) FVC and RVC",
            "c) FCC and RCC",
            "d) FCC and RVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FCC (Forward Control Channel) and RCC (Reverse Control Channel) are control channels responsible for initiating mobile calls."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Of the total channels present in the cellular system, what is the percentage of voice and control channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 95% voice channels, 5% control channels",
            "b) 5% voice channels, 95% control channels",
            "c) 50% voice channels, 50% control channels",
            "d) 25% voice channels, 75% control channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In each cellular system, control channels are 5% of the total channels available and remaining 95% are dedicated to voice and data traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "What is MIN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Subscriber’s telephone number",
            "b) Paging message",
            "c) Traffic request number",
            "d) Mobile Internet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MIN (Mobile Identification Number) is a 10 digit unique number which represents the telephone number of subscriber."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "What is transmitted along with the call initiation request during the origin of call by a mobile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MIN",
            "b) ESN",
            "c) ESN and SCM",
            "d) MIN, ESN and SCM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When a mobile originates the call, it sends the MIN (mobile identification number), ESN (electronic serial number) and SCM (station class mark) along with the call initiation request."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "What does SCM indicates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum receiver power level for a particular user",
            "b) Maximum transmitter power level for a particular user",
            "c) Minimum receiver power level for a particular user",
            "d) Minimum transmitter power level for a particular user"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SCM (Station Class Mark) indicates the maximum transmitter power level for a particular user."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the cell present in the cellular system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular",
            "b) Square",
            "c) Hexagonal",
            "d) Triangular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shape of the cell present in the cellular network is hexagonal since it can cover the entire geographical area without any gap and overlapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Why the size of the cell is kept small in cellular network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase capacity",
            "b) Decrease capacity",
            "c) Increased size of base station electronics",
            "d) Slow process of handoffs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The size of the cells in cellular network is kept small because of the need of high capacity in areas with high user density and reduced size and cost of base station electronics."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "What is handoff?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward channel",
            "b) Switching technique",
            "c) Roamer",
            "d) Guard channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Handoff is a switching technique which refers to the process of transferring an active call or data session from one cell in a cellular network to another."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which one is not an advantage of using frequency reuse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased capacity",
            "b) Limited spectrum is required",
            "c) Same spectrum may be allocated to other network",
            "d) Number of base stations is reduced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Frequency reuse is a technique of reusing frequencies and channels within a cellular system to improve capacity and spectral efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "The process of transferring a mobile station from one base station to another is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MSC",
            "b) Roamer",
            "c) Handoff",
            "d) Forward channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Handoff is the process of changing the channel associated with current connection while a call is in progress."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "The interference between the neighbouring base stations is avoided by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Assigning different group of channels",
            "b) Using transmitters with different power level",
            "c) Using different antennas",
            "d) Using different base stations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The interference between the neighbouring base stations is avoided by assigning different group of channels and reusing the same channel after a certain amount of distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following multiple access techniques are used by second generation cellular systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FDMA/FDD and TDMA/FDD",
            "b) TDMA/FDD and CDMA/FDD",
            "c) FDMA/FDD and CDMA/FDD",
            "d) FDMA/FDD only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: First generation cellular system used FDMA/FDD techniques. Second generation standards uses TDMA/FDD and CDMA/FDD multiple access techniques. 2G networks are digital."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which one is not a TDMA standard of second generation networks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) IS-136",
            "c) AMPS",
            "d) PDC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: GSM (Global System Mobile), IS-136 (Interim Standard 136) and PDC (Pacific Digital Cellular) are the three most popular TDMA standards of second generation. AMPS is a first generation standard."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a CDMA standard of second generation network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-95",
            "b) IS-136",
            "c) ETACS",
            "d) EDGE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Interim Standard 95 (IS-95) is the most popular CDMA standard of second generation networks. IS-136 is a TDMA standard of 2G. EDGE is a standard of 2.5G and ETACS is a 1G standard."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Popular 2G CDMA standard IS-95 is also known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CdmaOne",
            "b) CdmaTwo",
            "c) IS-136",
            "d) IS-95B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The popular 2G CDMA standard, Interim Standard (IS-95) is also known as CdmaOne. The 2.5G CDMA standard, IS-95B is called CdmaTwo. And IS-136 is a TDMA standard for 2G."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "How many users or voice channels are supported for each 200 KHz channel in GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eight",
            "b) Three",
            "c) Sixty four",
            "d) Twelve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GSM is a circuit switched system that divides each 200 KHz channel into eight 25 KHz time slots, i.e. each radio channel is divided into eight voice channels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "How many voice channels are supported for each 30 KHz radio channel in IS-136?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eight",
            "b) Thirty",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Sixteen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Interim Standard 136 (IS-136) was popularly known as North American Digital Cellular (NADC) system. It divides each 30 KHz radio channel into three time slots, each of 10 KHz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "How many users are supported in IS-95 for each 1.25 MHz?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eight",
            "b) Sixty four",
            "c) Sixteen",
            "d) Twenty five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS-95 supports upto 64 users which are orthogonally coded and simultaneously transmitted on each 1.25 MHz. The services of IS-95 standard are short messaging service, slotted paging, over-the-air activation, enhanced mobile station identities etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which modulation technique is used by GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GMSK",
            "b) BPSK",
            "c) QPSK",
            "d) GFSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GSM uses a form of modulation known as GMSK (Gaussian Minimum Shift Keying). It is a form of modulation with no phase discontinuities and provides data transmission with efficient spectrum usage."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "IS-95 uses which modulation technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GMSK",
            "b) BPSK",
            "c) QAM",
            "d) AFSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS- 95 uses BPSK (Binary Phase Shift Keying) with quadrature spreading. It is regarded as one of the most robust digital modulation technique and is used for long distance wireless communication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "IS-136 uses which modulation technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) π/4 DQPSK",
            "b) BPSK",
            "c) GMSK",
            "d) AFSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS-136 uses π/4 DQPSK modulation technique. This technique allows a bit rate of 48.6 Kbit/s with 30 KHz channel spacing which gives a bandwidth efficiency of 1.62 bit/s/Hz."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Which is one of the disadvantages of 2G standards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short Messaging Service (SMS)",
            "b) Digital modulation",
            "c) Limited capacity",
            "d) Limited Internet Browsing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 2G technologies use circuit switched data modems that limits data users to a single circuit switched voice channel. The advantages of 2G network are that they are digital in nature and supports SMS service."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "GSM (Global System for Mobile) was earlier also known as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group System Mobile",
            "b) Global Special Meaning",
            "c) Group Special Mobile",
            "d) Global Special Mobile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: GSM was earlier known as Group Special Mobile. As it became more global, the meaning of acronym was changed to Global System for Mobile."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "2G CDMA standard, IS-95, was proposed by which company?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nippon Telephone and Telegraph (NTT)",
            "b) Qualcomm",
            "c) Bellcore and Motorola",
            "d) AT&T Bell Laboratories"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS-95 was proposed by Qualcomm in early 1990s. Later it was adopted as a standard by Telecommunications Industry Association in TIA/EIA/IS-95 release published in 1995."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which one of the following 2G standard is used in Japan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-136",
            "b) GSM",
            "c) PDC",
            "d) AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PDC (Personal Digital Cellular) was standardized by Japanese Ministry of Posts and Telecommunication in 1991. It is similar to IS- 136, but with 25 KHz voice channels to be compatible with the Japanese analog channels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "The 2G GSM technology uses a carrier separation of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.25 MHz",
            "b) 200 KHz",
            "c) 30 KHz",
            "d) 300 KHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Global System for Mobile (GSM) uses a carrier separation of 200 KHz, each channel supporting upto eight users."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "What is the name of the web browsing format language supported by 2.5G technology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wireless Application Protocol",
            "b) Hypertext Markup Language",
            "c) Extensible Markup Language",
            "d) Hypertext Transfer Protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 2.5G technology supports a new web browsing format language, which is called Wireless Application Protocol (WAP). It allows standard web pages to be viewed in a compressed format specifically designed for small, portable hand held wireless devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "What is the name of the internet microbrowser technology used by NTT DoCoMo in Japan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wireless Application Protocol",
            "b) I-mode",
            "c).W-mode",
            "d) Hypertext Markup Language"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: I-mode is a wireless data service and Internet microbrowser technology introduced by NTT DoCoMo on its PDC network in 1998. It is currently used by other wireless services throughout the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a TDMA standard of 2.5G network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HSCSD",
            "b) GPRS",
            "c) EDGE",
            "d) GSM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As 2.5G is the upgradation of 2G technology, 2.5G upgradation path must match the original 2G technology. For example, 2.5G upgrade solution designed for GSM must dovetail with original GSM interface so that change of hardware is not required."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a 2.5G CDMA standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-95",
            "b) Cdma2000",
            "c) IS-95B",
            "d) CdmaOne"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GSM (Global System for Mobile) is a TDMA standard for 2G network. HSCSD (High Speed Circuit Switched Data), GPRS (General Packet Radio Service) and EDGE (Enhanced Data rates for GSM Evolution) are TDMA standards of 2.5G technology."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "HSCSD supports which 2G standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) IS-136",
            "c) GSM and IS-136",
            "d) PDC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS-95B (Interim Standard 95B) is code division multiple access standard for 2.5G. It is an upgradation of IS- 95 which is a second generation standard of CDMA."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "How does HSCSD differs from the GSM to obtain higher speed data rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By allowing single user to use one specific time slot",
            "b) By allowing single user to use consecutive user time slots",
            "c) By using 8-PSK modulation technique",
            "d) By allowing multiple users to use individual time slot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High Speed Circuit Switched Data (HSCDC) supports the Global system for Mobile (GSM) standard. It only requires a software upgrade at the base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "GPRS and EDGE supports which 2G standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM only",
            "b) IS-136 only",
            "c) GSM and IS-136 both",
            "d) PDC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HSCSD allows individual data users to use consecutive time slots in order to obtain higher speed data access on the GSM network. In case of GSM, it limits each user to use only one specific time slot."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "How is HSCSD different from GPRS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infrastructure",
            "b) Multiple Access Scheme",
            "c) Modulation technique",
            "d) Switching Technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: GPRS (General Packet Radio Service) network provides a packet network on dedicated GSM or IS-136 radio channels. EDGE (Enhanced Data rates for GSM Evolution) is also developed keeping in desire both GSM and IS-136 operators. "
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "What changes GPRS need to acquire while upgrading itself from GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A whole new base station",
            "b) New transceiver at base station",
            "c) New channel cards",
            "d) New packet overlay including routers and gateways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GPRS is a packet based network. HSCSD dedicates circuit switched channels to specific users whereas GPRS supports many more users, but in a bursty manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Which new modulation technique is used by EDGE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BPSK",
            "b) 8- PSK",
            "c) DQPSK",
            "d) AFSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GPRS requires a GSM operator to install new routers and Internet gateways at the base station along with new software upgrade. New base station RF hardware is not required."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Various air interface formats used by EDGE are also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation and coding schemes",
            "b) Coding schemes",
            "c) Modulating air interface",
            "d) Air interface coding schemes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: EDGE uses a new digital modulation format, 8- PSK (Octal Phase Shift Keying). It is used in addition to GSM’s standard GMSK (Gaussian Minimum Shift Keying) modulation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "EDGE is sometimes also referred as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HSCSD",
            "b) 3GPP",
            "c) EGPRS",
            "d) EGSCSD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EDGE allows nine different air interface formats known as multiple modulation and coding schemes (MCS). Each MCS state may use either GMSK or 8- PSK modulation for network access, depending upon the instantaneous demands of the network and the operating conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "What is one disadvantage of EDGE in comparison to HSCSD and GPRS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low data rates",
            "b) Small coverage range",
            "c) Low speed",
            "d) No advancement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: EDGE is sometimes also referred as Enhanced GPRS (EGPRS). It is an enhancement of a GSM network in which EDGE is introduced on top of the General Packet Radio Service (GPRS). It is used to transfer data in a packet switched mode on various time slots."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of 3G network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Communication over VoIP",
            "b) Unparalleled network capacity",
            "c) Multi-megabit Internet access",
            "d) LTE based network"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Multi-megabit Internet access, communication using Voice over internet Protocol (VoIP), voice activated calls, unparalleled network capacity are some of the characteristics of 3G network. 3G systems promise unparalleled wireless access which is not possible in 2G systems. LTE (Long term Evolution) is a standard of 4G systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "What is the term used by ITU for a set of global standards of 3G systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IMT 2000",
            "b) GSM",
            "c) CDMA",
            "d) EDGE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: International Telecommunications Union (ITU) used the term IMT-2000 in 1998. It is used for a set of global standards for third generation (3G) mobile telecoms services and equipment."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Which of the following leads to evolution of 3G networks in CDMA systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-95",
            "b) IS-95B",
            "c) CdmaOne",
            "d) Cdma2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 3G evolution of CDMA system leads to cdma2000. It is based on the fundamentals of IS-95 and IS-95B. IS-95 is a 2G standard for CDMA systems. IS-95B is a CDMA system for 2.5G networks."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which of the following leads to the 3G evolution of GSM, IS-136 and PDC systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) W-CDMA",
            "b) GPRS",
            "c) EDGE",
            "d) HSCSD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 3G evolution for GSM, IS-136 and PDC systems leads to W-CDMA (Wideband CDMA). It is based on the network fundamentals of GSM, as well as merged versions of GSM and IS-136 through EDGE. GPRS, EDGE and HSCSD are 2.5G networks."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "What is 3GPP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Project based on W-CDMA",
            "b) Project based on cdma2000",
            "c) Project based on 2G standards",
            "d) Project based on 2.5G standards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 3GPP is a 3G Partnership Project for Wideband CDMA standards based on backward compatibility with GSM and IS-136. The project was established in December 1998. Its initial scope was to make a globally applicable third generation mobile phone system."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "What is 3GPP2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Project based on W-CDMA",
            "b) Project based on cdma2000",
            "c) Project based on 2G standards",
            "d) Project based on 2.5G standards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 3GPP2 is a 3G Partnership Project for Cdma2000 standards based on backward compatibility with earlier CdmaOne 2G CDMA technology. It was initiated by IMT-2000 to cover high speed, broadband and Internet Protocol (IP) based mobile systems. It mainly focuses on North American and Asian regions."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a standard of 3G?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UMTS",
            "b) Cdma2000",
            "c) TD-SCDMA",
            "d) LTE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: UMTS (Universal Mobile Telecommunication System), TD-SCDMA (Time Division Synchronous Code Division Multiple Access), Cdma2000 are the standards defined for 3G networks. LTE (Long Term Evolution) is a 4G standard for high speed wireless communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which of the following 3G standard is used in Japan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdma2000",
            "b) TD-SCDMA",
            "c) UMTS",
            "d) UTRA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Japan uses UMTS (W-CDMA) standard for its 3G network. The standards used are UMTS 800, UMTS 900, UMTS 1500, UMTS 1700 and UMTS 2100. They are standardized by ARIB (Association of Radio industries and Business)."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "What does the number 2000 in IMT-2000 signifies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Year",
            "b) Number of subscribers per cell",
            "c) Number of cells",
            "d) Area (Km)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The International Telecommunication Union (ITU) defined the third generation (3G) of mobile telephony standards, IMT-2000 to facilitate growth, increase bandwidth, and support more diverse applications. The number 2000 in IMT-2000 indicates the start of the system (year 2000) and the spectrum used (around 2000 MHz). "
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of third generation network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Global Positioning System (GPS)",
            "b) Video conferencing",
            "c) Mobile TV",
            "d) Downloading rate upto 1 Gbps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 3G applications include GPS (Global Positioning System), MMS (Multimedia Messaging System), video conferencing, location based services, video on demand, wireless voice telephony and high data rates with peak downloading rate of 100 Mbps. For 4G networks, the peak downloading rate is 1 Gbps. "
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "What is the full form of UMTS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Universal Mobile Telephone System",
            "b) Ubiquitous Mobile Telephone System",
            "c) Ubiquitous Mobile Telemetry System",
            "d) Universal Machine Telemedicine System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: UMTS (Universal Mobile Telephone System) is a visionary air interface standard that was introduced in 1996. European carriers, manufacturers, and government regulators collectively developed the early version of UMTS as an open air interface standard for third generation wireless telecommunication."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "UMTS use which multiple access technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CDMA",
            "b) TDMA",
            "c) FDMA",
            "d) SDMA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Although UMTS is designed to operate on evolved GSM core networks, it uses code division multiple access (CDMA) for its air interface. The majority of the 3G systems in operation employ CDMA, while the rest use TDMA. CDMA allows various users to share a channel at the same time, while TDMA allows users to share the same channel by chopping it into different time slots."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "UMTS does not has backward compatibility with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) IS-136",
            "c) IS-95",
            "d) GPRS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: UMTS assures backward compatibility with the second generation GSM, IS-136 and PDC TDMA technologies. It is also compatible with all 2.5G TDMA techniques like GPRS and EDGE. But it does not provide compatibility to CDMA technologies of 2G and 2.5 G. IS-95 is a CDMA standard of 2G."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "UMTS is also known as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-95",
            "b) GPRS",
            "c) CdmaOne",
            "d) W-CDMA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: UMTS uses Wideband CDMA (W-CDMA) to carry the radio transmissions. Therefore, it is also referred as W-CDMA. W-CDMA offers greater spectral efficiency and bandwidth to mobile network operators."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What is the chip rate of W-CDMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2288 Mcps",
            "b) 3.84 Mcps",
            "c) 270.833 Ksps",
            "d) 100 Mcps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: W-CDMA uses a chip rate of 3.84 Mcps. Chip rate is the product of symbol rate and spreading factor. If the symbol rate is 960 Kbps and spreading factor is 4 for W-CDMA, then the chip rate is 3.84 Mcps. The chip rate for Cdma2000 and GSM are 1.2288 Mcps and 27.0833 Ksps respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "How much packet data rate per user is supported by W-CDMA if the user is stationary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.048 Kbps",
            "b) 100 Mbps",
            "c) 2.048 Mbps",
            "d) 1 Gbps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: W-CDMA works in both FDD and TDD mode. W-CDMA developed for wide area cellular coverage uses FDD. And TDD is used by W-CDMA for indoor cordless type applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "What is the minimum spectrum allocation required by W-CDMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 MHz",
            "b) 20MHz",
            "c) 1.25 MHz",
            "d) 200 KHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the user is stationary, W-CDMA supports packet data rates upto 2.048Mbps per user. Thus, it allows high quality data, multimedia, streaming audio video and broadcast type services to consumers. Future version of WCDMA will support stationary user data rates in excess of 8Mbps."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "How much increase in spectral efficiency is provided by W-CDMA in comparison to GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two times",
            "b) Three times",
            "c) No increase",
            "d) Six times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: W-CDMA/UMTS requires a minimum spectrum allocation of 5 MHz. Using this bandwidth, it has the capacity to carry over 100 simultaneous voice calls. It is able to carry data at speeds up to 2 Mbps in its original format. 20 MHz is the bandwidth defined for LTE. CdmaOne uses a bandwidth of 1.25 MHz. GSM’s bandwidth is 200 KHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following has no backward compatibility with 3G Cdma2000?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-95",
            "b) GPRS",
            "c) IS-95A",
            "d) IS-95B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  3G Cdma2000 is based on the original IS-95 and IS-95A CDMA standards, as well as the 2.5G IS-95B air interface. While upgrading, Cdma2000 maintains backward compatibility with existing IS-95, IS-95A and IS-95B equipments. Thus, Cdma2000 allow wireless carriers to introduce a family of new high data rate Internet access capabilities within existing systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following the first 3G CDMA air interface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-95",
            "b) IS-95B",
            "c) Cdma2000 1xRTT",
            "d) CdmaOne"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cdma2000 does not require change in entire base station or additional RF equipment. All the changes are made in software or in baseband hardware."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Within ITU IMT-2000 body, Cdma2000 1xRTT is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdma2000 1xEV-DO",
            "b) Cdma2000 1xEV-DV",
            "c) IS-95B",
            "d) G3G-MC-CDMA-1X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cdma2000 1xRTT is the first 3G air interface. Here, RTT stands for Radio Transmission Technology and 1x indicates that the bandwidth is one times that of the original CdmaOne channel. It is modulated on a single carrier."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "How many users are supported by Cdma2000 1X in comparison to 2G CDMA standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Half",
            "b) Twice",
            "c) Six times",
            "d) Ten times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cdma2000 1xRTT is also known as G3G-MC-CDMA-1X. The initials MC stand for multicarrier. RTT stand for Radio Transmission Technology, a language suggested by IMT-2000 body. Usually, MC and RTT are omitted for convenience."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of Cdma2000?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adaptable baseband signalling rates",
            "b) Adaptable baseband chipping rates",
            "c) Multicarrier technologies",
            "d) OFDMA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cdma2000 support up to twice as many users as the 2G CDMA standard. It also provides the two times the standby time for longer lasting battery life."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Cdma2000 1xEV was developed by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motorola",
            "b) AT&T Laboratories",
            "c) Qualcomm",
            "d) NTT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cdma2000 works in both FDD and TDD mode. Cdma2000 developed for wide area cellular coverage uses FDD. And TDD is used by Cdma2000 for indoor cordless type applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "How is bandwidth increased in Cdma2000?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clubbing adjacent radio channels",
            "b) Changing the hardware of base stations",
            "c) Change of spectrum",
            "d) Change of RF equipment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cdma2000 does not use OFDMA technique. OFDMA is used by 4G networks. Cdma2000 uses rapidly adaptable baseband signalling rates and chipping rates for each user. It also provides multi-level keying within same framework."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "What are the two options provided by Cdma2000 1xEV?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdma2000 1xRTT. Cdma2000 3xRTT",
            "b) Cdma2000 1xEV-DO, Cdma2000 1xEV-DV",
            "c) Cdma2000 1xEV-DT, Cdma2000 1xEV-DO",
            "d) Cdma2000 1xRTT, Cdma2000 1xEV-DV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cdma2000 is an evolutionary advancement for CDMA. It was developed by Qualcomm Inc. It is a proprietary high data rate (HDR) packet standard that can be overlaid upon existing IS-95, IS-95B and Cdma2000 networks."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not backward compatible with Cdma2000?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdma2000 1xRTT",
            "b) Cdma2000 3xRTT",
            "c) Cdma2000 1xEV-DO",
            "d) Cdma2000 1xEV-DT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The increase in the bandwidth is achieved through clubbing the adjacent radio channels of CdmaOne and using multicarrier technologies. For example, Cdma2000 3xRTT uses these technologies by combining three adjacent 1.25 MHz bandwidth of CdmaOne channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "What is the full form of WLAN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wide Local Area Network",
            "b) Wireless Local Area Network",
            "c) Wireless Land Access Network",
            "d) Wireless Local Area Node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: WLAN stands for Wireless Local Area Network. Wireless networks is increasingly used as a replacement for wires within homes, buildings, and office settings through the deployment of wireless local area networks (WLANs)."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "What is the name of 300 MHz of unlicensed spectrum allocated by FCC in ISM band?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UNII",
            "b) Unlicensed PCS",
            "c) Millimetre wave",
            "d) Bluetooth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: WLANs use low power and generally do not require a license for spectrum. They provide ad hoc high data transmission rate connections deployed by individuals. In the late 1980s, FCC provided licence free bands for low power spread spectrum devices in ISM band, which is used by WLAN. "
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which of the following specifies a set of media access control (MAC) and physical layer specifications for implementing WLANs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IEEE 802.16",
            "b) IEEE 802.3",
            "c) IEEE 802.11",
            "d) IEEE 802.15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FCC allocated 300 MHz of unlicensed spectrum in the ISM bands. This allocation is called the Unlicensed National Information Infrastructure (UNII) band. It was allocated for the express purpose of supporting low power license free spread spectrum data communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a standard of WLAN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HIPER-LAN",
            "b) HIPERLAN/2",
            "c) IEEE 802.11b",
            "d) AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IEEE 802.11 is a set of media access control and physical layer specification for implementing WLAN computer communication. It was founded in 1987 to begin standardization of spread spectrum WLANs for use in the ISM bands."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the 802.11 High Rate Standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IEEE 802.15",
            "b) IEEE 802.15.4",
            "c) IEEE 802.11g",
            "d) IEEE 802.11b"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: AMPS is a standard of first generation network. HIPERLAN is a WLAN standard developed in Europe in mid 1990s. HIPERLAN/2 is also developed in Europe that provides upto 54 Mbps of user data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Which of the following spread spectrum techniques were used in the original IEEE 802.11 standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FHSS and DSSS",
            "b) THSS and FHSS",
            "c) THSS and DSSS",
            "d) Hybrid technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IEEE 802.11b was a high rate standard approved in 1999. It provided new data rate capabilities of 11 Mbps, 5.5 Mbps in addition to the original 2 Mbps and 1 Mbps user rates of IEEE 802.11."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of the following WLAN standard has been named Wi-Fi?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IEEE 802.6",
            "b) IEEE 802.15.4",
            "c) DSSS IEEE 802.11b",
            "d) IEEE 802.11g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Original IEEE 802.11 used both the approaches of FHSS (Frequency Hopping Spread Spectrum) and DSSS (Direct Sequence Spread Spectrum). But from late 2001s, only DSSS modems are used within IEEE 802.11."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which of the following is developing CCK-OFDM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IEEE 802.11a",
            "b) IEEE 802.11b",
            "c) IEEE 802.15.4",
            "d) IEEE 802.11g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DSSS IEEE 802.11b standard has been named Wi-Fi by the Wireless Ethernet Compatibility Alliance. It is a group that promotes adoption of 802.11 DSSS WLAN."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "What is the data rate of HomeRF 2.0?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 Mbps",
            "b) 54 Mbps",
            "c) 200 Mbps",
            "d) 1 Mbps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IEEE 802.11g is developing CCK-OFDM (Complementary Code Keying Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing) standards. It will support roaming capabilities and dual band use for public WLAN networks. It also has backward compatibility with 802.11b technologies."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "HIPER-LAN stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High Precision Radio Local Area Network",
            "b) High Performance Radio Local Area Network",
            "c) High Precision Radio Land Area Network",
            "d) Huge Performance Radio Link Access Node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HomeRF 2.0 has data rate of the order of 10 Mbps. The FHSS proponents of IEEE 802.11 have formed the HomeRF standard that supports the frequency hopping equipment. In 2001, HomeRF developed a 10 Mbps FHSS standard called HomeRF 2.0."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "What is the range of asynchronous user data rates provided by HIPER-LAN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-100 Mbps",
            "b) 50-100 Mbps",
            "c) 1-20 Mbps",
            "d) 500 Mbps to 1 Gbps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HIPER-LAN stands for High Performance Radio Local Area Network. It was developed in Europe in mid 1990s. It was intended to provide individual wireless LANs for computer communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "What is the name of the European WLAN standard that provides user data rate upto 54 Mbps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UNII",
            "b) WISP",
            "c) MMAC",
            "d) HIPERLAN/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: HIPER-LAN provides asynchronous user data rates of between 1 to 20 Mbps, as well as time bounded messaging of rates of 64 kbps to 2.048 Mbps. It uses 5.2 GHz and 17.1 GHz frequency bands."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is WISP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wideband Internet Service Protocol",
            "b) Wireless Internet Service Provider",
            "c) Wireless Instantaneous Source Provider",
            "d) Wideband Internet Source Protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: HIPERLAN/2 has emerged as the next generation European WLAN standard. It provides upto 54 Mbps of user data to a variety of networks. The networks includes the ATM backbone, IP based networks and the UMTS network."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an open standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bluetooth",
            "b) WWW",
            "c) HTML",
            "d) VPN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An open standard is a standard that is publicly available. It has various rights to use associated with it. Bluetooth is an open standard that has been embraced by over thousand manufacturers of electronic appliances. VPN (Virtual Private Network) is a private network."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "What is the nominal range of Bluetooth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 Km",
            "b) 10 m",
            "c) 1 m",
            "d) 10 Km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The power of the transmitter governs the range over which a Bluetooth device can operate. Generally, Bluetooth devices are said to fall into one of three classes. The most common kind is class 2, and it operates in 10 m range."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Bluetooth standard is named after ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) King Ronaldo Bluetooth",
            "b) Pope Vincent Bluetooth",
            "c) King Herald Bluetooth",
            "d) Pope Francis Bluetooth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bluetooth standard is named after King Harald Bluetooth. He was the 10th century Viking who united Denmark and Norway. The Bluetooth standard aims to unify the connectivity chores of appliances within the personal workspace of an individual."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Bluetooth operates in which band?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ka Band",
            "b) L Band",
            "c) Ku Band",
            "d) 2.4 GHz ISM Band"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bluetooth is a radio technology operating in 2.4 GHz frequency band. Bluetooth is best suited for low-bandwidth applications like transferring sound data with telephones (i.e. with a Bluetooth headset) or byte data with hand-held computers (transferring files) or keyboard."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Which of the following scheme is used by Bluetooth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency hopping TDD scheme",
            "b) Frequency hopping FDD scheme",
            "c) DSSS TDD scheme",
            "d) DSSS FDD scheme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency hopping TDD (Time Division Duplexing) scheme is used by Bluetooth. Frequency hopping provides a form of multiple access among co-located devices in different piconets."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "What is the range of time slot in Bluetooth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 milliseconds",
            "b) 625 microseconds",
            "c) 577 microseconds",
            "d) 5.7 seconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bluetooth uses a timeslot of 625 microseconds. A data channel hops randomly 1600 times per second between 79 RF channels. Thus, each channel is divided into time slots 625 microseconds."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Which modulation scheme is used by Bluetooth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DQPSK",
            "b) MSK",
            "c) GFSK",
            "d) BPSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bluetooth uses GFSK (Gaussian Frequency Shift Keying). When GFSK is used for Bluetooth modulation, the frequency of the carrier is shifted to carry the modulation. By doing this the Bluetooth modulation achieves a bandwidth of 1 MHz with stringent filter requirements to prevent interference on other channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What is the channel symbol rate in Bluetooth for each user?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 270.833 Kbps",
            "b) 1 Gbps",
            "c) 100 Mbps",
            "d) 1 Mbps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Each user in Bluetooth uses a radio channel symbol rate of 1 Mbps using GFSK modulation. The frequency hopping scheme of each Bluetooth user is determined from a cyclic code with a length of 1027-1."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "What is the raw channel bit error rate of Bluetooth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-3",
            "b) 10-10",
            "c) 103",
            "d) 10-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bluetooth has a bit error rate (BER) of 10-3. Bluetooth uses a number of forward error control (FEC) coding and automatic repeat request (ARR) schemes to achieve this bit rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which of the following standard committee specifies Bluetooth and other Personal Area Networks (PAN)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IEEE 802.11b",
            "b) IEEE 802.15",
            "c) IEEE 802.11g",
            "d) IEEE 802.16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IEEE 802.15 standards committee is formed to provide an international forum for developing Bluetooth and other PANs. PANs are used to interconnect pocket PCs, personal digital assistants (PDAs), cell phones, light projectors and other appliances."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Why neighbouring stations are assigned different group of channels in cellular system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To minimize interference",
            "b) To minimize area",
            "c) To maximize throughput",
            "d) To maximize capacity of each cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cellular concept is a system level idea that replaces a single high power transmitter to many low power transmitters. High power transmitters lead to large cell, and thus it was impossible to use the same frequencies throughout the systems. But, it is possible with low power transmitter."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "What is a cell in cellular system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A group of cells",
            "b) A group of subscribers",
            "c) A small geographical area",
            "d) A large group of mobile systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Neighbouring base stations are assigned different group of channels. It minimizes the interference between base stations and the users under their control."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "What is frequency reuse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process of selecting and allocating channels",
            "b) Process of selection of mobile users",
            "c) Process of selecting frequency of mobile equipment",
            "d) Process of selection of number of cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cell is a small geographic area in a cellular system. Each cellular base station within a cell is allocated a group of radio channels that could be used in another cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a universally adopted shape of cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square",
            "b) Circle",
            "c) Triangle",
            "d) Hexagon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency reuse is the process of using the same radio frequencies on radio transmitter sites within a geographic area. They are separated by sufficient distance to cause minimal interference with each other. "
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Actual radio coverage of a cell is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fingerprint",
            "b) Footprint",
            "c) Imprint",
            "d) Matrix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hexagonal cell shape is a simplistic model of radio coverage for each base station. It has been universally adopted since the hexagon permits easy and manageable analysis of a cellular system."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Why the shape of cell is not circle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Omni directionality",
            "b) Small area",
            "c) Overlapping regions or gaps are left",
            "d) Complex design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Actual radio coverage of a cell is known as the footprint. It is determined from field measurements or propagation prediction models. Although the real footprint is amorphous in nature, a regular cell shape is needed for systematic system design."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "What is the main reason to adopt hexagon shape in comparison to square and triangle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Largest area",
            "b) Simple design",
            "c) Small area",
            "d) Single directional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Circle is the first natural choice to represent the coverage area of a base station. But while adopting this shape, adjacent cells cannot be overlaid upon a map without leaving gaps or creating overlapping regions."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Which type of antenna is used for center excited cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dipole antenna",
            "b) Grid antenna",
            "c) Sectored antenna",
            "d) Omnidirectional antenna"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a given distance between the center of a polygon and its farthest perimeter points, the hexagon has the largest area. Thus, by using the hexagon geometry, the fewest number of cells can cover a geographic region. "
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which type of antenna is used for edge excited cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Omnidirectional antenna",
            "b) Grid antenna",
            "c) Sectored directional antenna",
            "d) Dipole antenna"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For center excited cells, base station transmitters are used at the center of cell. To cover the whole cell, omnidirectional antenna is the best choice for base station transmitters."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "For a cellular system, if there are N cells and each cell is allocated k channel. What is the total number of available radio channels, S?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S=k*N",
            "b) S=k/N",
            "c) S=N/k",
            "d) S=kN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For edge excited cell, mostly base station transmitters are placed on three of the six cell vertices. To cover the assigned portion of a cell, sectored directional antenna is the best choice."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "What is a cluster in a cellular system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group of frequencies",
            "b) Group of cells",
            "c) Group of subscribers",
            "d) Group of mobile systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If there is a cellular system with total of S duplex channels. Each cell is allocated a group of k channels and there are total N cells in the system, S channels are divide among N cells into unique and disjoint channel groups. Therefore, total number of radio channel is the product of total number of cells in the system (N) and number of channel allocated to each cell (k)."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "What is a frequency reuse factor for N number of cells in a system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) N",
            "b) N2",
            "c) 2*N",
            "d) 1/N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cluster is group of N cells. These cells use the complete set of frequency available for the cellular system at that location."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Capacity of a cellular system is directly proportional to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of cells",
            "b) Number of times a cluster is replicated",
            "c) Number of Base stations",
            "d) Number of users"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The frequency reuse factor is defined as 1 over the number of cells in the cluster of the system (N). It is given by 1/N since each cell within a cluster is only assigned 1/N of the total available channels in the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "A spectrum of 30 MHz is allocated to a cellular system which uses two 25 KHz simplex channels to provide full duplex voice channels. What is the number of channels available per cell for 4 cell reuse factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 channels",
            "b) 600 channels",
            "c) 50 channels",
            "d) 85 channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacity of a cellular system is directly proportional to the number of times a cluster is replicated in a fixed area. If the cluster size N is reduced while the cell size is kept constant, more clusters are required to cover a given area, and hence more capacity is achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an objective for channel assignment strategies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficient utilization of spectrum",
            "b) Increase of capacity",
            "c) Minimize the interference",
            "d) Maximize the interference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The objective of channel assignment strategy is to utilize the spectrum efficiently. And for efficient utilization, a frequency reuse scheme consistent with the objective of increasing capacity and minimizing interference is required."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "In fixed channel assignment strategy, each cell is allocated a predetermined set of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voice channels",
            "b) Control channels",
            "c) Frequency",
            "d) base stations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The choice of channel assignment strategy impacts the performance of the system. Particularly as to how calls are managed, when a mobile user is handed off from one cell to another."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "What happen to a call in fixed channel strategy, if all the channels in a cell are occupied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Queued",
            "b) Cross talk",
            "c) Blocked",
            "d) Delayed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a foxed channel strategy, each cell is allocated a predetermined set of voice channels. Any call attempt within the cell can only be served by the unused channels in that particular cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "What is a borrowing strategy in fixed channel assignments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Borrowing channels from neighbouring cell",
            "b) Borrowing channels from neighbouring cluster",
            "c) Borrowing channels from same cell",
            "d) Borrowing channels from other base station in same cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As any call attempt within a cell can be served by unused channels in fixed channel strategy. If all the channels in that cell are occupied, the call is blocked and subscriber does not receive any service."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "In dynamic channel assignment strategy, base station requests channel from ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MSC",
            "b) Neighbouring cell",
            "c) Neighbouring cluster",
            "d) Neighbouring base station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In borrowing strategy, a cell is allowed to borrow channels from a neighbouring cell if all of its own channels are already occupied. The MSC supervises such borrowing procedure and ensures that the borrowing of channel does not interfere with any call in progress."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "RSSI stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Received Signal Strength Indicator",
            "b) Restricted Signal Strength Indicator",
            "c) Radio Signal Strength Indication",
            "d) Restricted System Software Indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a dynamic channel strategy, voice channels are not allocated to different cells permanently. Instead, serving base station requests a channel from MSC each time a cell request is made."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "What is the drawback of dynamic channel assignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease channel utilization",
            "b) Increase probability of blocked call",
            "c) Cross talk",
            "d) Increase storage and computational load on system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each time a call request is made, the serving base station requests a channel from the MSC. The switch then allocates a channel to the requested cell following an algorithm that takes into account the likelihood of future blocking within the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "What is the condition for handoff?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A mobile moves into a different cell while in conversation",
            "b) A mobile remains in the same cell while in conversation",
            "c) A mobile moves to different cell when idle",
            "d) A mobile remains in the same cell and is idle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Handoff occurs when a mobile moves into a different cell while a conversation is in progress. The MSC automatically transfers the call to a new channel belonging to the new base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "The time over which a call can be maintained within a cell without handoff is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Run time",
            "b) Peak time",
            "c) Dwell time",
            "d) Cell time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Handoff operation involves identifying a new base station. It also requires that the voice and control signal be allocated to channels associated with the new base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Dwell time does not depend on which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propagation",
            "b) Interference",
            "c) Distance between subscriber and base station",
            "d) Mobile station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The time over which a call is maintained within a cell without handoff is called as dwell time. Dwell time vary depending on speed of user and type of radio coverage. "
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Which of the following is associated with the handoff in first generation analog cellular systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Locator receiver",
            "b) MAHO",
            "c) Cell dragging",
            "d) Breathing cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dwell time of a particular user is governed by a number of factors. They include propagation, interference, distance between the subscriber and the base station, and other time varying effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "MAHO stands for ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) MSC assisted handoff",
            "b) Mobile assisted handoff",
            "c) Machine assisted handoff",
            "d) Man assisted handoff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Locator receiver is a spare receiver in each base station. It is used to scan and determine signal strengths of mobile users which are in neighbouring cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "What is the condition for intersystem interference?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mobile moves from one cell to another cell",
            "b) Mobile remains in the same cell",
            "c) Mobile moves from one cellular system to another cellular system",
            "d) Mobile remains in the same cluster"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MAHO stands for mobile assisted handoff. In 2G systems, handoff decisions are mobile assisted. In MAHO, every mobile station measure the received power from surrounding base station and continuously reports the results to serving base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "What is the disadvantage of guard channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficient utilization of spectrum",
            "b) Cross talk",
            "c) Near far effect",
            "d) Reduce total carried traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MAHO measures the power received from the surrounding base station. And a handoff is initiated when the power received from the base station of a neighbouring cell begins to exceed the power received from current base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following priority handoff method decrease the probability of forced termination of a call due to lack of available channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Queuing",
            "b) Guard channel",
            "c) Cell dragging",
            "d) Near far effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An intersystem handoff is initiated when a mobile moves from one cellular system to another during a course of a call. An MSC engages in an intersystem interference when a mobile becomes weak in a given cell and MSC cannot find another cell to which call can be transferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Umbrella cell approach is possible by using _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antenna of same heights",
            "b) Antenna of different heights",
            "c) Different voice channels",
            "d) Different control channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Guard channel is a concept for handling priority in handoff. Here, a fraction of the total available channels in a cell is reserved exclusively for handoff requests from ongoing calls. This method has the disadvantage of reducing the total carried traffic, as fewer channels are allocated to originating calls."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Cell dragging is a problem occur due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestrian users",
            "b) Stationary users",
            "c) High speed mobile systems",
            "d) Base stations having same frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Queuing of handoff requests is a method to decrease the probability of forced termination of a call due to lack of available channels. Queuing of handoff is possible due to the fact that there is a finite time interval between the time the received signal level drops below the handoff threshold and the time the call is terminated."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "What was the typical handoff time in first generation analog cellular systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 second",
            "b) 10 seconds",
            "c) 1 minute",
            "d) 10 milliseconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Umbrella cell approach is possible by using different antenna heights and different power levels. By using this approach, it is possible to provide large and small cells which are co-located at a single location."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "How much time it takes for handoff in digital cellular systems like GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 second",
            "b) 10 seconds",
            "c) 1 minute",
            "d) 10 milliseconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell dragging is a practical handoff problem in microcell system. It results from pedestrian users that provide a very strong signal to the base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Soft handoff is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAHO",
            "b) Hand over",
            "c) Break before make",
            "d) Make before break"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In first generation analog cellular system, the typical time to make a handoff once the signal level is below the threshold, is about 10 seconds. This requires the value for threshold to be 6 dB to 12 dB."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a source of interference?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base station in a different cluster",
            "b) Another mobile in same cell",
            "c) A call in progress in neighbouring cell",
            "d) Any BS operating on same frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Interference is a major limiting factor in the performance of cellular radio systems. Sources of interference includes another mobile in the same cell, a call in progress in neighbouring cell, other base stations operating in the same frequency band, or any non-cellular system which inadvertently leaks energy into the cellular frequency band."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Interference on voice channels causes _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blocked calls",
            "b) Cross talk",
            "c) Queuing",
            "d) Missed calls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Interference on voice channels causes crass talk. Here, the subscriber hears interference in the background due to an undesired transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Interference in control channel leads to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cross talk",
            "b) Queuing",
            "c) Blocked calls",
            "d) Voice traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On control channels, interference leads to missed and blocked calls. This happens due to errors in the digital signalling."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "What are co-channel cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cells having different base stations",
            "b) Cells using different frequency",
            "c) Cells using adjacent frequency",
            "d) Cells using same frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Interference is more severe in rural areas. It happens due to the greater RF noise floor and the large number of base stations and mobiles."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Co-channel interference is a function of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radius of cell",
            "b) Transmitted power",
            "c) Received power",
            "d) Frequency of mobile user"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to frequency reuse concept, there are several cells that use the same set of frequencies. These cells are called co-channel cells. And the interference between these cells is called co-channel interference."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Co-channel reuse ratio is define by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q=D*R",
            "b) Q=D/R",
            "c) Q=D^R",
            "d) Q=1/R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the case when the size of each cell is approximately the same and the base stations transmit the same power. Co-channel interference ratio is independent of the transmitted power and becomes a function of the radius of the cell ® and the distance between centers of the nearest co channel cell (D)."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "Co-channel ratio in terms of cluster size is defined as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt{(3N)}\\) ",
            "b) N",
            "c) 3N",
            "d) √N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Co-channel reuse ratio is defined by Q=D/R. By increasing the ratio of D/R, the spatial separation between co-channel cells relative to the coverage distance of a cell is increased. Thus, interference I reduced from improved isolation of RF energy from the co-channel cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "What is the cluster size for CDMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) N=10",
            "b) N=100",
            "c) N=1",
            "d) N=50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Co-channel reuse is defined using \\(\\sqrt{(3N)}\\). A small value of Q provides larger capacity since the cluster size N is small. However, a large value of Q improves the transmission quality, due to smaller level of co-channel interference."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "What is breathing cell effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed coverage region",
            "b) Dynamic and time varying coverage region",
            "c) Large coverage region",
            "d) Very small coverage region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CDMA systems have a cluster size of N=1.Therefore, frequency reuse is not as difficult as for TDMA or first generation cellular systems. "
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Adjacent channel interference occurs due to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power transmitted by Base station",
            "b) MSCs",
            "c) Same frequency of mobile users",
            "d) Imperfect receiver filters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Breathing cell is a concept used by CDMA systems. They had a dynamic, time varying coverage region which varies depending on the instantaneous number of users on the CDMA radio channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following problem occur due to adjacent channel interference?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blocked calls",
            "b) Cross talk",
            "c) Near-far effect",
            "d) Missed calls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Interference resulting from signals which are adjacent in frequency to the desired signal is called adjacent channel interference. It results from imperfect receiver filters which allow nearby frequencies to leak into the passband."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "In near-far effect, a nearby transmitter captures the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Receiver of the subscriber",
            "b) Transmitter of the subscriber",
            "c) Nearby MSC",
            "d) Neighbouring base station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One of the main problems with adjacent channel interference is the near-far effect. It occurs when a mobile close to a base station transmits on a channel close to one being used by a weak mobile."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Adjacent channel interference can be minimized through _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Changing frequency of base stations",
            "b) Careful filtering and channel assignments",
            "c) Increasing number of base stations",
            "d) Increasing number of control channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Near-far effect occurs if an adjacent channel user is transmitting in very close range to a subscriber’s receiver while the receiver attempts to receive a base station on the desired channel. In this effect, a nearby transmitter captures the receiver of the subscriber."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What is the concept for accommodating a large number of users in a limited radio spectrum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grade of service",
            "b) Trunking",
            "c) Multiplexing",
            "d) Multitasking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cellular radio systems rely on trunking to accommodate a large number of users in a limited radio spectrum. The concept of trunking allows a large number of users to share the relatively small number of channels in a cell by providing access to each user, on demand."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Who developed the fundamental of trunking theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Newton",
            "b) Ohm",
            "c) Erlang",
            "d) Einstein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a trunked radio system, each user is allocated a channel on a per call basis. Upon termination of the call, the previously occupied channel is immediately returned to the pool of available channels. It is a method for a system to provide network access to many clients by sharing a set of lines or frequencies instead of providing them individually."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "What is the unit for the measure of traffic intensity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meters",
            "b) Henry",
            "c) Ohm",
            "d) Erlang"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a trunked mobile radio system when a particular user requests service, there is a possibility that all the channels are already in use. Then the user is blocked, or denied access to the system. Sometimes, a queue may be used to hold the requesting users until a channel becomes available."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "One Erlang represents _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One call- hour per hour",
            "b) One call-minute per hour",
            "c) One call- hour per minute",
            "d) Many calls- hour per hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The fundamentals of trunking theory were developed by Erlang. He was a Danish mathematician. He embarked on the study of how a large population could be accommodated by a limited number of servers in late 19th century."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "What is the measure of the ability of user to access a trunked system during the busiest hour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trunking",
            "b) Grade of Service (GOS)",
            "c) Multiplexing",
            "d) Sectoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The measure of traffic intensity is given by Erlang. It is defined as the ratio of the time during which a facility is cumulatively occupied to the time this facility is available for occupancy. Telecommunication operators are vitally interested in traffic intensity as it dictates the amount of equipment they must supply."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "GOS is typically given as a likelihood that a ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Call is in progress",
            "b) Channels are busy",
            "c) Call is blocked",
            "d) Channel are free"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One Erlang represents the amount of traffic intensity carried by a channel that is completely occupied (i.e. one call- hour per hour or one call- minute per minute). For example, a radio channel that is occupied for 30 minutes during an hour carries 0.5 Erlangs of traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "The time requires to allocate a trunked radio channel to a requesting user is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dwell time",
            "b) Holding time",
            "c) Run time",
            "d) Set up Time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The grade of service (GOS) is a measure of the ability of a user to access a trunked system during the busiest hour. The busy hour is based upon customer demand at the busiest hour during a week, month or a year. "
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Average duration of a typical call is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Holding time",
            "b) Dwell time",
            "c) Set up time",
            "d) Run time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: GOS is typically given as the likelihood that a call is blocked or the likelihood of a call experiencing a delay greater than a certain queuing time. It is the wireless designer’s job to estimate the maximum required capacity used to allocate the proper number of channels in order to meet GOS."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "The average number of call requests per unit time is also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Request rate",
            "b) Load",
            "c) Grade o Service",
            "d) Traffic intensity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When any user makes a call request, the time required to allocate a trunked channel to a user is known as set up time. TETREA (Terrestrial Trunked Radio) call set up time is 0.3 seconds. GSM uses a call set up time of several seconds."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Traffic intensity offered by each user is the product of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set up time and holding time",
            "b) Call request rate and holding time",
            "c) Load and holding time",
            "d) Call request rate and set up time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Average time of a typical call is called holding time. It is denoted by H (in seconds). It is used to measure the traffic intensity per user. The time over which a call may be maintained within a cell, without handoff is called dwell time."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "AMPS cellular system is designed for a GOS of _____ blocking.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 50 %",
            "c) 2%",
            "d) 1%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Request rate is the average number of call requests per unit time. It is denoted by λ. Unit for request rate is second-1. It can also be defined as the ratio of traffic intensity of each user and the holding time."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Blocked calls cleared formula is also known as _______ formula.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erlang C",
            "b) Erlang A",
            "c) Erlang D",
            "d) Erlang B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The traffic intensity offered by each user is equal to the call request rate multiplied by the holding time. Each user generates a traffic intensity A=λH Erlang. Here, H is the average duration of a call and λ is the average number of call requests per unit time for each user."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Blocked calls delayed formula is also known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erlang A",
            "b) Erlang B",
            "c) Erlang C",
            "d) Erlang D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The AMPS (Advanced Mobile Phone System) cellular system is designed for a GOS of 2% blocking. This implies that the channel allocations for cell sites are designed so that 2 out of 100 calls will be blocked due to channel occupancy during the busiest hour."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques do not help in expanding the capacity of cellular system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sectoring",
            "b) Scattering",
            "c) Splitting",
            "d) Microcell zone concept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the demand for wireless service increases, the number of channels assigned to a call eventually becomes insufficient to support the required number of user. Techniques such as cell splitting, sectoring and coverage zone approaches are used in practice to expand the capacity of cellular system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "________ uses directional antennas to control interference.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sectoring",
            "b) Cell splitting",
            "c) Repeaters",
            "d) Micro cell zone concept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sectoring uses directional antenna to further control the interference and frequency reuse of channels. By decreasing the cell radius R and keeping the co-channel reuse ratio D/R unchanged, cell splitting increases the number of channels per unit area."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "_______ allows an orderly growth of cellular system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sectoring",
            "b) Scattering",
            "c) Cell splitting",
            "d) Micro cell zone technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cell splitting allows an orderly growth of cellular system. By defining new cells which have a smaller radius than the original cells, capacity increases due to additional number of channels per unit area."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Which of the following technology distributes the coverage of the cell and extends the cell boundary to hard-to-reach places?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell splitting",
            "b) Scattering",
            "c) Sectoring",
            "d) Micro cell zone concept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Micro cell zone concept distributes the coverage of the cell and extends the cell boundary to hard-to reach places. It is the solution for the problem of increased number of handoffs when sectoring which results in an increase of load on switching."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following increases the number of base stations in order to increase capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell splitting",
            "b) Sectoring",
            "c) Repeaters",
            "d) Micro cell zone concept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell splitting increases the number of base stations in order to increase capacity. Whereas, sectoring and zone microcells rely on base station antenna placements to improve capacity by reducing co-channel interference."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following trunking inefficiencies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell splitting",
            "b) Micro cell zone technique",
            "c) Sectoring",
            "d) Repeaters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sectored cells experience trunking inefficiencies. Cell splitting and zone micro cell techniques do not suffer the trunking inefficiencies experienced by sectored cells. They enable the base station to oversee all handoff chores related to microcells, thus reducing the computational load at MSC."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "The process of subdividing a congested cell into smaller cells is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell splitting",
            "b) Sectoring",
            "c) Micro cell technique",
            "d) Repeaters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell splitting is the process of subdividing a congested cell into smaller cells. Each small cell has its own base station and a there is a corresponding reduction in antenna height and transmitter power. "
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Cell splitting increases the capacity of a cellular system since it increases the number of times ________ are reused.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cells",
            "b) Channels",
            "c) Transmitters",
            "d) Mobile stations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cell splitting increases the capacity of a cellular system since it increases the number of times channels are reused. But it has a limitation that handoffs are more frequent and channel assignments become more difficult."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Which of the following technique is used to limit radio coverage of newly formed microcells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sectoring",
            "b) Splitting",
            "c) Antenna downtilting",
            "d) Scattering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cell splitting allows a system to grow by replacing large cells with smaller cells. It does not upset the channel allocation scheme required to maintain the minimum co channel reuse ratio Q between co-channel cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which of the following has range extension capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sectoring",
            "b) Repeaters",
            "c) Scattering",
            "d) Micro cell zone concept"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Antenna downtilting deliberately focuses radiated energy from the base station toward the ground (rather than toward the horizon). It is often used to limit the radio coverage of newly formed microcells."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Repeaters has one drawback of reradiating ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency",
            "b) Channels",
            "c) Power",
            "d) Repeater noise and interference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sectoring increases SIR so that cluster size may be reduced. SIR is improved using directional antenna. And then capacity improvement is achieved by reducing the number of cells in a cluster, thus increasing the frequency reuse. "
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of micro cell zone technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduced co channel interference",
            "b) Improved signal quality",
            "c) Increase in capacity",
            "d) Increasing number of base stations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wireless operator needs to provide dedicated coverage for hard-to-reach areas, such as within buildings, or in valleys or tunnels. Radio transmitters used to provide such range extension capabilities are called as repeaters. They are bidirectional in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "In a micro cell zone concept, when a mobile travels from one zone to another within the cell, it retains the same _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power level",
            "b) Base station",
            "c) Channel",
            "d) Receiver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Upon receiving signals from a base station forward link, the repeater amplifies and reradiates the base station signals to the specific coverage region. Unfortunately, the received noise and interference is also reradiated by repeater on both the forward and reverse link."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "The mechanism behind electromagnetic wave propagation cannot be attributed to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflection",
            "b) Diffraction",
            "c) Scattering",
            "d) Sectoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The mechanisms behind electromagnetic wave propagation are diverse. They can be greatly attributed to reflection, diffraction and scattering. Due to multiple reflections from various objects, the electromagnetic waves travel along different paths of varying lengths."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The propagation model that estimates radio coverage of a transmitter is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large scale propagation model",
            "b) Small scale propagation model",
            "c) Fading model",
            "d) Okumura model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Large scale propagation model are useful in estimating the radio coverage area of a transmitter. They can predict the mean signal strength for an arbitrary transmitter-receiver (T-R) separation distance. They characterize signal strength over large T-R separation distances."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Propagation model that characterize rapid fluctuation is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hata model",
            "b) Fading model",
            "c) Large scale propagation model",
            "d) Okumura model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fading models characterize the rapid fluctuations of the received signal strength over very short travel distance (a few wavelengths) or shot time durations (on the order of seconds)."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Small scale propagation model is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fading model",
            "b) Micro scale propagation model",
            "c) Okumura model",
            "d) Hata model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Small scale propagation model is also called fading model. Fading model characterize the rapid fluctuations of the received signal strength over very short distance of a few wavelengths or short time duration. The propagation models are used to estimate the performance of wireless channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Free space propagation model is to predict ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Received signal strength",
            "b) Transmitted power",
            "c) Gain of transmitter",
            "d) Gain of receiver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Free space propagation model predicts the received signal strength when there is an unobstructed line of sight path between transmitter and receiver. It assumes the ideal propagation condition that the environment is empty between the transmitter and receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Which of the following do not undergo free space propagation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Satellite communication system",
            "b) Microwave line of sight radio links",
            "c) Wireless line of sight radio links",
            "d) Wired telephone systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: EM signals when traveling through wireless channels experience fading effects due to various effects. But in some cases the transmission is with no obstruction and direct line of sight such as in satellite communication, microwave and wireless line of sight radio links."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "The free space model predicts that received signal decays as a function of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gain of transmitter antenna",
            "b) T-R separation",
            "c) Power of transmitter antenna",
            "d) Effective aperture of the antenna"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As with most large scale radio wave propagation models, the free space model predicts that received signal decays as a function of the T-R separation distance raised to some power. Often it is given as a function of negative square root of the distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Relation between gain and effective aperture is given by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) G=(4πAe)/λ2",
            "b) G=(4π λ2)/Ae",
            "c) G=4πAe",
            "d) G=Ae/λ2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gain of the antenna is proportional to effective aperture area. Therefore, antennas with large effective apertures are high gain antennas and have small angular beam widths. Most of their power is radiated in a narrow beam in one direction, and little in other directions."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Relation between wavelength and carrier frequency is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) λ=c/f",
            "b) λ=c*f",
            "c) λ=f/c",
            "d) λ=1/f"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wavelength is inversely proportional to carrier frequency. For electromagnetic radiation in free space, wavelength is a ratio of speed of light (c) and carrier frequency (f). Speed of light is 3*108 m/s. The unit for wavelength is meters."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Which of the following antenna radiates power with unit gain uniformly in all directions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directional antenna",
            "b) Dipole antenna",
            "c) Isotropic antenna",
            "d) Loop antenna"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Isotropic antenna radiates the power with unit gain uniformly in all directions. It is an ideal antenna. From practical point of view, there is no actual isotropic antenna. But, an isotropic antenna is often used as a reference antenna for the antenna gain."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "EIRP is abbreviated as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective isotropic radiated power",
            "b) Effective isotropic radio power",
            "c) Effective and immediate radiated power",
            "d) Effective and immediate ratio of power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EIRP stands for Effective Isotropic Radiated Power. It is the amount of power that a theoretical isotropic antenna would emit to produce the peak power density observed in the direction of maximum antenna gain. EIRP also takes into account the losses in transmission line and connectors and includes the gain of the antenna. "
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Path loss in free space model is defined as difference of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective transmitted power and gain",
            "b) Effective received power and distance between T-R",
            "c) Gain and received power",
            "d) Effective transmitter power and receiver power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: I Path loss is defined as difference of effective transmitter power and receiver power. Free-space path loss is the loss in signal strength of an electromagnetic wave that would result from a line-of-sight path through free space, with no obstacles nearby to cause reflection or diffraction."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Far field region is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Near field region",
            "b) Fraunhofer region",
            "c) Erlang region",
            "d) Fresnel region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The far field is the region far from the antenna. In this region, the radiation pattern does not change shape with distance. Also, this region is dominated by radiated fields, with the E- and H-fields orthogonal to each other and the direction of propagation as with plane waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Fraunhofer distance is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2D2/λ",
            "b) 2D/λ",
            "c) D/λ",
            "d) 2D/λ2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fraunhofer distance, also known as far field distance is inversely proportional to wavelength. It depends on the largest physical dimension of the antennal (D). This distance basically denotes the boundary between far field and near field region."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of the following is called an ideal antenna?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dipole antenna",
            "b) Directional antenna",
            "c) Isotropic antenna",
            "d) Loop antenna"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Isotropic antenna is an ideal antenna that directs the power uniformly in all directions. It is a theoretical point source of electromagnetic. It is practically not possible. It is mainly used as a hypothetical antenna to measure the gain."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of the following mechanism do not impact propagation in mobile communication system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflection",
            "b) Diffraction",
            "c) Scattering",
            "d) Refraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reflection, diffraction and scattering are the three basic propagation mechanism which impact propagation in mobile communication system. Large scale propagation model and small scale fading and multipath propagation are described by the physics of reflection, diffraction and scattering."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "What is the dimension of object as compared to wavelength of propagating wave when reflection occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Same",
            "d) Very small"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reflection occurs when a propagating electromagnetic wave impinges upon an object which has very large dimensions when compared to the wavelength of the propagation wave. Reflection occurs from the surface of the Earth and from buildings and walls."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "When does the wave propagating from one medium to another gets partially reflection and partially transmitted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both mediums have same electrical properties",
            "b) Both mediums have different electrical properties",
            "c) Both mediums have same magnetic properties",
            "d) Both mediums have different magnetic properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a radio wave propagating in one medium impinges upon another medium having different electrical properties. The wave is partially reflected and partially transmitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "What is the case of reflection, in course of second medium being a perfect dielectric?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loss of energy during absorption",
            "b) Total energy reflected back to first medium",
            "c) No loss of energy in absorption",
            "d) Total energy transmitted into second medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the plane wave is incident on a perfect dielectric, part of the energy is transmitted into the second medium and part of the energy is reflected back into the first medium. There is no loss of energy in absorption."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "What is the case of reflection, in course of second medium being a perfect conductor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loss of energy during absorption",
            "b) Total energy reflected back to first medium",
            "c) Partly transmission and reflection",
            "d) Total energy transmitted into second medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the second medium is perfect conductor, then all incident energy is reflected back into the second medium. There is no loss of energy during absorption."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which of the following relates the incident and reflected & transmitted wave?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fresnel transmission coefficient",
            "b) Scattering coefficient",
            "c) Diffraction coefficients",
            "d) Fresnel reflection coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electric field intensity of the reflected and transmitted waves may be related to the incident waves in the medium of origin through the Fresnel reflection coefficient. It is equal to the ratio of the amplitude of the reflected wave to the incident wave, with each expressed as phasors."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Reflection coefficient is not a function of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material property",
            "b) Diffraction loss",
            "c) Wave polarization",
            "d) Angle of incidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reflection coefficient is a function of the material properties, and generally depends upon the wave polarization, angle of incidence and frequency of propagating waves. It is a parameter that describes how much of an electromagnetic wave is reflected by an impedance discontinuity in the transmission medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Polarized wave can be mathematically represented as sum of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Four orthogonal components",
            "b) Two spatially adjacent components",
            "c) Two spatially orthogonal components",
            "d) Six orthogonal components"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A polarized wave may be mathematically represented as sum of two spatially orthogonal components. For an arbitrary polarization, super position may be used to compute the reflected fields from a reflecting surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Permittivity and conductivity are insensitive to ______ for a good conductor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operating frequency",
            "b) Polarization density",
            "c) Electric field",
            "d) Property of material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The plane of incidence is defined as the plane containing the incident, reflected and transmitted waves. The incident light is polarized with its electric field perpendicular to the plane containing the incident, reflected, and refracted rays."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Velocity of electromagnetic wave can be given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/√(μ∈)",
            "b) μ/∈",
            "c) 1/(μ∈)",
            "d) μ∈"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The terms permittivity and conductivity are insensitive to operating frequency when the material is a good conductor. In the case of conductors, it is evident that electric field inside a conductor is zero. That is because free charges reside only on the surface of conductor and not inside."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "The boundary condition at the surface of incidence obeys ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kepler’s law",
            "b) Gauss law",
            "c) Faraday law",
            "d) Snell’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a medium with permittivity, ∈ and permeability, μ the velocity of electromagnetic wave is given by 1/√(μ∈). It is also known as phase velocity. The velocity of light is given by 3*108 m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "The angle at which no reflection occurs in the medium of origin is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Azimuth angle",
            "b) Elevation angle",
            "c) Brewster angle",
            "d) Inclination angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Snell’s law is also known as Snell–Descartes law or the law of refraction. It gives a formula to describe the relationship between the angles of incidence and refraction, when referring to light or other waves passing through a boundary between two different isotropic media, such as water, glass, or air."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Diffraction occurs when radio path between Tx. And Rx. Is obstructed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface having sharp irregularities",
            "b) Smooth irregularities",
            "c) Rough surface",
            "d) All types of surfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diffraction occurs when radio path between transmitter and receiver is obstructed by a surface that has sharp irregularities (edges). The secondary waves resulting from the obstructing surface are present throughout the space and even behind the obstacle."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "At high frequencies, diffraction does not depends on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geometry of the object",
            "b) Distance between Tx and Rx",
            "c) Amplitude of incident wave",
            "d) Polarization of incident wave"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At high frequency, diffraction depends on the geometry of the object, as well as the amplitude, phase, and polarization of the incident wave at the point of diffraction. It gives rise to a bending of waves even when line of sight does not exist between transmitter and receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Diffraction allows radio signals to propagate around ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous surface",
            "b) Smooth surface",
            "c) Curved surface of Earth",
            "d) Does not allow propagation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diffraction allows radio signals to propagate around the curved surface of the Earth. Signals can propagate beyond the horizon and to propagate behind obstruction. It is the slight bending of light as it passes around the edge of an object."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Which principle explains the phenomenon of diffraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Principle of Simultaneity",
            "b) Pascal’s Principle",
            "c) Archimedes’ Principle",
            "d) Huygen’s principle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The phenomenon of diffraction can be explained by Huygen’s principle. It states that all points on a wavefront can be considered as point sources for the production of secondary wavelets. And these wavelets combine to produce a new wavefront in direction of propagation."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Diffraction is caused by propagation of secondary wavelets into _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bright region",
            "b) Shadowed region",
            "c) Smooth region",
            "d) Large region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diffraction is caused due to propagation of secondary wavelets into a shadowed region. The field strength in the shadowed region is the vector sum of the electric field components of all the secondary wavelets in the space around the obstacle."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Difference between the direct path and the diffracted path is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average length",
            "b) Radio path length",
            "c) Excess path length",
            "d) Wavelength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Excess path length denoted by ∆, is the difference between the direct path and the diffracted path. It is calculated with the help of Fresnel zone geometry."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "The phase difference between a direct line of sight path and diffracted path is function of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Height and position of obstruction",
            "b) Only height",
            "c) Operating frequency",
            "d) Polarization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phase difference between a direct line of sight path and diffracted path is a function of height and position of the diffraction. It is also a function of transmitter and receiver location."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Which of the following explains the concept of diffraction loss?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Principle of Simultaneity",
            "b) Pascal’s Principle",
            "c) Fresnel zone",
            "d) Archimedes’ Principle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The concept of diffraction loss is a function of the path difference around an obstruction. It can be explained by Fresnel zones. Fresnel zones represent successive regions where secondary waves have a path length from Tx to Rx which are nλ/2 greater than total path length."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "In mobile communication system, diffraction loss occurs due to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dielectric medium",
            "b) Obstruction",
            "c) Electric field",
            "d) Operating frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diffraction loss occurs from the blockage of secondary waves such that only a portion of the energy is diffracted around an obstacle. An obstruction causes a blockage of energy from source some of the Fresnel zones, allowing only some of the transmitted energy to reach the receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "For predicting the field strength in a given service area, it is essential to estimate ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polarization",
            "b) Magnetic field",
            "c) Height of transmitter",
            "d) Signal attenuation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Estimating the signal attenuation caused by diffraction of radio waves over hills and buildings is essential in predicting the field strength in a given service area. In practice, prediction is a process of theoretical approximation modified by necessary empirical corrections."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Scattering occurs when medium consists of objects with dimensions _______ compared to the wavelength.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Large",
            "d) Very large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Scattering occurs when the medium through which the wave travels consists of objects with dimensions that are small compared to the wavelength. But the number of obstacles per unit volume is large."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Scattered waves are produced at ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rough surface",
            "b) Shadowed region",
            "c) Smooth surface",
            "d) Horizon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Scattered waves are produced by rough surfaces, small objects or by other irregularities in the channel. In practice, foliage, street signs, and lamp posts induce scattering in a mobile communication system."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "The actual received signal is ______ than what is predicted by reflection and diffraction model.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weaker",
            "b) Equal",
            "c) Stronger",
            "d) Very weak"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The actual received signal in a mobile radio environment is often stronger than what is predicted by reflection and diffraction model alone. This is because when a radio wave incidence upon the rough surface, reflected energy is spread out in all directions."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Scattered energy in all directions provides _________ at a receiver.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Channels",
            "b) Loss of signal",
            "c) No energy",
            "d) Additional radio energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Objects such as lamp posts and trees tend to scatter energy in all directions. They provide additional radio energy at a receiver. Scattering may also refer to particle-particle collisions between molecules, atoms, electrons, photons and other particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Surface roughness are often tested using __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rayleigh criterion",
            "b) Lawson criterion",
            "c) Barkhausen stability criterion",
            "d) Nyquist criterion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rough surface is often tested using a Rayleigh criterion. It defines the critical height of surface protuberances for a given angle of incidence. The Rayleigh criterion is the criterion for the minimum resolvable detail. The imaging process is said to be diffraction-limited when the first diffraction minimum of the image of one source point coincides with the maximum of another."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "A surface is considered rough if protuberance is ________ than critical height.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Less",
            "c) Greater",
            "d) No relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A surface is considered rough if its minimum to maximum protuberance is greater than the critical height calculated using Rayleigh criterion. It is considered smooth if protuberance is less than critical height."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "RCS of scattering object is defined as the ratio of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power density of signal scattered to power density of radio wave incident",
            "b) Power density of radio wave incident to power density of signal scattered",
            "c) Power density of incident waves to power density of reflected wave",
            "d) Power density of reflected wave to power density of incident waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The radar cross section of a scattering object is defined as the ratio of the power density of the signal scattered in the direction of the receiver to the power density of the radio wave incident upon the scattering object. It has unit of square meters."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which equation is used to calculate the received power due to scattering for urban mobile radio system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laplace equation",
            "b) Bistatic radar equation",
            "c) Poisson’s equation",
            "d) Maxwell equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For urban mobile radio systems, models based on bistatic radar equation is used to compute the received power due to scattering in the far field. This equation describes the propagation of wave in free space which impinges on a scattering object and then reradiated in the direction of receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "In ionosphere propagation, waves arriving at the receiving antenna using the phenomenon of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scattering",
            "b) Refraction",
            "c) Diffraction",
            "d) Radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Scattering is a general physical process where some forms of radiation, such as light, sound, or moving particles, are forced to deviate from a straight trajectory by one or more paths. It is due to localized non-uniformities in the medium through which they pass."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Power density is basically termed as ________ power per unit area.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflected",
            "b) Refracted",
            "c) Radiated",
            "d) Diffracted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power density is the amount of power (time rate of energy transfer) per unit volume. It is also termed as radiated power per unit area. In energy transformers including batteries, fuel cells, motors, etc., power density refers to a volume. It is then also called volume power density."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a practical path loss estimation technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Log distance path loss model",
            "b) Log normal shadowing",
            "c) Determination of percentage of coverage area",
            "d) Hata model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The empirical approach is based on fitting curves or analytical expressions that recreate a set of measured data. This has the advantage of implicitly taking into account all propagation factors, both known and unknown through actual field measurements."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Average received signal power decreases __________ with distance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exponentially",
            "b) Logarithmically",
            "c) Two times",
            "d) Four times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Log normal shadowing, log distance path loss model and determination of percentage of coverage area are practical pat loss estimation techniques. Hata model is only valid for exterior environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "What does path loss exponent indicates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rate at which path loss decreases with distance",
            "b) Rate at which path loss increases with distance",
            "c) Rate at which path loss decreases with power density",
            "d) Rate at which path loss increases with power density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Both theoretical and measurement based propagation models indicate that average received signal power decreases logarithmically with distance. It is valid for both outdoor and indoor channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which distribution describes the shadowing effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Log normal distribution",
            "b) Nakagami distribution",
            "c) Cauchy distribution",
            "d) Rayleigh distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average large scale path loss for an arbitrary T-R separation is expressed as a function of distance by using a path loss exponent, n. It indicates the rate at which the path loss increases with distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Log normal shadowing implies that measured signal levels at specific T-R separation have ______ distribution when signal levels have values in dB units.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rayleigh",
            "b) Gamma",
            "c) Gaussian",
            "d) Nakagami"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is important to select a free space reference distance that is appropriate for the propagation environment. The reference distance should always be in the far field of the antenna so that near field effects do not alter the reference path loss."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "A link budget is accounting of all __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gain and losses from the transmitter",
            "b) Power transmitted by transmitter",
            "c) Power received by receiver",
            "d) Power transmitted and received"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Log normal distribution describes the random shadowing effects. It occurs over a large number of measurement locations which have the same T-R separation, but have different clutter on the propagation path."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Antenna’s efficiency is given by the ratio of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Losses",
            "b) Physical aperture to effective aperture",
            "c) Signal power to noise power",
            "d) Effective aperture to physical aperture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Log normal shadowing occurs over a large number of measurement locations which have the same T-R separation, but have different levels of clutter on the propagation path. It follows log normal distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an outdoor propagation model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longley-Rice model",
            "b) Ericson Multiple Breakpoint Model",
            "c) Hata model",
            "d) Okumura model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ericson multiple breakpoint model is an indoor propagation model. Longley-Rice, Hata and Okumura model are outdoor propagation models. Most of these models are based on a systematic interpretation of measurement data obtained in the service area."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Longley –Rice model is applicable to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Point to point communication",
            "b) All to all communication",
            "c) Point to multipoint communication",
            "d) Multipoint microwave distribution sstem"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Longley-Rice model is applicable to point-to-point communication systems in the frequency range from 40 MHz to 100 GHz. They are applicable for different kinds of terrain. Terrain profile may vary from a simple curved Earth profile to a highly mountainous profile."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Longley-Rice prediction model is also referred as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Okumura model",
            "b) Hata model",
            "c) ITS irregular terrain model",
            "d) Bertoni model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Longley Rice prediction model is also referred to as ITS irregular terrain model. The model is based on electromagnetic theory and on statistical analyses of both terrain features and radio measurements. It predicts the median attenuation of a radio signal as a function of distance and the variability of the signal in time and in space."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "The extra term for additional attenuation due to urban clutter near the receiving antenna is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power factor",
            "b) Urban gain",
            "c) Clutter factor",
            "d) Urban factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The urban factor (UF) is derived by comparing the predictions by the original Longley –Rice model with those obtained by Okumura. It deals with radio propagation in urban areas and is relevant to mobile radio."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which method is used by Edwards and Durkin algorithm to calculate the loss associated with diffraction edges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epstein and Peterson method",
            "b) Interpolation method",
            "c) Knife edge diffraction method",
            "d) Fresnel- Kirchoff method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One shortcoming of the Longley –Rice model is that it does not provide a way of determining corrections due to environmental factors. It does not consider correction factors to account for the effects of buildings and foliage. Multipath is also not considered."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Which of the most widely used model for signal prediction in urban areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ericsson Multiple Breakpoint Model",
            "b) Log distance path loss model",
            "c) Okumura model",
            "d) Attenuation factor model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Edwards and Durkin algorithm uses Epstein and Peterson method to calculate the loss associated with two diffraction edges. It is the sum of two attenuations. First is loss at second diffraction edge caused by first diffraction edge. And second is the loss at receiver caused by second diffraction edge."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Okumura model is applicable for distances of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 m to 10 m",
            "b) 1 km to 100 km",
            "c) 100 km to 1000 km",
            "d) 10 km to 10000 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Durkin’s model is very attractive because it can read in a digital elevation map and perform a site specific propagation computation on the elevation data. It can produce a signal strength contour that is reported to be good within a few dB."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the major disadvantage of the Okumura model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex",
            "b) Inaccurate",
            "c) Not practical",
            "d) Slow response to rapid change in terrain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Okumura’s model is one of the most widely used models for signal prediction in urban areas. This model is applicable for frequencies in the range 150 MHz to 1920 MHz (Extrapolated upto 3000 MHz)."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "The Hata model is empirical formulation of which model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Okumura model",
            "b) Longley- Rice model",
            "c) Durkin’s model",
            "d) Walfisch and Bertoni model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Okumura’s model is applicable for distances of 1 km to 100 km. It can be used for base station antenna heights ranging from 30 m to 1000 m. Okumura developed a set of curves giving the median attenuation relative to free space in an urban area."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Hata model is well suited for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Personal communication system",
            "b) Large cell mobile radio system",
            "c) Small cell mobile radio system",
            "d) Every mobile radio system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Okumura’s model is considered to be among the simplest and best in terms of accuracy in path loss prediction for mature cellular and land mobile radio system. It is very practical and has become a standard for system planning in modern land mobile system in Japan."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Which of the following considers the impact of rooftops and building?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Okumura model",
            "b) Hata model",
            "c) Walfisch and Bertoni model",
            "d) Longley- Rice model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The major disadvantage with the model is its slow response to rapid changes in terrain. Therefore the model is fairly good in urban and suburban areas, but not as good in rural areas. Common standard deviations between predicted and measured path loss values are 10 dB to 14 dB."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Propagation within building is not influenced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Layout of the building",
            "b) Construction materials",
            "c) Building type",
            "d) Trees outside the building"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The indoor radio channel differs from the traditional mobile radio channel. The distances covered are much smaller and variability of the environment is much greater for a much smaller range of T-R separation distances."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "What is hard partition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Partition as part of the building",
            "b) Partition that can be moved",
            "c) Partition not touching ceiling",
            "d) Partition between different floors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It has been observed that propagation within buildings is strongly influenced by specific features. These features are layout of the building, the construction materials, and the building type."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Partitions that can be moved are called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soft partitions",
            "b) Hard partitions",
            "c) Disk partition",
            "d) Dynamic partition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Smaller propagation distances make it more difficult to insure far field radiation for all receiver location and types of antenna. The condition is very variable for smaller propagation distances."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Losses between the floors of the building can be determined using ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal dimensions",
            "b) Material used to create antenna",
            "c) External dimension",
            "d) Line of sight path"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Partitions that are formed as part of the building structure are called hard partitions. Partitions vary widely in their electrical and physical characteristics. Thus, it makes difficult in applying general models to specific indoor installation."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Technique of drawing a single ray between the transmitter and receiver is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary ray tracing",
            "b) Primary ray tracing",
            "c) Line of sight",
            "d) Straight line tracing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Partitions that may be moved are called soft partitions. They do not span to the ceiling. Office buildings often have large open areas which are constructed by using moveable office partitions. Thus, space can be reconfigured easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "________ is a process of converting plain text into cipher text.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Authentication",
            "b) Decryption",
            "c) Encryption",
            "d) Compression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The losses between floors of a building are determined by external dimensions as well as materials of the building. It is also determined using type of construction used to create the floors and external surroundings."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "_______ reduces the cell size to increase capacity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intelligent cell approach",
            "b) Microcell approach",
            "c) Top down approach",
            "d) Bottom up approach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PAF (path attenuation factor) represents a specific obstruction encountered by a ray drawn between the transmitter and receiver in 3-D. This technique of drawing a single ray between transmitter and receiver is called primary ray tracing."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "_________ configuration describes a desktop in an office.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mobile and wired",
            "b) Fixed and wired",
            "c) Fixed and wireless",
            "d) Mobile and wireless"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Encryption is the most effective way to achieve data security. It is the process of encoding a message in such a way that only authorized parties can access it. Encryption does not itself prevent interference but denies the intelligible content to a would-be interceptor."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Small scale fading describes the _________ fluctuations of the amplitude, phases of a signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid",
            "b) Slow",
            "c) Instantaneous",
            "d) Different"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Small scale fading or simply fading, is used to describe the rapid fluctuations of amplitudes, phases, or multipath delays of a radio signal over a short period of time or travel distance. It ignores the large scale path loss."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an effect caused by multipath in radio channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rapid changes in signal strength",
            "b) Random frequency modulation",
            "c) Power of base station",
            "d) Time dispersion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fading is caused by interference. It is caused by interference between two or more versions of the transmitted signal which arrive at the receiver at slightly different times."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "In urban areas, fading occurs due to height of mobile antenna ________ than height of surrounding structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same",
            "b) Smaller",
            "c) Greater",
            "d) Very larger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rapid changes in signal strength over a small travel distance are caused due to multipath. It causes random frequency modulation due to varying Doppler shifts on different multipath signals. Time dispersion is also caused by multipath propagation delays."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Apparent shift in frequency in multipath wave is caused due to relative motion between________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base station and MSC",
            "b) Mobile and surrounding objects",
            "c) Mobile and MSC",
            "d) Mobile and base station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In urban areas, fading occurs because height of the mobile antenna is below the height of surrounding structures. Therefore, there is no single line of sight path to the base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Doppler shift is directly proportional to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity",
            "b) Height of antenna",
            "c) Power of receiving antenna",
            "d) Power of transmitter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The received signal may fade even when the mobile receiver is stationary. It is due to the movement of surrounding objects in the radio channel. The multipath components combine vectorially at the receiver antenna and cause signal to distort or fade."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor does not influence small scale fading?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multipath propagation",
            "b) Power density of base station",
            "c) Speed of mobile",
            "d) Speed of surrounding objects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to relative motion between mobile and base station, each multipath wave experiences an apparent shift in frequency. This shift in received signal frequency due to motion called Doppler shift."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Signal will distort if transmitted signal bandwidth is greater than bandwidth of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Receiver",
            "b) Radio channel",
            "c) Multipath channel",
            "d) Transceiver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shift in received signal frequency due to motion is called Doppler shift. It is directly proportional to the velocity and direction of motion of mobile with respect to the direction of arrival of the received multipath wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "What is a measure of the maximum frequency difference for which signals are strongly correlated in amplitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coherence bandwidth",
            "b) Narrow bandwidth",
            "c) Incoherent bandwidth",
            "d) Wide bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many physical factors in radio channel influence small scale fading. Multipath propagation, speed of mobile, speed of surrounding objects, transmission bandwidth of the signal influences small scale fading in a large way."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "The Doppler shift for mobile moving with constant velocity, v is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) (v*cos θ)/λ",
            "b) v/λ",
            "c) v*cos θ",
            "d) v*λ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Received signal will be distorted if transmitted signal bandwidth is greater than bandwidth of multipath channel. But received signal strength will not fade much over a local area."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Small scale variations of a mobile radio signal are directly related to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impulse response of mobile radio channel",
            "b) Impulse response of base station",
            "c) Frequency response of antenna",
            "d) Frequency response of base station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The small scale variations of a mobile radio signal can be directly related to the impulse response of mobile radio channel. he impulse response is a wideband channel characterization and contains all information necessary to simulate or analyze any type of radio transmission through the channel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Mobile radio channel can be modelled as a ______ filter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-linear",
            "b) Low-pass",
            "c) Linear",
            "d) Bandpass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Impulse response is a wideband channel characterization. It contains all information necessary to simulate or analyse any type of radio transmission through the channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Received signal can be expressed as ______ of transmitted signal with channel impulse response.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition",
            "b) Subtraction",
            "c) Division",
            "d) Convolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mobile radio channel may be modelled as a linear filter with a time varying impulse response. The time variation is due to receiver motion in space. The filtering nature is caused by summation of amplitudes and delays of multiple arriving waves at any instant of time."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Discretization of multipath delay axis of impulse response into equal time delay segments is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excess delay bins",
            "b) Delay bins",
            "c) Discrete bins",
            "d) Digital bins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Impulse response is a useful characterization of channel. It may be used to predict and compare the performance of different mobile communication systems and transmission bandwidth for a particular mobile channel condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Small scale received power is ________ of average powers received in each multipath component.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Log",
            "b) Exponential",
            "c) Multiplication",
            "d) Sum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The received signal y(t) can be expressed as a convolution of transmitted signal x(t) with impulse response of mobile radio channel. The variable t represents the time variations due to motion and the channel impulse multipath delay for fixed value of t."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Average power for a CW signal is _______ to average received power for a wideband signal in small scale region.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equivalent",
            "b) Two times",
            "c) Four times",
            "d) Ten times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is useful to discretize the multipath delay axis of the impulse response into equal time delay segments called excess delay bins. The technique of quantizing the delay bins determines the time delay resolution of the channel model."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "The received local ensemble average power of wideband and narrowband signals are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Different",
            "b) Equivalent",
            "c) Not dependent",
            "d) Double"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The average small received power is the sum of the average powers received in each multipath component. This is the case if transmitted signal is able to resolve the multipath."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a small scale multipath measurement technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirect pulse measurement",
            "b) Direct pulse measurement",
            "c) Spread spectrum sliding correlator measurement",
            "d) Swept frequency measurement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of the importance of multipath structure in determining the small scale fading effects, a number of wideband channel sounding techniques have been developed. These are direct pulse measurement, spread spectrum sliding correlator and swept frequency measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What is the main disadvantage of RF pulse system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complexity",
            "b) Not real time",
            "c) Interference and noise",
            "d) Simplicity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Direct RF pulse systems have a very attractive system. They lack complexity because of the use of off the shelf equipment. This system can also provide a local average power delay profile."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Why is the phase of individual multipath components are not received in RF Pulse system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to use of duplexer",
            "b) Due to use of ADC",
            "c) Due to use of flip flops",
            "d) Due to use of envelope detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The main problem with RF pulse system is that it is subject to interference and noise. This is due to wide passband filter required for multipath time resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Spread spectrum sliding correlator has better ________ in comparison to RF pulse system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic range",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Power density",
            "d) Structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Another disadvantage of RF pulse system is that phase of individual multipath components are not received due to use of an envelope detector. However, use of a coherent detector permits measurement of the multipath phase using this technique."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "If a PN sequence has chip duration of Tc, then chip rate is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tc",
            "b) 1/Tc",
            "c) 2 Tc",
            "d) Tc2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While the probing signal may be wideband, it is possible to detect the transmitted signal using a narrowband receiver preceded by a wideband mixer. Thus, it improves the dynamic range of the system in comparison to RF pulse system."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "The maximal length of PN sequence, the sequence length for n number of shift register is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2n",
            "b) 1/2n",
            "c) 2n – 1",
            "d) 2n + 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a spread spectrum channel sounder, a carrier signal is spread over a large bandwidth. It is done by mixing it with a binary pseudo number (PN) sequence having a chip duration of Tc and chip rate of 1/Tc."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "The ratio between transmitter chip clock rate and the difference between the transmitter chip clock and difference between transmitter and receiver chip clock rates is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slide factor",
            "b) Chip factor",
            "c) Reuse factor",
            "d) Shape factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a maximal length pseudo number (PN) sequence, the sequence length is 2n – 1. Here, n is the number of shift registers in the sequence register. "
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of spread spectrum channel sounding system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rejection of passband noise",
            "b) Real time",
            "c) Coverage range improvement",
            "d) Less transmitter power required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slide factor is defined as ratio between transmitter chip clock rate and the difference between the transmitter chip clock and difference between transmitter and receiver chip clock rates. It is unit less quantity."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of spread spectrum channel sounding system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passband noise",
            "b) Less coverage area",
            "c) Large transmitter power required",
            "d) Not in real time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the main advantage of spread spectrum channel sounding system is ability to reject passsband noise. Thus, it improves the coverage range for a given transmitter power. Also, required transmitter powers can be considerably lower compared to direct pulse systems due to inherent processing gain."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Transmissivity is a _________ domain response.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Time-frequency",
            "d) Spatial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A disadvantage of spread spectrum system as compared to direct RF pulse system, is that measurements are not made in real time. But they are compiled as the PN codes slide past one another."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Frequency domain channel sounding system is _______ in nature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Real time",
            "b) Digital",
            "c) Non real time",
            "d) Analog"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is a dual relationship between time domain and frequency domain techniques. Therefore, it is possible to measure the channel impulse response in the frequency domain. Frequency domain channel sounder is used for measuring channel impulse response."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Faster sweep time can be accomplished by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing frequency steps",
            "b) Increasing time slots",
            "c) Reducing time slots",
            "d) Reducing frequency steps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transmissivity response is a frequency domain response. It is a frequency domain representation of channel impulse response. This response is then converted to the time domain using inverse discrete Fourier transform."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Power delay profile is represented as plots of __________ with respect to fixed time delay reference.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relative received power",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Transmitted power",
            "d) Relative power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Power delay profiles are generally represented as plots of relative received power as a function of excess delay with respect to a fixed time delay reference. They are calculated by averaging instantaneous power delay profile measurements over a local area."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a multipath channel parameter that can be determined from power delay profile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean excess delay",
            "b) RMS delay spread",
            "c) Excess delay spread",
            "d) Doppler spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The mean excess delay, excess delay spread and rms delay spread are some multipath channel parameters. They can be determined from a power delay profile. Doppler spread is a measure of spectral broadening caused by time rate of change of mobile radio channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "The time dispersive properties of wideband multipath channel are quantified by ______ and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean excess delay, rms delay spread",
            "b) Doppler spread, rms delay spread",
            "c) Doppler spread, coherence time",
            "d) Mean excess delay, Doppler spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time dispersive properties of wide band multipath channels are most commonly quantified by their mean excess delay and rms delay spread. Coherence time characterizes the time varying nature of frequency dispersiveness of mobile radio channel in time domain."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "_______ is the square root of the second central moment of the power delay profile.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean excess delay",
            "b) Rms delay spread",
            "c) Excess delay spread",
            "d) Coherence time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rms delay spread is the square root of the second central moment of the power delay profile. Many measurements are made at many local areas in order to determine a statistical range of multipath channel parameters for a mobile communication system over a large scale area."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first moment of the power delay profile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rms delay spread",
            "b) Excess delay spread",
            "c) Mean excess delay",
            "d) Doppler spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mean excess delay is the first moment of the power delay profile. It is defined from a single power delay profile which is temporal or spatial average of consecutive impulse response measurements collected and averaged over a local area."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What is the order of typical values of rms delay spread in outdoor mobile radio channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microseconds",
            "b) Nanoseconds",
            "c) Seconds",
            "d) Minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Typical values of rms delay spread are on the order of microseconds in outdoor mobile radio channels. For indoor mobile radio channels, they are of the order of nanoseconds."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Power delay profile and magnitude frequency response of a mobile radio channel are related through _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laplace Transform",
            "b) Fourier Transform",
            "c) S Transform",
            "d) Wavelet Transform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Power delay profile and magnitude frequency response of a mobile radio channel are related through the Fourier transform. Therefore, it is possible to obtain an equivalent description of the channel in the frequency domain using its frequency response characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "______ and coherence bandwidth are inversely proportional to one another.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rms delay spread",
            "b) Mean excess delay",
            "c) Excess delay spread",
            "d) Doppler spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rms delay spread and coherence bandwidth are inversely proportional to one another. However, their exact relationship is a function of the exact multipath structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Coherence bandwidth is a statistical measure of range of frequencies over which channel is considered _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time dispersive",
            "b) Frequency selective",
            "c) Time variant",
            "d) Flat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Coherence bandwidth is a statistical measure of range of frequencies over which channel is considered flat. A flat channel is a channel which passes all spectral components with approximately equal gain and linear phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which of the following describes time varying nature of the channel in a small scale region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay spread and coherence time",
            "b) Coherence bandwidth and delay spread",
            "c) Doppler spread and coherence time",
            "d) Delay spread and doppler spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Delay spread and coherence bandwidth describes the time dispersive nature of the channel in a local area. They do not give information about the time varying nature of the channel caused by either relative motion between the mobile and base station, or by movement of objects in the channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Doppler spread is a range of frequencies over which received Doppler spread is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Non zero",
            "c) Infinite",
            "d) One"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Doppler spread is a range of frequencies over which received Doppler spectrum is essentially non-zero. It is a measure of spectral broadening caused by time rate of change of mobile radio channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "_______ is a statistical measure of time duration over which channel impulse response is invariant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coherence time",
            "b) Doppler spread",
            "c) Mean excess delay",
            "d) Rms delay spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coherence time is actually a statistical measure of the time duration over which the channel impulse response is essentially invariant. It quantifies the similarity of the channel response at varying times."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a channel parameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bandwidth",
            "b) Coherence time",
            "c) Rms delay spread",
            "d) Doppler spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Channel parameters are coherence bandwidth, rms delay spread and Doppler spread. Signal parameters are bandwidth and symbol period. Different types of fading occur depending on the relation between channel and signal parameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "______ leads to time dispersion and frequency selective fading.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doppler spread",
            "b) Multipath delay spread",
            "c) Time dispersive parameters",
            "d) Frequency delay spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Multipath delay spread leads to time dispersion and frequency selective fading. Doppler spread leads to frequency dispersion and time selective fading. These two propagation mechanism are independent of each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Which of the following s not a characteristic of flat fading?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mobile radio channel has constant gain",
            "b) Linear phase response",
            "c) Non linear phase response",
            "d) Bandwidth is greater than the bandwidth of transmitted signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The received signal will undergo flat fading if mobile radio channel has a constant gain and linear phase response over a bandwidth which is greater than the bandwidth of transmitted signal. It is the most common type of fading."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Flat fading channel is also known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude varying channel",
            "b) Wideband channel",
            "c) Phase varying channel",
            "d) Frequency varying channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In flat fading, the multipath structure of the channel is such that spectral characteristics of the transmitted signal are preserved at the receiver. But, the strength of the received signal changes with time due to fluctuations in the gain of channel caused by multipath."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Frequency selective fading channels are also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrowband channel",
            "b) Wideband channel",
            "c) Amplitude varying channel",
            "d) Phase varying channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flat fading channel is also known as amplitude varying channel. They are also sometimes referred to as narrowband channel. In flat fading channel, the bandwidth of the applied signal is narrow as compared to the channel flat fading bandwidth."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "For fast fading channel, the coherence time of the channel is smaller than _______ of transmitted signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doppler spread",
            "b) Bandwidth",
            "c) Symbol period",
            "d) Coherence bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the channel possesses a constant gain and linear phase response over a bandwidth that is smaller than the bandwidth of transmitted signal, then the channel creates frequency selective fading on the received signal. Frequency selective fading channel are much more difficult to model than flat fading channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "In slow fading channel, Doppler spread of the channel is much less than the ________ of baseband signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Symbol period",
            "b) Phase",
            "c) Coherence time",
            "d) Bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frequency selective fading channels are also known as wideband channels. The bandwidth of the signal is wider than the bandwidth of channel impulse response."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Which of the following distribution is used for describing statistical time varying nature of received envelope of multipath component?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Log normal distribution",
            "b) Levy distribution",
            "c) Rayleigh distribution",
            "d) Gaussian distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rayleigh distribution is the most common distribution for statistical modelling. It is used to describe the statistical time varying nature of the received envelope of a flat fading signal. It also describes the envelope of an individual multipath component."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Envelope of the sum of two quadrature Gaussian noise signal obeys _________ distribution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rayleigh",
            "b) Inverse Gaussian",
            "c) Nakagami",
            "d) Gamma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is well known that the envelope of the sum of two quadrature Gaussian noise signal obeys Rayleigh distribution. This fading distribution could be applied to any scenario where there is no line of sight path between transmitter and receiver antennas."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "For a Rayleigh fading signal, mean and median differ by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 dB",
            "b) 10 dB",
            "c) 0.55 dB",
            "d) 100 dB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mean and median differ by only 0.55 dB in a Rayleigh fading signal. The differences between the rms values and the other two values are higher."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "For a nonfading signal component present, the small scale fading envelope distribution is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rayleigh",
            "b) Gaussian",
            "c) Log normal",
            "d) Ricean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By using median values instead of mean values, it is easy to compare different fading distributions which may have widely varying means. Median is used in practice since fading data is measured in the field and a particular distribution cannot be assumed."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Ricean distribution degenerates to ________ distribution when the dominant component fades away.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Log normal",
            "b) Gamma",
            "c) Rayleigh",
            "d) Gaussian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The small scale fading envelope is Ricean when there is a dominant stationary (nonfading) signal component, such as line of sight propagation path. In such a situation, random multipath components arriving at different angles are superimposed on a stationary dominant signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "The envelope of a bandpass noise is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniformly distributed",
            "b) Rayleigh",
            "c) Ricean",
            "d) Gaussian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ricean distribution degenerates to Rayleigh distribution when the dominant component fades away. As the dominant signal becomes weaker, the composite signal resembles a noise signal which has an envelope that is Rayleigh."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "The envelope of a sinusoid plus bandpass noise has __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniformly distributed",
            "b) Rayleigh",
            "c) Ricean",
            "d) Gaussian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The envelope of only bandpass noise is Rayleigh distribution. Rayleigh distribution is a continuous probability density function for positive random variables. "
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "What do you call an attenuation that occurs over many different wavelengths of the carrier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rayleigh fading",
            "b) Ricean fading",
            "c) Wavelength fading",
            "d) Slow fading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The envelope of a sinusoid plus bandpass noise has Ricean distribution. In probability theory, Ricean distribution is the probability distribution which has magnitude of a circular bivariate normal random variable with potentially non-zero mean."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Which of the reception problems below that is not due to multipath?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delayed spreading",
            "b) Rayleigh fading",
            "c) Random Doppler shift",
            "d) Slow fading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Slow fading does not vary quickly with the frequency. It originates due to effect of mobility. Slow fading is the result of signal path change due to shadowing and obstructions such as tree or buildings etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a statistical models for multipath fading channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clarke’s model for flat fading",
            "b) Saleh and Valenzuela indoor statistical model",
            "c) Two ray Rayleigh fading model",
            "d) Faraday model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Several multipath models have been suggested to explain the observed statistical nature of a mobile channel. Clarke’s model for flat fading, Saleh and Valenzuela indoor statistical model, two ray Rayleigh fading model are some of the statistical model for multipath fading channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Who presented the first statistical model for multipath fading channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ossana",
            "b) Rayleigh",
            "c) Newton",
            "d) Faraday"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first statistical model was presented by Ossana. It was based on interference of wave incident and reflected from the flat sides of randomly located buildings. Ossana model predicts flat fading power spectra that were in agreement with measurements in suburban areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an important statistics of a Rayleigh fading useful for designing error control codes and diversity schemes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mobile speed",
            "b) Doppler frequency",
            "c) Level crossing rate (LCR)",
            "d) Power density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Clarke developed a model where the statistical characteristics of the electromagnetic fields of the received signal at the mobile are deduced from scattering. Clarke’s model assumes a fixed transmitter with a vertically polarized antenna."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "The level crossing rate (LCR) is defined as expected rate at which _______ fading envelope crosses a specified level.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rayleigh",
            "b) Saleh",
            "c) Vanezuela",
            "d) Faraday"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Every wave that is incident on the mobile undergoes a Doppler shift. It is due to the motion of the receiver and it arrives at the receiver at the same time. Therefore, there is no excess delay due to multipath for any of the waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Level crossing rate is a function of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power transmitted by base station",
            "b) Power density of receiver",
            "c) Mobile speed",
            "d) Bit error rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The level crossing rate (LCR) and average fade duration of a Rayleigh fading signal are important statistics. They are useful for designing error control codes and diversity schemes to be used in mobile communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Saleh and Venezuela reported the results of ______ propagation measurements.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indoor",
            "b) Outdoor",
            "c) Air",
            "d) High frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The LCR is defined as the expected rate at which the Rayleigh fading envelop is normalized to the local rms signal level. And it crosses a specified level in a positive going direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Saleh and Venezuela show that indoor channel is _______ time varying.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Not",
            "b) Very slow",
            "c) Fast",
            "d) Very fast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The level crossing rate is a function of mobile speed. Because, it is possible to relate the time rate of change of the received signal of the signal level and velocity of the mobile."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "What is the full form of SIRCIM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simulation of Indoor Radio Channel Impulse response Model",
            "b) Statistical Indoor Radio Channel for Impulse Model",
            "c) Statistical Impulse Radio Channel for Indoor Model",
            "d) Simulation of Impulse Radio Channel for Indoor Model"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Clarke’s model and the statistics for Rayleigh fading are for flat fading conditions. They do not consider multipath time delay."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "The rapid fluctuations due to small scale fading affect the _________ design.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Receiver",
            "b) Transmitter",
            "c) MSC",
            "d) Base station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term small scale fading describes the rapid fluctuations of received power level due to changes in receiver position. This effect is due to the constructive and destructive interference of the numerous multipath waves that impinge upon a wireless receiver. "
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a principle shape factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angular spread",
            "b) Angular constriction",
            "c) Azimuthal direction of maximum fading",
            "d) Angle of arrival"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rapid fluctuation due to small scale fading affect every aspect of receiver design such as dynamic range, equalization, diversity, modulation scheme and channel error correction coding. These fluctuations are a function of direction of travel as related to the angle of arrival of multipath delay. "
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Angular spread is a measure of how multipath concentrates about __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle of arrival",
            "b) Transmitted power",
            "c) Single azimuthal direction of arrival",
            "d) Received power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An approximately omnidirectional channel model accurately describes fading statistics if directional or smart antenna systems are employed at the receiver. Unfortunately, recent measurements and models have shown that the arriving multipath in a local area bears little resemblance to the omnidirectional propagation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Angular constriction is a measure of how multipath concentrates about ______ azimuthal direction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Three principle shape factors are angular spread, angular constriction, and azimuthal direction of maximum fading. They are exactly related to the average rate at which a received signal fades. "
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "_______ of a stationary process is actually the variance of the rate of change.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean",
            "b) Mean square",
            "c) Mean squared derivative",
            "d) Mean squared integral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shape factor, angular spread is a measure of how multipath concentrates about a single azimuthal direction of arrival. It has several advantages like it is invariant under changes in transmitted power.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Complex received voltage is a summation of __________ that have impinged upon receiver antenna.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multipath waves",
            "b) Waves",
            "c) Power density",
            "d) Single path waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shape factor, angular constriction is a measure of how multipath concentrates about two azimuthal directions. The measure for angular constriction is invariant under changes in transmitted power. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Which of the following is equal to received power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square of complex voltage",
            "b) Complex voltage",
            "c) Magnitude of complex voltage",
            "d) Magnitude squared of complex voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Azimuthal direction of maximum fading is the third shape factor which is a directional or orientation parameter. Its value corresponds to the direction in which s mobile user would move in order to experience the maximum fading rate in the local area. "
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Which of the following is equal to received envelope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square of complex voltage",
            "b) Complex voltage",
            "c) Magnitude of complex voltage",
            "d) Magnitude squared of complex voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mean squared derivative of a stationary process is actually the variance of the rate of change. The mean derivative of the stationary process is zero; the mean squared derivative is the simplest statistics that measures the fading rate of a channel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following describes the average fading rate within a local area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angular spread",
            "b) Angular constriction",
            "c) Azimuthal direction of maximum fading",
            "d) Angle of arrival"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Complex received voltage is a baseband representation. It us a summation of numerous multipath waves that have impinged upon the receiver antenna and have excited a complex voltage component at the input of a receiver. "
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which is the process of encoding information from a message source in suitable manner for transmission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation",
            "b) Demodulation",
            "c) Encryption",
            "d) Decryption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Modulation is the process of encoding information from a message source in suitable manner for transmission. It translates the baseband message signal to a bandpass signal at frequencies that are very higher compared to the baseband frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "AM signal have all information in ______ of the carrier.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Magnitude",
            "c) Frequency",
            "d) Power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bandpass signal is called the modulated signal and the baseband message signal is called the modulating signal. Modulation is done by varying the amplitude, phase or frequency of a high frequency carrier in accordance with the amplitude of the message signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "In frequency modulation, the amplitude of modulated carrier signal is ______and its frequency is ______ by the modulating message signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant, constant",
            "b) Varied, constant",
            "c) Constant, varied",
            "d) Varied, varied"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: AM signals have all information in the amplitude of the carrier. Because, AM signal superimpose the exact relative amplitudes of the modulating signal onto the carrier."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "FM signals have all their information in ______ of the carrier.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Magnitude",
            "c) Frequency",
            "d) Power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In frequency modulation (FM), the amplitude of modulated carrier signal is kept constant while its frequency is varied by the modulating message signal. FM is the most popular analog modulation technique used in mobile communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Amplitude modulation has ______ relationship between the quality of the received signal and the power of the received signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) No",
            "b) Non linear",
            "c) Constant",
            "d) Linear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FM signal have all their information in the phase or frequency of the carrier. This provides a nonlinear and very rapid improvement in reception quality once a certain minimum received signal level, called FM threshold is achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "FM has _______ noise immunity when compared to amplitude modulation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same",
            "b) Less",
            "c) No",
            "d) Better"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In amplitude modulation schemes, there is a linear relationship between the quality of the received signal and the power of the received signal. AM signals superimpose the exact relative amplitudes of the modulating signal onto the carrier."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "FM signals are _____ susceptible to atmospheric and impulse noise as compared to AM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Largely",
            "b) Less",
            "c) Not",
            "d) Better"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: FM offers many advantages over amplitude modulation which makes it a better choice for many mobile radio applications. Frequency modulation has better noise immunity when compared to amplitude modulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an advantage of AM systems in comparison to FM sysytems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Occupy less bandwidth",
            "b) Superior performance in fading",
            "c) Better noise immunity",
            "d) Not susceptible to impulse noise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FM signals are represented as frequency variations rather than amplitude variations. Therefore, FM signals are less susceptible to atmospheric and impulse noise."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "An FM signal is a ______ envelope signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Varied",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Large",
            "d) Constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the FM received signal is above the FM threshold, burst noise does not affect FM system performance as much as AM systems. It is due to the fact that message amplitude variations do not carry information in FM."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "FM uses class______ amplifiers and AM uses class ______ amplifiers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C, C",
            "b) A, C",
            "c) C, A",
            "d) AB, C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike AM, FM has a modulation index. Hence, bandwidth occupancy can be varied to obtain greater signal to noise performance. Thus, it is possible to tradeoff bandwidth occupancy for improved noise performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a drawback of FM systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burst noise",
            "b) Susceptible to atmospheric noise",
            "c) Wider frequency band",
            "d) Poor performance in fading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: AM signals are able to occupy less bandwidth as compared to FM signals, since the transmission system is linear. Small scale fading causes rapid fluctuations in the received signal. Thus, FM offers superior qualitative performance in fading when compared to AM."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Carrier signal in modulation technique is _______ signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High frequency",
            "b) Low frequency",
            "c) High amplitude",
            "d) Low amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Carrier signal in modulation technique is a high frequency signal. In amplitude modulation, the amplitude of a high frequency carrier signal is varied in accordance to the instantaneous amplitude of the modulating signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Modulation index of an AM signal is ratio of __________ to the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peak carrier amplitude, Peak message signal amplitude",
            "b) Peak message signal amplitude, Peak carrier amplitude",
            "c) Carrier signal frequency, Message signal frequency",
            "d) Message signal frequency, Carrier signal frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The modulation index k of an AM signal is defined as the ratio of the peak message signal amplitude to the peak carrier amplitude. The modulation index is often expressed as a percentage. It is also called percentage modulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "If the peak message signal amplitude is half the peak amplitude of the carrier signal, the signal is _____ modulated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100%",
            "b) 2%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 70%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The modulation is also expressed in percentage. It is also called percentage modulation. The signal is said to be 50% modulated if the peak message signal amplitude is half the peak amplitude of the carrier signal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "A percentage of modulation greater than ___________ will distort the message signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 25%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A percentage of modulation greater than 100% will distort the message signal if detected by an envelope detector. In this case the lower excursion of the signal will drive the carrier amplitude below zero, making it negative (and hence changing its phase)."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "The RF bandwidth of AM is ____________ the maximum frequency contained in the modulating message signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Two times",
            "c) Four times",
            "d) Ten times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The RF bandwidth of an AM signal is equal to BAM=2fm. It is double the maximum frequency contained in the modulating message signal. AM spectrum consists of an impulse at the carrier frequency and two sidebands which replicate the message spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "How is the performance of SSB AM systems in fading channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poor",
            "b) Best",
            "c) Good",
            "d) Average"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Single sideband (SSB) AM systems transmit only one of the sidebands (either upper or lower) about the carrier. Hence, they occupy only half the bandwidth of conventional AM systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of tone-in-band SSB system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High bandwidth",
            "b) Bad adjacent channel protection",
            "c) Effects of multipath",
            "d) Generation and reception of signal is complicated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SSB systems have the advantage of being very bandwidth efficient. But their performance in fading channels is very poor. For proper detection, the frequency of the oscillator at the product detector mixer in the receiver must be same as that of the incoming carrier frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "FFSR in AM systems stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feedforward signal regeneration",
            "b) Feedbackward signal regeneration",
            "c) Feedbackward system restoration",
            "d) Feedforward system restoration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tone-in-band SSB systems has the advantage of maintaining the low bandwidth property of the SSB signals, while at the same time providing good adjacent channel protection. The tone in band system employs feedforward automatic gain and frequency control to mitigate the effects of multipath induced fading."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "AM demodulation technique can be divided into _____ and _____ demodulation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct, indirect",
            "b) Slope detector, zero crossing",
            "c) Coherent, noncoherent",
            "d) Quadrature detection, coherent detection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FFSR stands for Feedforward signal regeneration. If the pilot tone and the information bearing signal undergo correlated fading, it is possible at the receiver to counteract the effects of fading through signal processing based on tracking of pilot tone. This process is called FFSR."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "A product detector in AM systems is also called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Envelope detector",
            "b) Differentiator",
            "c) Integrator",
            "d) Phase detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: AM demodulation techniques may be broadly divide into two main categories. They are called coherent and noncoherent demodulation. They are differentiated by the knowledge of transmitted carrier frequency and phase at the receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "FM is a part of general class of modulation known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle modulation",
            "b) Phase modulation",
            "c) Amplitude modulation",
            "d) Frequency modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FM is a part of general class of modulation known as angle modulation. Angle modulation varies a sinusoidal carrier signal in such a way that the angle of the carrier is varied according to the amplitude of the modulating baseband signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "FM is called constant envelope because ______ of carrier wave is kept constant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency",
            "b) Amplitude",
            "c) Phase",
            "d) Angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FM is called the constant envelope because amplitude of the carrier wave is kept constant. It is duo to the fact that the envelope of the carrier does not change with changes in the modulating signal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Which of the following are two most important classes of angle modulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude modulation, frequency modulation",
            "b) Amplitude modulation, phase modulation",
            "c) Frequency modulation, phase modulation",
            "d) Single sideband amplitude modulation, phase modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two most important classes of angle modulation are frequency modulation and phase modulation. They provide the ways in which phase of a carrier signal may be varied in accordance with the baseband signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Frequency modulation index defines the relationship between the ______ and bandwidth of transmitted signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency of message signal",
            "b) Amplitude of message signal",
            "c) Amplitude of carrier signal",
            "d) Frequency of carrier signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frequency modulated signal is regarded as the phase modulated signal in which the modulating wave is integrated before modulation. This means that an FM signal can be generated by first integrating the message signal and then using the result as an input to a phase modulator."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "FM bandwidth is approximated using _______ rule.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carson’s",
            "b) Faraday’s",
            "c) Maxwell’s",
            "d) Armstrong’s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The frequency modulation index defines the relationship between the message amplitude and the bandwidth of the transmitted signal. If the modulating signal is a low pass signal, maximum bandwidth of the modulating signal is equal to the highest frequency component present in the modulating signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the following are two methods for generating FM signal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coherent method, noncoherent method",
            "b) Product detector, envelope detector",
            "c) Direct method, indirect method",
            "d) Slope detector, Zero crossing detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The approximation of bandwidth is done using Carson’s rule. Carson’s bandwidth rule defines the approximate bandwidth requirements of communications system components for a carrier signal that is frequency modulated by a continuous or broad spectrum of frequencies rather than a single frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to vary the frequency of the carrier frequency in accordance with the baseband signal amplitude variations in direct method of FM generation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrator",
            "b) Envelope detector",
            "c) Multivibrator",
            "d) Voltage controlled oscillators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Direct method and indirect method are the methods used for generating FM signals. These methods are differentiated by the variation of the carrier frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a technique for FM demodulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slope detection",
            "b) Zero crossing detection",
            "c) Product detector",
            "d) Phase locked discriminator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above is the case for direct method. In the indirect method, a narrowband FM signal is generated using a balanced modulator, and frequency multiplication is used to increase both the frequency deviation and the carrier frequency to the required level."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Which of the following FM demodulator is sometimes known as pulse averaging discriminator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slope detection",
            "b) Zero crossing detection",
            "c) Quadrature detection",
            "d) Phase locked discriminator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In direct method, VCOs are used to vary the frequency of the carrier signal in accordance with the baseband signal amplitude variations. These oscillators use devices with reactance that can be varied by the application of a voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "PLL in FM detection stands for ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phase locked loop",
            "b) Programmable logic loop",
            "c) Phase locked logic",
            "d) Programmable locked loop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency demodulator produces an output voltage with instantaneous amplitude that is directly proportional to the instantaneous frequency of the input FM signal. Thus, frequency demodulator is a frequency to amplitude converter circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "In angle modulation, signal to noise ratio before detection is a function of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation index",
            "b) Input signal to noise ratio",
            "c) Maximum frequency of the message",
            "d) IF filter bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Various techniques such as slope detection, zero crossing detection, phase locked discrimination and quadrature detection are used to demodulate FM. Product detector is used for demodulating AM signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of digital modulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater noise immunity",
            "b) Greater security",
            "c) Easier multiplexing",
            "d) Less bandwidth requirement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Modern mobile communication systems use digital modulation techniques. Advancements in VLSI and digital signal processing technology have made digital modulation more cost effective than analog transmission systems. "
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "A desirable modulation scheme provides _________ bit error rates at __________ received signal to noise ratios.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low, low",
            "b) Low, high",
            "c) High, high",
            "d) High, low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Digital modulation offer many advantages over analog modulation. Some advantages include greater noise immunity and robustness. They provide easier multiplexing of various forms of information and greater security."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "The performance of modulation scheme is not measured in terms of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power efficiency",
            "b) Bandwidth efficiency",
            "c) Cost and complexity",
            "d) Transmitted power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A desirable modulation scheme provides low bit error rates at low received signal to noise ratios. They perform well in multipath and fading conditions, occupies a minimum bandwidth and is easy and cost effective to implement."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "In digital communication system, in order to increase noise immunity, it is necessary to increase _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal power",
            "b) Signal amplitude",
            "c) Signal frequency",
            "d) Signal magnitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The performance of modulation scheme is often measured in terms of its power efficiency and bandwidth efficiency. Other factors also affect the choice of modulation scheme, such as cost and complexity of the subscriber receiver and modulation which is simple to detect."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the ratio of signal energy per bit to noise power spectral density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bandwidth efficiency",
            "b) Spectral density",
            "c) Power efficiency",
            "d) Power density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In digital communication system, in order to increase noise immunity, it is necessary to increase signal power. However, the amount by which the signal power should be increased to obtain a certain level of fidelity depends on the particular type of modulation employed."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the ratio of the throughput data rate per Hertz?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bandwidth efficiency",
            "b) Spectral density",
            "c) Power efficiency",
            "d) Power density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Power efficiency is often expressed as the ratio of signal energy per bit to noise power spectral density required at the receiver input for a certain probability of error. Power efficiency is a measure of how favourably the trade-off between fidelity and signal power is made."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following is defined as the range of frequencies over which the signal has a non zero power spectral density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Null to null bandwidth",
            "b) Half power bandwidth",
            "c) 3 dB bandwidth",
            "d) Absolute bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is an unavoidable relationship between data rate and bandwidth occupancy. Increasing the data rate implies decreasing the pulse width of a digital symbol, which increases the bandwidth of the signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "_______ is equal to width of main spectral lobe.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Null to null bandwidth",
            "b) Half power bandwidth",
            "c) 3 dB bandwidth",
            "d) Absolute bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bandwidth efficiency reflects how efficiently the allocated bandwidth is utilized. It is defined as the ratio of throughput data rate per Hertz in a given bandwidth. It describes the ability of a modulation scheme to accommodate data within a limited bandwidth."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Half power bandwidth is also called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absolute bandwidth",
            "b) Null to null bandwidth",
            "c) 3 dB bandwidth",
            "d) Zero dB bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The absolute bandwidth is defined as the range of frequencies over which the signal has a non-zero power spectral density. For symbols represented as rectangular baseband pulses, the PSD profile extends over an infinite range of frequencies, and has an absolute bandwidth of infinity."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Intersymbol interference (ISI) leads to ________ probability of the receiver for making an error in detecting the symbols.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased",
            "b) Decreased",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) One"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ISI leads to increased probability of the receiver making an error in detecting a symbol. When rectangular pulses are passed through a bandlimited channel, the pulses will spread in time, and the pulse for each symbol will smear into the time intervals of succeeding symbols."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "ISI is ________ by increasing channel bandwidth.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximized",
            "b) Minimized",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) Infinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Increasing channel bandwidth is one of the method to minimize intersymbol interference. But mobile communication systems use minimal bandwidth, thus other methods to reduce ISI are desirable."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Why is pulse shaping technique used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase ISI",
            "b) To increase spectral width of modulated signal",
            "c) To reduce ISI",
            "d) To reduce power spectral density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pulse shaping techniques reduces the intersymbol interference. They are also used to reduce the spectral width of the modulated digital signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Who was the first to solve the problem of ISI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manchester",
            "b) Faraday",
            "c) Graham Bell",
            "d) Nyquist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nyquist was the first to solve the problem of ISI. He overcome the problem of ISI while keeping the transmission bandwidth low. He observed that ISI can be completely nullified if at every instant, the response due to all symbols except the current symbol is equal to zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "According to Nyquist, the impulse response of the overall communication system should have ______ decay with _______ magnitude for sample values not equal to zero.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast, small",
            "b) Slow, small",
            "c) Slow, large",
            "d) Fast. Large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to Nyquist, the impulse response of the overall communication system should have fast decay with small magnitude for sample values not equal to zero. If the channel is ideal then it should be possible to realize approximate shaping filters at both transmitter and receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "As the roll off factor in raised cosine rolloff filter __________ the occupied bandwidth ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases, decreases",
            "b) Decreases, constant",
            "c) Increases, increases",
            "d) Decreases, increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Raised cosine filter is the most popular pulse shaping filter used in mobile communication. It belongs to the class of filters that satisfy Nyquist criterion."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for a Gaussian filter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large bandwidth",
            "b) Minimum ISI",
            "c) High overshoot",
            "d) Sharp cut off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the rolloff factor increases, the bandwidth of the filter also increases and the time sidelobe levels decrease in adjacent symbol slots. Thus, it implies that increasing rolloff factor decreases the sensitivity to timing jitter but increases the occupied bandwidth."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "In linear modulation technique __________ of transmitted signal varies linearly with modulating digital signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Phase",
            "d) Angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In linear modulation technique, the amplitude of transmitted signal varies linearly with modulating digital signal. It is a form of digital modulation technique. "
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a linear modulation technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) OQPSK",
            "b) π/4 QPSK",
            "c) FSK",
            "d) BPSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Linear modulation techniques are bandwidth efficient. They are used in wireless communication systems when there is an increasing demand to accommodate more and more users within a limited spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "In BPSK, the ________ of constant amplitude carrier signal is switched between two values according to the two possible values.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Phase",
            "c) Frequency",
            "d) Angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: OQPSK, π/4 QPSK and BPSK are the most popular linear modulation techniques. They have very good spectral efficiency. However, FSK is an non-linear modulation technique."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "By applying cos(2πft), BPSK signal is equivalent to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double sideband suppressed carrier amplitude modulated waveform",
            "b) Single sideband suppressed carrier amplitude modulated waveform",
            "c) Frequency modulated waveform",
            "d) SSB amplitude waveform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In binary phase shift keying (BPSK), the phase of a constant amplitude carrier signal is switched between two possible values m1 and m2. These two values corresponds to binary 1 and 0 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "In DPSK system, input signal is differentially encoded and then modulated using a ________ modulator.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) BPSK",
            "d) QPSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The BPSK signal is equivalent to a double sideband suppressed carrier amplitude modulated waveform, where cos(2πft) is applied as the carrier. Hence, a BPSK signal can be generated using a balanced modulator."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "The energy efficiency of DPSK is _________ to coherent PSK.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superior",
            "b) Same",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) Inferior"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: BPSK uses coherent or synchronous demodulation. It requires the information about the phase and frequency of the carrier be available at the receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "QPSK has ________ the bandwidth efficiency of BPSK.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twice",
            "b) Same",
            "c) Half",
            "d) Four times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Differential phase shift keying uses noncoherent form of phase shift keying. Noncoherent form avoids the need for a coherent reference signal at the receiver. Noncoherent receivers are also easy and cheap to build."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "QPSK provides twice the bandwidth efficiency and _______ energy efficiency as compared to BPSK.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twice",
            "b) Half",
            "c) Same",
            "d) Four times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In DPSK system, input binary sequence is first differentially encoded and then modulated using a BPSK modulator. The differentially encoded sequence is generated from input binary sequence by complimenting their modulo-2 sum."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "What is the full form of OQPSK?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optical Quadrature Phase Shift Keying",
            "b) Orthogonal Quadrature Pulse Shift Keying",
            "c) Orthogonal Quadrature Phase Shift Keying",
            "d) Offset Quadrature Phase Shift Keying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The energy efficiency of DPSK is inferior to that of coherent PSK by about 3 dB. But, it has an advantage of reduced receiver complexity."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "The bandwidth of OQPSK is _______ to QPSK.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Identical",
            "b) Twice",
            "c) Half",
            "d) Four times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Quadrature phase shift keying (QPSK) has twice the bandwidth of BPSK. It is because two bits are transmitted in a single modulation symbol. The phase of the carrier takes on one of the four equally spaced values, where each value of phase corresponds to a unique pair of message bit."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a detection technique used for detection of π/4 QPSK signals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Baseband differential detection",
            "b) IF differential detection",
            "c) FM discriminator detection",
            "d) Envelope detection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bit error probability of QPSK is identical to BPSK but twice as much data can be sent in the same bandwidth. Thus, when compared to BPSK, QPSK provides twice the spectral efficiency with exactly the same efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Constant envelope modulation techniques occupy ______ bandwidth than linear modulation schemes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Larger",
            "b) Smaller",
            "c) Same",
            "d) Twice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In non-linear modulation, the amplitude of the carrier is constant regardless of the variation in the modulating signal. Many practical mobile radio communication systems use these types of nonlinear modulation methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "In BFSK __________ of constant amplitude carrier signal is switched between two values.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phase",
            "b) Angle",
            "c) Frequency",
            "d) Amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The constant envelope family of modulation has an advantage of satisfying various conditions. In this, power efficient Class C amplifiers can be used without introducing degradation in the spectrum occupancy of the transmitted signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "MSK stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum shift keying",
            "b) Minimum shift keying",
            "c) Minimum space keying",
            "d) Maximum space keying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Constant envelope modulation technique occupies a larger bandwidth than linear modulation technique. It is one of the disadvantage of constant envelope modulation. It is not well suited where bandwidth efficiency is more important than power efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "What is the modulation index of MSK?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In BFSK, the frequency of a constant amplitude carrier signal is switched between two values according to the two possible message states. These states are called high and low tunes, which corresponds to binary 1 or 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "The modulation index of an FSK signal is similar to modulation index of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude modulation",
            "b) Phase modulation",
            "c) QPSK",
            "d) Frequency modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MSK stands for minimum shift keying. It is a special type of continuous phase shift keying. It is form of digital modulation technique that was developed in 1950s."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "The name minimum phase shift keying implies minimum _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency separation",
            "b) Amplitude separation",
            "c) Phase change",
            "d) Amplitude deviation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Minimum shift keying is a special type of CPFSK. Its peak frequency deviation is equal to ¼ the bit rate. In other words, MSK is continuous phase FSK with a modulation index of 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "MSK is sometimes also referred as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slow FSK",
            "b) Fast FSK",
            "c) Slow PSK",
            "d) Fast PSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The modulation index of an FSK signal is similar to FM modulation index. It is defined by (2∆F)/Rb. Here ∆F is the peak RF frequency and Rb is the bit rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of MSK?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variable envelope",
            "b) Spectral efficiency",
            "c) Good BER performance",
            "d) Self synchronizing capability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The name minimum phase shift keying implies minimum frequency separation, i.e. the bandwidth that allows orthogonal detection. A modulation index of 0.5 corresponds to the minimum frequency spacing that allows two FSK signals to be coherently orthogonal."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "GMSK is a ________ of MSK.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integral",
            "b) Opposite",
            "c) Derivative",
            "d) Similar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Minimum shift keying is sometimes also referred as fast FSK. It is so called because frequency spacing used is only half as much as that used in conventional noncoherent frequency shift keying."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following holds true for GMSK?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum ISI",
            "b) Minimum error rate",
            "c) Good spectral efficiency",
            "d) Variable envelope property"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MSK has a constant envelope. It is a spectrally efficient scheme. It possesses properties such as constant envelope, spectral efficiency, good BER performance and self-synchronizing capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a combined linear and constant envelope technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MPSK",
            "b) PSK",
            "c) BPSK",
            "d) QPSK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: M-ary phase shift keying (MPSK) is a combined linear and constant envelope technique. It is a part of M-ary modulation techniques. These modern modulation techniques exploit the fact that digital baseband data may be sent by varying both the envelope and phase of an RF carrier."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "In an M-ary signalling scheme two or more bits are grouped together to form a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chip",
            "b) Symbol",
            "c) Byte",
            "d) Pattern"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In an M-ary signalling scheme two or more bits are grouped together to form symbols. And one of the M possible signals is transmitted during each symbol period of duration Ts."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "The number of possible signal in M-ary signalling is given by M and M = __________ where n is an integer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) n",
            "b) 2n",
            "c) 2n",
            "d) n2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two or more bits are grouped to form a symbol in M-ary modulation. And the number of possible symbols should be equal to 2n, where n is an integer."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "In M-ary PSK, the carrier ___________ takes one of M possible values.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Angle",
            "d) Phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Timing errors increase when smaller distances between signals in the constellation diagram are used. M-ary signalling techniques are attractive for use in bandlimited channel, but are limited in their applications due to sensitivity in timing jitter."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "The constellation of M-ary PSK is ____________ dimensional.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Does not exist",
            "c) Two",
            "d) Three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: M-ary modulation schemes have poor power efficiency, but they have a better bandwidth efficiency. An 8-PSK system requires a bandwidth that is 3 times smaller than a BPSK system, whereas its BER performance is very worse since signals are packed more closely in the signal constellation."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "What is the radius of the circle in M-ary PSK on which message points are equaly spaced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) √Es",
            "b) √Eb",
            "c) Eb",
            "d) Es"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In an M-ary PSK, the carrier phase takes one of the M possible values. The possible values of phase are θi=2(i-1)/M, where i=1,2,…….,M."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "As the value of M _________ the bandwidth efficiency ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases, same.",
            "b) Increases, decreases",
            "c) Increases, increases",
            "d) Decreases, same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The constellation of M-ary PSK is two dimensional. It is due to the presence of two basis signals. And the M-ary message points are equally spaced on a circle."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "The power efficiency of the M ary PSK decreases because of the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freely packed constellation",
            "b) Increment of bandwidth efficiency",
            "c) Fixed null bandwidth",
            "d) Densely packed constellation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The M-ary message points are equally spaced on a circle of radius √Es centred at the origin.  Here Es is energy per symbol. Thus, MPSK is a constant envelope signal when no pulse shaping is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "In QAM, the amplitude is _______ and phase is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Varied, constant",
            "b) Varied, varied",
            "c) Constant, varied",
            "d) Constant, constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first null bandwidth of M-ary PSK signals decrease as M increases while Rb is held constant. Therefore, as the value of M increases, the bandwidth efficiency also increases. "
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "In comparison to M-ary PSK, M-ary QAM bandwidth efficiency is _____ and power efficiency is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Identical, superior",
            "b) Less, superior",
            "c) Identical, identical",
            "d) Superior, superior"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bandwidth efficiency increases as the value of M increases. But at the same time, increasing M implies that the constellation is more densely packed. Hence the power efficiency or noise tolerance is decreased."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "The bandwidth efficiency of an M-ary FSK signal ________ with ________ in M.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant, increase",
            "b) Increases, increase",
            "c) Decreases, increase",
            "d) Decreases, decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Quadrature amplitude modulation (QAM) is obtained by allowing the amplitude to also vary with the phase. Thus, the constellation consists of square lattice of signal points."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Power efficiency of M-ary FSK increases, since _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constellation is densely packed",
            "b) M signals are non-orthogonal",
            "c) Fixed null bandwidth",
            "d) M-signals are orthogonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: M-ary QAM does not have constant energy per symbol. It also does not have constant distance between possible symbol states. It reasons that particular values of M-ary QAM signal will be detected with higher probability than others."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Why spread spectrum technique is inefficient for a single user?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large transmission bandwidth",
            "b) Small transmission bandwidth",
            "c) Fixed transmission bandwidth",
            "d) Fixed null bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spread spectrum techniques employ a transmission bandwidth that is several orders of magnitude greater than the minimum required signal bandwidth. On the other hand, primary objective of all the modulation schemes is to minimize the required transmission bandwidth."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of spread spectrum techniques?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interference rejection capability",
            "b) Multipath fading",
            "c) Frequency planning elimination",
            "d) Multiple user, multiple access interface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spread spectrum systems are bandwidth inefficient for single users. But in spread spectrum systems, many users can simultaneously use the same bandwidth without significantly interfering with one another. It is one of the advantages of spread spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of PN sequence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nearly equal number of 0s and1s",
            "b) Low correlation between shifted version of sequence",
            "c) Non deterministic",
            "d) Low cross-correlation between any two sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Resistance to multipath fading is one of the fundamental reasons for considering spread spectrum systems for wireless communication. Since spread spectrum signals have uniform energy over a very large bandwidth, at any given time only a small portion of the spectrum will undergo fading."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "The period of a PN sequence produced by a linear m stage shift register cannot exceed _____ symbols.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2m",
            "b) m",
            "c) 2m",
            "d) 2m-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pseudo-Noise sequences are deterministic in nature. Certain characteristics of PN sequence are nearly equal number of 0s and 1s, very low correlation between shifted versions of the sequence, very low cross correlation between any two sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "DSSS system spreads the baseband signal by ________ the baseband pulses with a pseudo noise sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adding",
            "b) Subtracting",
            "c) Multiplying",
            "d) Dividing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PN sequence is usually generated using sequential logic circuits. When the feedback logic consists of exclusive OR gates, the shift register is called a linear PN sequence generator."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Frequency hopping involves a periodic change of transmission _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Phase",
            "d) Amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are exactly 2m-1 non-zero states for an m stage feedback shift register. Thus, the period of a PN sequence produced by a linear m stage shift register cannot exceed 2m-1."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "What is the set of possible carrier frequencies in FH-SS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hopset",
            "b) Hop",
            "c) Chips",
            "d) Symbols"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A direct sequence spread spectrum (DS-SS) system spreads the baseband data by directly multiplying the baseband data pulses with a pseudo noise sequence. And the pseudo noise sequence is produced by a pseudo noise code generator."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "The bandwidth of the channel used in the hopset is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hopping bandwidth",
            "b) Total hopping bandwidth",
            "c) Instantaneous bandwidth",
            "d) 3 dB bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frequency hopping involves a periodic change of transmission frequency. A frequency hopping signal is regarded as a sequence of modulated data bursts with time varying, pseudo random carrier frequencies."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "The processing gain of FH systems is given by ratio of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hopping bandwidth and hopping period",
            "b) Instantaneous bandwidth and hopping duration",
            "c) 3 dB bandwidth and bit rate",
            "d) Total hopping bandwidth and instantaneous bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The set of possible carrier frequencies in FH-SS is called hopset. Hopping occurs of a frequency band that includes a number of channels. Each channel is defined as a spectral region with central frequency in the hopset."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Which of the following is specified by a specific number of bit errors occurring in a given transmission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bit error rate",
            "b) Equally likely event",
            "c) Outage event",
            "d) Exhaustive events"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bit error rate does not provide information about the type of error. However, bit error rate (BER) evaluation gives a good indication of the performance of a particular modulation scheme."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Irreducible BER floor is created in frequency selective channels due to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intersymbol interference",
            "b) Random spectral spreading",
            "c) Time varying Doppler spread",
            "d) Blind speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Outage event is specified by a specific number of bit errors occurring in a given transmission. Evaluating the probability of outage is one of the means to judge the effectiveness of the signalling scheme in a mobile radio channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Irreducible BER floor is created in non frequency selective channels due to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intersymbol interference",
            "b) Multipath time delay",
            "c) Time varying Doppler spread",
            "d) Blind speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency selective fading is caused due to multipath delay spread which causes intersymbol interference. It results in an irreducible BER floor for mobile systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "The performance of BPSK is best is term of BER because _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Symbol offset interference does not exist",
            "b) Existence of cross rail interference",
            "c) No multipath delay",
            "d) Doppler spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Even if a mobile channel is not frequency selective, the tie varying Doppler spread due to motion creates an irreducible BER floor. It is caused due random spectral spreading."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which of the following do not impact bit error rate in mobile communication systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mobile velocity",
            "b) Channel delay spread",
            "c) Modulation format",
            "d) Base station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: BER performance of BPSK is best among all the modulation schemes compared. This is because symbol offset interference does not exist in BPSK. Symbol offset interference is also called cross rail interference due to the fact that the eye diagram has multiple rails."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Coherence time refers to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time required attaining a call with the busy base station",
            "b) Time required for synchronization between the transmitter and the receiver",
            "c) Minimum time for change in magnitude and phase of the channel",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High capacity mobile systems are interference limited, but they are not noise limited. It was clearly seen that when carrier to interference ratio (C/I) is large, the errors are primarily due to fading, and interference has very little effect. However, as C/I drops below a certain level, interference dominates the link performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Doppler spread refers to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal fading due to Doppler shift in the channel",
            "b) Temporary failure of message transfer",
            "c) Large coherence time of the channel as compared to the delay constraints",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The mobile velocity, channel delay spread, interference levels and modulation formats all independently impact the raw bit error rate in mobile communication systems. And simulation is a powerful way to design or predict the performance of wireless communication links."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "A rake receiver uses multiple ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay circuits",
            "b) Correlators",
            "c) Detectors",
            "d) Flip flops"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coherence time is the time required for synchronization between the transmitter and receiver. It is the over which a propagating wave is said to be coherent."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used to improve received signal quality over small scale times and distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation",
            "b) Equalization",
            "c) Diversity",
            "d) Channel coding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Equalization, diversity and channel coding are the three techniques which are used to improve received signal quality and link performance over small scale times and distance. But, the approach, cost, complexity and effectiveness varies in wireless communication system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Equalization is used to compensate __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peak signal to noise ratio",
            "b) Intersymbol interference",
            "c) Channel fading",
            "d) Noises present in the signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Equalization compensate the intersymbol interference (ISI) created by multipath within time dispersive channels. An equalizer within a receiver compensates for the average range of the expected channel amplitude and delay characteristics. "
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Training and tracking are the operating modes of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diversity techniques",
            "b) Channel coding techniques",
            "c) Equalization techniques",
            "d) Demodulation techniques"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: General operating modes of an adaptive equalizer includes training and tracking. A known fixed length training sequence is sent by the transmitter so that the receiver’s equalizer may adapt to a proper setting for minimum bit error rate detection. "
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "An equalizer is said to be converged when it is properly _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trained",
            "b) Tracked",
            "c) Installed",
            "d) Used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When an equalizer has been properly trained, it is said to have converged. Equalizers are commonly used in digital communication systems where user data is segmented into short time blocks or time slots. "
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Time for convergence of an equalizer is not a function of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equalizer algorithm",
            "b) Equalizer structure",
            "c) Time rate of change of multipath radio channel",
            "d) Transmitter characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The timespan over which an equalizer converges is a function of the equalizer algorithm, the equalizer structure and the time rate of change of the multipath radio channel. Equalizers require proper retraining in order to maintain effective ISI cancellation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Equalizer is usually implemented in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmitter",
            "b) Baseband or at IF in a receiver",
            "c) Radio channel",
            "d) Modulator stage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An equalizer is implemented at baseband or at IF in a receiver. Since the baseband complex envelope expression can be used to represent bandpass waveform, the channel response, the demodulated signal and adaptive equalizer algorithm are usually simulated and implemented at baseband. "
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Equalizer is ________ of the channel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Opposite",
            "b) Same characteristics",
            "c) Inverse filter",
            "d) Add on"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An equalizer is actually an inverse filter of the channel. The goal of equalization is to satisfy that the combination of the transmitter, channel and receiver be an all pass channel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "______ controls the adaptive algorithm in an equalizer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Error signal",
            "b) Transmitted signal",
            "c) Received signal",
            "d) Channel impulse response"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The adaptive algorithm is controlled by the error signal. The error signal is derived by comparing the output of the equalizer and some signal which is either an exact scaled replica of the transmitted signal or represents a property of transmitted signal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "The adaptive algorithms in equalizer that do not require training sequence are called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear adaptive algorithms",
            "b) Blind algorithms",
            "c) Non-linear adaptive algorithms",
            "d) Spatially adaptive algorithms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Blind algorithms exploit the characteristics of the transmitted signal and do not require training sequence. These type of algorithm are able to acquire equalization through property restoral techniques of transmitted signal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a blind algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear adaptive algorithms",
            "b) Constant modulus algorithm",
            "c) Non-linear adaptive algorithms",
            "d) Spatially adaptive algorithms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Blind algorithm technique uses algorithms such as the constant modulus algorithm (CMA) and the spectral coherence restoral algorithm (SCORE). CMA is used for constant envelope modulation and forces the equalizer weights to maintain a constant envelope on the received signal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Equalization techniques can be categorised into _______ and ______ techniques.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear, non linear",
            "b) Active, passive",
            "c) Direct, indirect",
            "d) Slow, fast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Equalization techniques can be classified into linear and non linear techniques. These categories are determined from how the output of an adaptive equalizer is used for subsequent control of the equalizer."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "In the context of equalizers, LTE stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long transversal equalizer",
            "b) Least time-varying equalizer",
            "c) Linear transversal equalizer",
            "d) Linear time-varying equalizer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the analog signal is not used in the feedback path to adapt the equalizer, the equalization is linear. On the other hand, if it is fed back to change the subsequent outputs of the equalizer, the equalization is non-linear."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of FIR filter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Many zeroes",
            "b) Poles only at z=0",
            "c) Transfer function is a polynomial of z-1",
            "d) Many poles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most common equalizer structure used for equalization is linear transveral equalizer (LTE). It is made up of tapped delay lines, with the tappings speed a symbol period apart."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of lattice equalizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple structure",
            "b) Numerical stability",
            "c) Faster convergence",
            "d) Dynamic assignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Finite impulse response filter (FIR) has many zeroes but poles only at z=0. The transfer function of the filter is a polynomial of z-1. It is also referred to as transversal filter."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a non-linear equalization technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decision feedback equalization",
            "b) Maximum likelihood symbol detection",
            "c) Minimum square error detection",
            "d) Maximum likelihood sequence detection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The structure of lattice equalizer is more complicated than a linear transversal equalizer. But, numerical stability and faster convergence are two advantage of laatic equalizer. Also, its unique structure allows dynamic assignment of the most effective length of lattice equalizer."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not hold true for MLSE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimizes probability of sequence error",
            "b) Require knowledge of channel characteristics",
            "c) Requires the statistical distribution of noise",
            "d) Operates on continuous time signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Non-linear equalizers are used in applications where the channel distortion is too severe for a linear equalizer to handle. They are most commonly used in practical wireless communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor could not determine the performance of algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural properties",
            "b) Rate of convergence",
            "c) Computational complexity",
            "d) Numerical properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The performance of an algorithm is determined by various factors. These factors are rate of convergence, computational complexity and numerical properties. The performance of algorithm does not depend on structural properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Rate of convergence is defined by __________ of algorithm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time span",
            "b) Number of iterations",
            "c) Accuracy",
            "d) Complexity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rate of convergence is required as number of iterations required for the algorithm to converge close enough to the optimum solution. It enables the algorithm to track statistical variations when operating in non stationary environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Computational complexity is a measure of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Number of iterations",
            "c) Number of operations",
            "d) Accuracy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Computational complexity is the number of operations required to make one complete iteration of the algorithm. It helps in comparing the performance with other algorithms."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Choice of equalizer structure and its algorithm is not dependent on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost of computing platform",
            "b) Power budget",
            "c) Radio propagation characteristics",
            "d) Statistical distribution of transmitted power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cost of the computing platform, the power budget and the radio propagation characteristics dominate the choice of an equalizer structure and its algorithm. Battery drain at the subscriber unit is also a paramount consideration."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an algorithm for equalizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero forcing algorithm",
            "b) Least mean square algorithm",
            "c) Recursive least square algorithm",
            "d) Mean square error algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The choice of algorithm and its corresponding rate of convergence depends on the channel data rate and coherence time. The speed of the mobile unit determines the channel fading rate and the Doppler spread, which is directly related to coherence time of the channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a drawback of zero forcing algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long training sequence",
            "b) Amplification of noise",
            "c) Not suitable for static channels",
            "d) Non zero ISI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Three classic equalizer algorithm are zero forcing (ZF) algorithm, least mean squares (LMS) algorithm and recursive least squares (RLS) algorithm. They offer fundamental insight into algorithm design and operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "LMS equalizer minimizes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Computational complexity",
            "b) Cost",
            "c) Mean square error",
            "d) Power density of output signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The zero forcing algorithm has the disadvantage that the inverse filter may excessively amplify noise at frequencies where the folded channel spectrum has high attenuation."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "For N symbol inputs, LMS algorithm requires ______ operations per iterations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2N",
            "b) N+1",
            "c) 2N+1",
            "d) N2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ZF is not often used in wireless links as it neglects the effect of noise altogether. However, it performs well for static channels with high SNR, such as local wired telephone links."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Stochastic gradient algorithm is also called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero forcing algorithm",
            "b) Least mean square algorithm",
            "c) Recursive least square algorithm",
            "d) Mean square error algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: LMS equalizer is a robust equalizer. It is used to minimize mean square error (MSE) between the desired equalizer output and the actual equalizer output."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not hold true for RLS algorithms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complex",
            "b) Adaptive signal processing",
            "c) Slow convergence rate",
            "d) Powerful"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The LMS algorithm is the simplest algorithm. For N symbol inputs, it requires only 2N+1 operations per iteration."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Which of the following algorithm uses simple programming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LMS Gradient DFE",
            "b) FTF algorithm",
            "c) Fast Kalman DFE",
            "d) Gradient Lattice DFE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimization of the MSE is carried out recursively, and it can be performed by the use of stochastic gradient algorithm. This more commonly called the least mean square (LMS) algorithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Diversity decisions are made by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Receiver",
            "b) Transmitter",
            "c) Channel",
            "d) Adaptive algorithms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike equalization, diversity requires no training overhead since a training sequence is not required by the transmitter. Diversity is a powerful communication receiver technique that provides wireless link improvement at a relatively low cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Small scale fades are characterized by ____________ amplitude fluctuations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large",
            "b) Small",
            "c) Rapid",
            "d) Slow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In virtually all applications, diversity decisions are made by the receiver and are unknown to the transmitter. Diversity exploits the random nature of radio propagation by finding independent signal paths for communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "____________ is used to prevent deep fade for rapidly varying channel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation",
            "b) Demodulation",
            "c) Macroscopic diversity technique",
            "d) Microscopic diversity technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Small scale fades are characterized by deep and rapid fluctuations. They occur as the mobile system moves over distances of just a few wavelengths. These fades are caused by multiple reflections from the surrounding in the vicinity of the mobile."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "Large scale fading can be mitigated with the help of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation",
            "b) Demodulation",
            "c) Macroscopic diversity technique",
            "d) Microscopic diversity technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In order to prevent deep fades from occurring, microscopic diversity techniques can exploit the rapidly changing signal. By selecting the best signal at all times, a receiver can mitigate small scale fading effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Space diversity s also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antenna diversity",
            "b) Time diversity",
            "c) Frequency diversity",
            "d) Polarization diversity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Large scale fading is mitigated with macroscopic diversity techniques. It is done by selecting a base station which is not shadowed when others are, the mobile can improve substantially the average signal to noise ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a category of space diversity technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Selection diversity",
            "b) Time diversity",
            "c) Feedback diversity",
            "d) Equal gain diversity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Space diversity is also known as antenna diversity. It is one of the popular forms of diversity used in wireless communications. Signals received from the spatially separated antenna on the mobile would have essentially uncorrelated envelopes for antenna separation."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Polarization diversity uses the ________ as the diversity element.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation index",
            "b) Carrier frequency",
            "c) Reflection coefficient",
            "d) Coherence time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Space diversity reception methods can be classified into four categories. They are selection diversity, feedback diversity, maximal ratio combining and equal gain diversity."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Which of the factor does not determine the correlation coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polarization angle",
            "b) Cross polarization discrimination",
            "c) Offset angle from the main beam direction",
            "d) Coherence time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Selection diversity uses m demodulators to provide m diversity branches. Their gain is adjusted to provide the same average SNR for each branch."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Frequency diversity is implemented by transmitting information on more than one ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carrier frequency",
            "b) Amplitude",
            "c) Phase",
            "d) Modulation scheme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Decorrelation of the signal in each polarization is caused by multiple reflections in the channel between mobile and base station antenna. Reflection coefficient for each polarization is different, which results in different amplitudes and phases for each reflection."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Frequency diversity uses ________ as a diversity element.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Correlation coefficient",
            "b) Coherence time",
            "c) Coherence bandwidth",
            "d) SNR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correlation coefficient is determined by three factors, polarization angle, offset angle from the main beam direction of the diversity antenna, and the cross polarization discrimination. The correlation coefficient generally becomes higher as offset angle becomes large."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Time diversity repeatedly transmits information at time spacings that exceed ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coherence bandwidth",
            "b) Dwell time",
            "c) Run time",
            "d) Coherence time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency diversity is implemented by transmitting information on more than one carrier frequency. Frequency diversity is often employed in microwave line of sight links which carry several channels in frequency division multiplex mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "In maximal ratio combining, the output SNR is equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean of all individual SNRs",
            "b) Maximum of all SNRs",
            "c) Sum of individual SNR",
            "d) Minimum of all SNRs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rationale behind the frequency diversity is that frequencies separated by more than the coherence bandwidth of the channel will be uncorrelated. Thus, they will not experience the same fade."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "A RAKE receiver collects the __________ versions of the original signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time shifted",
            "b) Amplitude shifted",
            "c) Frequency shifted",
            "d) Phase shifted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In CDMA spread spectrum systems, the chip rate is typically much greater than the flat fading bandwidth of the channel. Whereas conventional modulation techniques require an equalizer to undo intersymbol interference between adjacent channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "RAKE receiver uses separate _________ to provide the time shifted version of the signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) IF receiver",
            "b) Equalizer",
            "c) Correlation receiver",
            "d) Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RAKE receiver attempts to collect the time shifted versions of the original signal. It is due to the fact that there is useful information present in the multipath components."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Each correlation receiver in RAKE receiver is adjusted in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency shift",
            "b) Amplitude change",
            "c) Phase shift",
            "d) Time delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RAKE receiver uses separate correlation receivers to provide the time shifted version of the original signal for each of the multipath signal. CDMA receivers combine these time shifted versions of the original signal to transmission in order to improve the signal to noise ratio of the receiver."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "The range of time delays that a particular correlator can search is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Search window",
            "b) Sliding window",
            "c) Time span",
            "d) Dwell time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Each correlation receiver may be adjusted in time delay, so that a microprocessor controller can cause different correlation receivers to search in different time windows for significant multipath."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "RAKE receiver is used for _______ technique.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CDMA",
            "b) TDMA",
            "c) FDMA",
            "d) OFDM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The range of time delays that a particular correlator an search is called a search window. RAKE receiver attempts to collect the time shifted version of the original signal by providing a separate correlation receiver for each of the multipath signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "A RAKE receiver uses __________ to separately detect the M strongest signals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single correlator",
            "b) Multiple correlator",
            "c) Single IF receiver",
            "d) Multiple IF receivers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RAKE receiver is essentially a diversity receiver which is used specifically for CDMA. It uses the fact that the multipath components are practically uncorrelated from one another when their relative propagation delays exceed a chip period."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "A RAKE receiver uses __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equalization",
            "b) Channel coding",
            "c) Diversity",
            "d) Encryption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A RAKE receiver uses multiple correlators to separately detect the M strongest multipath components. Demodulation and bit decisions are then based on the weighted ouputs of the M correlators."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Interleaving is used to obtain ___________ diversity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Polarization",
            "d) Antenna"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a RAKE receiver, if the output from one correlator is corrupted by fading, the others may not be. And the corrupted signal may be discounted through weighting process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "In block codes, parity bits are ___________ to block of messages.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Added",
            "b) Subtracted",
            "c) Multiplied",
            "d) Divided"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In block codes, parity bits are added to the block of message bits to make codewords or code blocks. They enable a limited number of errors to be detected and corrected without retransmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "How many redundant bits are added in block codes for k information bits and n code bits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) n+k",
            "b) n-k",
            "c) k2",
            "d) n2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In block encoder, k information bits are encoded into n code bits. A total of n-k redundant bits are added to the k information bits for the purpose of detecting and correcting errors."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "For (n,k) block codes, rate of the code is defined as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) n2/k",
            "b) k2/n",
            "c) n/k",
            "d) k/n"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The block code is referred to as an (n,k) code, and the rate of the code is defined as R=n/k. It is equal to the rate of information divided by the raw channel rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "The ability of the block code to correct errors is a function of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of parity bits",
            "b) Number of information bits",
            "c) Number of code bits",
            "d) Code distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ability of a block code to correct errors is a function of the code distance. Block codes can be used to improve the performance of communication systems when other means of improvement are impractical."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "The weight of code is given by number of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-zero elements in the codeword",
            "b) Zero elements in the codeword",
            "c) Total elements in the codeword",
            "d) Elements in parity bits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The weight of a code is given by number of non-zero elements in the codeword. For a binary code, the weight is basically the number of ones in the codeword."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of block code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linearity",
            "b) Systematic",
            "c) Cyclic",
            "d) Non linearity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Block codes are linear, systematic and cyclic in nature. Encoding and decoding techniques make use of mathematical constructs known as finite fields."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "In systematic codes, parity bits are appended at the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beginning",
            "b) End",
            "c) End",
            "d) Odd places"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A systematic code is one in which the parity bits are appended to the end of the information bits. For an (n,k) code, the first k bits are identical to the information bits, and the remaining (n-k) bits of each code word are linear combinations of k information bits."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of block code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hamming code",
            "b) Cyclic code",
            "c) Convolution code",
            "d) BCH codes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hamming codes, cyclic codes and BCH codes are the example of block codes. Convolution code does not come in the category of block code. Some other examples of block codes are Reed Solomon codes, Golay codes and Hadamard codes."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Which of the following code is a class of non-binary BCH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hamming code",
            "b) Hadamard code",
            "c) Golay code",
            "d) Reed Solomon codes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most important and most common class of non binary is the family of codes known as Reed Solomon codes. BCH codes are among the most popular block codes that exist for a wide range of rates, achieve significant coding gains."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Which of the following linear codes achieve largest possible minimum distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hamming code",
            "b) Hadamard code",
            "c) Golay code",
            "d) Reed Solomon codes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RS codes achieve the largest possible minimum distance, dmin of any linear code. They are non-binary codes which are capable of correcting errors that appears in bursts."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "CDPD stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellular Digital Packet Data",
            "b) Cellular Decoded Packet Data",
            "c) Cellular Demodulated Packet Data",
            "d) Cellular Decoded Plane Data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CDPD (Cellular Digital Packet Data) is a wide area mobile data service which uses unused bandwidth. It was mostly used in AMPS phones. Reed Solomon code in US CDPD uses m=6 bits per code symbol."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Which of the following indicates the number of input bits that the current output is dependent upon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constraint length",
            "b) Code length",
            "c) Search window",
            "d) Information rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Convolution code can achieve a larger coding gain that can be achieved using a block coding with the same complexity. Their mapping is highly structured, enabling a decoding method considerably different from block codes."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way to represent convolution code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) State diagram",
            "b) Trellis diagram",
            "c) Tree diagram",
            "d) Linear matrix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Constraint length determines the number of input data bits that the current output is dependent upon. The constraint length determines how powerful and complex the code is."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an algorithm for decoding convolution codes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viterbi algorithm",
            "b) Stack algorithm",
            "c) Fano’s sequential coding",
            "d) Ant colony optimization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Linear matrix is not a way to represent convolution code. Various ways of representing convolution codes are generator matrix, generator polynomial, logic tables, state diagram, tree diagram and trellis diagram."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Viterbi algorithm performs ____________ decoding of convolutional codes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum likelihood",
            "b) Maximum a posteriori",
            "c) Minimum square",
            "d) Minimum mean square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are a number of techniques for decoding convolution codes. The most important of these methods is Viterbi algorithm. Other decoding algorithms for convolutional codes are Fano’s sequential coding, stack algorithm and feedback coding."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Fano’s algorithm in comparison to Viterbi’s algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less storage",
            "b) Large constraint length",
            "c) Error rate",
            "d) Small delays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Viterbi algorithm performs maximum likelihood decoding of convolutional codes. The algorithm was first developed by A.J. Viterbi. It is one of the most important algorithm used for decoding convolutional codes."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an error correction and detection code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Block code",
            "b) Convolutional codes",
            "c) Passive codes",
            "d) Turbo codes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fano’s algorithm searches for the most probable path through the trellis diagram by examining one path at a time. The error rate performance of Fano’s algorithm is comparable to Viterbi’s algorithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which decoding method involves the evaluation by means of Fano’s algorithm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum Likelihood Decoding",
            "b) Sequential Decoding",
            "c) Maximum a priori",
            "d) Minimum mean square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In comparison to Viterbi decoding, sequential decoding has a significantly larger delay. In advantage over Viterbi decoding is that it requires less storage, and thus codes with larger constraint lengths can be employed."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "In Viterbi’s algorithm, the selected paths are regarded as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Survivors",
            "b) Defenders",
            "c) Destroyers",
            "d) Carriers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In comparison to Fano’s algorithm, the stack algorithm is computationally simpler since there is no retracting over the same path. But stack algorithm requires more storage than Fano’s algorithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of the following are two types of speech coders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waveform coders and source coders",
            "b) Active coders and passive coders",
            "c) Direst coders and indirect coders",
            "d) Time and frequency coders"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lower the bit rate at which the coder can deliver toll quality speech, the more speech channels can be compressed within a given bandwidth. Thus, manufacturers are continuously in search of speech coders that provide toll quality speech at lower bit rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Waveform coders has _______ complexity and achieves _______ economy in transmission bit rate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum, moderate",
            "b) Maximum, high",
            "c) Minimal, moderate",
            "d) Minimal, high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Speech coders can be categorised into waveform coders and source coders. Waveform coders can further be categorised into time domain and frequency domain. Source coders can be classified into linear predictive coders and vocoders."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Vocoders has _______ complexity and achieves _______ economy in transmission bit rate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum, moderate",
            "b) Maximum, high",
            "c) Minimal, moderate",
            "d) Minimal, high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Waveform coders have minimal complexity. This class of coders achieves only moderate economy in transmission bit rate. They are designed to be source independent and hence code equally well a variety of signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property that is utilized in coder design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non zero autocorrelation between successive speech signals",
            "b) Non flat nature of speech signal",
            "c) Quasiperiodicity of voiced speech signals",
            "d) Uniform probability distribution of speech amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vocoders achieve very high economy in transmission bit rate. They are in general more complex. They are based on using a priori knowledge about the signal to be coded, and for this reason, they are signal specific."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Speech waveforms are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bandlimited",
            "b) Bandpass",
            "c) High pass",
            "d) Infinite bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Speech waveforms have a number of useful properties that can be exploited when designing efficient coders. They are non uniform probability distribution of speech amplitude, non-zero autocorrelation between successive speech samples, the nonflat nature of the speech spectra and quasiperiodicity of voiced speech signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of pdf of speech signals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non uniformity",
            "b) Very high probability of non-zero amplitudes",
            "c) Significant probability of very high amplitudes",
            "d) Increasing function of amplitudes between these extremes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most basic property of speech waveforms that are exploited by all speech coders is that they are bandlimited. A finite bandwidth means that it can be time-discretized at a finite rate and reconstructed complexity from its samples."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Auto correlation function measures______ between samples of a speech signal as a function of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Similarity, frequency",
            "b) Dissimilarity, time",
            "c) Similarity, time",
            "d) Dissimilarity, frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is a non-uniform probability distribution of speech amplitude. The pdf of a speech signal is in general characterized by a very high probability of non-zero amplitudes, a significant probability of very high amplitudes, and a monotonically decreasing function of amplitudes between these extremes."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Spectral flatness measure is the ratio of ______ and _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variance, Geometric mean",
            "b) Geometric Mean, Variance",
            "c) Arithmetic mean, geometric mean",
            "d) Geometric mean, arithmetic mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The autocorrelation function (ACF) gives a quantitative measure of the closeness or similarity between samples of a speech signal as a function of their time separation. In every sample of speech, there is a large component that is easily predicted from the values of the previous samples."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Quantization is a process of mapping a ________ range of amplitude of a signal into a finite set of __________ amplitudes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous, discrete",
            "b) Discrete, continuous",
            "c) Discrete, discrete",
            "d) Continuous, continuous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Quantization is a process of mapping a continuous range of amplitude of a signal into a finite set of discrete amplitudes. Quantizers are the devices that remove the irrelevancies in the signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "For a n bit quantizer, number of levels is equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) n",
            "b) 2n",
            "c) n2",
            "d) 2n"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A quantizer that uses n bits can have M = 2n discrete amplitude levels. Amplitude quantization is an important step in any speech coding process, and it determines to a great extent the overall distortion as well as bit rate necessary to represent each waveform."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "Distortion produced by quantization is directly proportion to ________ and inversely proportional to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of levels, step size",
            "b) Amplitude of the signal, step size",
            "c) Square of step size, number of levels",
            "d) Amplitude of the signal, number of levels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The distortion introduced by any quantization operation is directly proportional to the square of the step size. It is inversely proportional to the number of levels for a given amplitude range."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Signal to quantization noise ratio of a PCM encoder is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.02n + α",
            "b) 3n + 6.02α",
            "c) n + 6.02α",
            "d) 6.02n + α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Signal to quantization noise (SQNR) ratio of a PCM encoder is related to the number of bits, n used for encoding. It follows the following relation, SQNR= 6.02n + α. Here, α = 4.77 dB for peak SQNR and α = 0 dB for average SQNR."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Companding technique used in the US is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ law",
            "b) A law",
            "c) Hybrid companding",
            "d) Direct companding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Companding technique known as μ law is used in US. In Europe, A law companding technique is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "An adaptive quantizer varies its ___________ in accordance to input speech signal power.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Level",
            "b) Step size",
            "c) Amplitude",
            "d) Frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An adaptive quantizer varies its step size in accordance to the input speech signal power. Its characteristics shrink and expand in time like an accordion."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "________ is a delayed decision coding technique.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adaptive quantization",
            "b) Uniform quantization",
            "c) Vector quantization",
            "d) Non-uniform quantization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Shannon predicted that better performance can be achieved by coding many samples at a time instead of one sample at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "The characteristics of compressor in μ-law companding are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous in nature",
            "b) Logarithmic in nature",
            "c) Linear in nature",
            "d) Discrete in nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vector (VQ) quantization is a delayed decision coding technique. It maps a group of input samples called a vector to a code book index. A code book is set up consisting of a finite set of vectors covering the entire anticipated range of values."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "What is the sequence of operations in PCM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sampling, quantizing, encoding",
            "b) Quantizing, encoding, sampling",
            "c) Quantizing, sampling, encoding",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the μ law companding, the compressor characteristic is continuous. It approximates the linear dependence on x for low input signals and a logarithmic one for high input signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "In Adaptive Delta Modulation, the slope error reduces and ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quantization error decreases",
            "b) Quantization error increases",
            "c) Quantization error remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sequence of operation in PCM is sampling, quantization and encoding. Sampling and quantizing operations transform an analogue signal to a digital signal. The quantizing and encoding operations are usually performed in the same circuit at the transmitter, which is called an Analogue to Digital Converter (ADC). At the receiver end the decoding operation converts the pulse back into an analogue voltage in a Digital to Analogue Converter (DAC). "
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Frequency domain coders divides the speech signal into __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A set of frequency components",
            "b) A set of different amplitudes",
            "c) A set of time delays",
            "d) A set of phase components"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the class of frequency domain coders, the speech signal is divided into a set of frequency components. Each frequency component is quantized and encoded separately."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Quantization is a ________ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Direct",
            "c) Non-linear",
            "d) Indirect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frequency domain coders have an advantage that number of bits used to encode each frequency component can be dynamically varied. They can also be shared among different bands."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which of the following is one of the most frequently used transform in speech coding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier transform",
            "b) Wavelet transform",
            "c) Shearlet transform",
            "d) Discrete cosine transform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Quantization is a non-linear process. It produces distortion products that are typically broad in spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "What does ATC stands for in speech coders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Automatic transform code",
            "b) Air traffic controller",
            "c) Active thermal convection",
            "d) Adaptive transform coding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is function of block transform coding. However, a sub band coder divides the speech signal into many smaller sub bands and encodes each sub band separately according to some perceptual criterion."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Waveform coders and Vocoders are the types of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speech coders",
            "b) Modulation technique",
            "c) Frequency translation methods",
            "d) Channel allocation for transmission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DCT (discrete cosine transform) is one of the most attractive and frequently used transforms for speech coding. Fast algorithms developed for computing the DCT in a computationally efficient manner are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "The type of frequency domain coding that divides the speech signal into sub bands is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waveform coding",
            "b) Vocoders",
            "c) Block transform coding",
            "d) Sub-band coding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In speech coding, ATC stands for adaptive transform coding. It is form of frequency domain coder that encodes the speech at bit rates in the range of 9.6 kbps and 20 kbps."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Speech coders are categorized on the basis of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal compression techniques",
            "b) Frequency of signal",
            "c) Bandwidth of the signal",
            "d) Phase of the signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Speech coders can be classified into waveform coders and Vocoders. Waveform coders convert the analog signal into digital signal. Vocoders exploit the special properties of speech signal to reduce the bit rate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "The speech coding technique that is dependent on the prior knowledge of the signal is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waveform coders",
            "b) Vocoders",
            "c) Sub band coding",
            "d) Block transform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sub band coding (SBC) is a method where the speech signal is subdivided into several frequency bands and each band is digitally encoded separately. The audible frequency spectrum 20Hz-20 KHz is divided into frequency sub-bands using a bank of finite impulse response (FIR) filter and output of each filter is sampled and encoded. "
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Vocoders analyse the speech signals at ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmitter",
            "b) Receiver",
            "c) Channel",
            "d) IF Filter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vocoders are a class of speech coding systems. They analyse the speech signal at the transmitter. And then transmit the parameters derived from the analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Vocoders __________ the voice at the receiver.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analyse",
            "b) Synthesize",
            "c) Modulate",
            "d) Evaluate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vocoders synthesize the voice at the receiver. All vocoder systems attempt to model the speech generation process as a dynamic system and try to quantify certain physical constraints of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a vocoding system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear predictive coder",
            "b) Channel vocoder",
            "c) Waveform coder",
            "d) Formant vocoder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vocoders are much more complex than the waveform coders. They can achieve very high economy in transmission bit rate but are less robust."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "Which of the following pronunciations lead to voiced sound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ‘f’",
            "b) ‘s’",
            "c) ‘sh’",
            "d) ‘m’"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Waveform coder is not a vocoding system. LPC (linear predictive coding) is the most popular vocoding system. Other vocoding systems are channel vocoder, formant vocoder, cepstrum vocoder etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Speech signal can be categorised in _____ and ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voiced, unvoiced",
            "b) Active, passive",
            "c) Direct, indirect",
            "d) Balanced, unbalanced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Voiced sounds are ‘m’, ‘n’ and ‘v’ pronounciations. They are a result of quasiperiodic vibrations of the vocal chord."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "________ is often called the formant of the speech signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch frequency",
            "b) Voice pitch",
            "c) Pole frequency",
            "d) Central frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Speech signal is of two types, voiced and unvoiced. Voiced sound is a result of quasiperiodic vibrations of the vocal chord. Unvoiced signals are fricatives produced by turbulent air flow through a constriction."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Cepstrum vocoder uses __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wavelet transform",
            "b) Inverse wavelet transform",
            "c) Cosine transform",
            "d) Inverse Fourier transform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Channel vocoders are frequency domain vocoders. They determine the envelope of the speech signal for a number of frequency bands and then sample, encode and multiplex these samples with the encoded outputs of the other filters."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Linear predictive coders belong to _______ domain class of vocoders.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Direct",
            "d) Indirect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Linear predictive vocoders belong to the time domain class of vocoders. This class of vocoders attempts to extract the significant features of the speech from the time waveform."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Linear predictive coding system models the vocal tract as __________ linear filter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pole and zero",
            "b) All zero",
            "c) All pole",
            "d) No pole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Linear predictive coders are computationally intensive. But, they are the most popular among the class of low bit vocoders. With LPC, it is possible to transmit good quality voice at 4.8 kbps and poorer quality voice at even lower rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Linear predictive vocoders use __________ to estimate present sample.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weighted sum of past samples",
            "b) Multiplication of past samples",
            "c) One past sample",
            "d) Do not use past samples"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The linear predictive coding system models the vocal tract as an all pole linear filter. The excitation to this filter is either a pulse at the pitch frequency or random white noise depending on whether the speech segment is voiced or unvoiced."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Which of the following LPC uses code book?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple excited LPC",
            "b) Residual excited LPC",
            "c) LPC Vocoders",
            "d) Code excited LPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The linear predictive coder uses a weighted sum of p past samples. Using this technique, the current sample can be written as linear sum of the immediately precoding samples."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "How many past samples are used by linear predictive coders to estimate present sample?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-150",
            "b) 10-15",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 1000-1100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Code excited LPC uses code book. In this method, the coder and decoder have a predetermined code book of stochastic (zero mean white Gaussian) excitation signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Which of the non-linear transform is generally used to improve the coding of reflection coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long area ratio transform",
            "b) Mutual information",
            "c) Least square",
            "d) Interpolation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LPCs uses weighted sum of past p samples to estimate the present samples. The number of past samples used by linear predictive coders ranges from 10 to 15."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which of the following LPC uses two sources at the receiver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple excited LPC",
            "b) Residual excited LPC",
            "c) LPC Vocoders",
            "d) Code excited LPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Long area ratio (LAR) transform is generally used to improve the coding of reflection coefficient. This non linear transformation reduces the sensitivity of reflection coefficients to quantization errors. LAR performs an inverse hyperbolic tangent mapping of reflection coefficients."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Which of the following LPC produces a buzzy twang in the synthesized speech?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple excited LPC",
            "b) Residual excited LPC",
            "c) LPC Vocoders",
            "d) Code excited LPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: LPC vocoder uses two sources at the receiver, one of white noise and the other with a series of pulses at the current pitch rate. The selection of either of these excitation methods is based on voiced/unvoiced decision made at the transmitter."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an important factor in determining spectral efficiency of the system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple access technique",
            "b) Cell size",
            "c) Modulation technique",
            "d) Vocoder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The choice of speech coder depends on the cell size used. When the cell size is sufficiently small such that high spectral efficiency is achieved through frequency reuse, it may be sufficient to use a simple high rate speech codec."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the name of original speech coder used in the pan European digital cellular standard GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multipulse excited codec",
            "b) Residual excited codec",
            "c) Regular pulse excited long term prediction",
            "d) Code excited codec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The type of multiple access technique used is an important factor in determining the spectral efficiency of the system. It strongly influences the choice of speech codec. "
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for baseband RELP codec?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good quality of speech, low complexity",
            "b) Good quality of speech, high complexity",
            "c) Bad quality of speech, low complexity",
            "d) Bad quality of speech, high complexity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The type of modulation employed has a considerable impact on the choice of speech codec. Using bandwidth efficient modulation scheme can lower the bit rate reduction requirements on the speech codec and vice versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for MPE-LTP codec?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good quality of speech, low complexity",
            "b) Good quality of speech, high complexity",
            "c) Bad quality of speech, low complexity",
            "d) Bad quality of speech, high complexity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The original speech coder used in the pan European digital cellular standard GSM goes by a rather grandiose name of regular pulse excited long term prediction (RPE-LTP) codec. This codec has a bit rate of 13 kbps."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Which of the following codec is used by IS-136?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Residual Excited Linear Predictive Coders",
            "b) Multipulse Excited LPC",
            "c) LPC Vocoders",
            "d) Vector sum excited LPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The advantage of baseband RELP codec is that it provides good quality speech at low complexity. The speech quality is sometimes limited due to tonal noise introduced by the process of high frequency generation."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "VSELP speech coder is a variant of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CELP",
            "b) MPE_LTP",
            "c) RELP",
            "d) RPE-LTP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The MPE-LTP technique produces excellent speech quality at high complexity. It is not much affected by bit errors present in the channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for VSELP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low speech quality, modest computational complexity, robust to channel errors",
            "b) Highest speech quality, low computational complexity, channel errors",
            "c) Highest speech quality, high computational complexity, robust to channel errors",
            "d) Highest speech quality, modest computational complexity, robust to channel errors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The RPE-LTP codec combines the advantages of the earlier French proposed RELP codec with those of the multipulse excited long term prediction (MPE-LTP) codec proposed by Germany. "
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "What is DAM in speech coding system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagnostic Acceptability Measure",
            "b) Digital Acceptability Measure",
            "c) Diagnostic Accessibility Measure",
            "d) Digital Accessibility Measure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The US digital cellular system, IS-136 uses a vector sum excited linear predictive coder (VSELP). This coder operates at a raw data rate of 7950 bits/s and a total data rate of 13 kbps after channel coding."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "________ exaggerates the bit errors originally received at the base station.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non linear transformation",
            "b) Tandem signalling",
            "c) Large cell size",
            "d) Complex vocoders"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The VSELP speech coder is a variant of the CELP type vocoders. The code books in the VSELP encoder are organised with a predefined structure such that a brute-force search is avoided."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Multiple access schemes are used to allow ________ mobile users to share simultaneously a finite amount of radio spectrum.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Many",
            "b) One",
            "c) Two",
            "d) Ten-Fifteen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Multiple access schemes are used to allow many mobile users to share simultaneously a finite amount of radio spectrum. The sharing of spectrum is required to achieve high capacity by simultaneously allocating the available bandwidth to multiple users."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "The technique that makes possible the task of listening and talking in communication system is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simplexing",
            "b) Duplexing",
            "c) Modulating",
            "d) Multiple access technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In conventional telephone systems, it is possible to talk and listen simultaneously. This effect is called duplexing and is generally required in wireless telephone systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Frequency division duplexing provides ________ distinct bands of frequencies for _________ user.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two, two",
            "b) One, two",
            "c) Two, one",
            "d) Two, many"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Frequency division duplexing (FDD) provides two distinct bands of frequencies for every user. In FDD, any duplex channel actually consists of two simplex channels. "
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Time division duplexing uses ________ to provide both a forward and reverse link.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency",
            "b) Time",
            "c) Time and frequency",
            "d) Cell spacing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The forward band in FDD provides traffic from the base station to the mobile. The reverse band provides traffic from the mobile to the base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "TDD is effective for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed wireless access and users are stationary",
            "b) Dynamic wireless access and users are stationary",
            "c) Fixed wireless access and users are moving",
            "d) Dynamic wireless access and users are moving"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:The frequency separation between each forward and reverse channel is constant throughout the system. It is regardless of the particular channel being used. A device called a duplexer is used inside each subscriber unit and base station to allow simultaneous bidirectional radio transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "In wideband systems, the transmission bandwidth of a single channel _________ coherence bandwidth of the channel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal to",
            "b) Not related to",
            "c) Larger than",
            "d) Smaller than"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Time division duplexing (TDD) uses time instead of frequency to provide both a forward and reverse link. In TDD, multiple users share a single radio channel by taking turns in the time domain."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Frequency division multiple access (FDMA) assigns ______ channels to _______ users.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Individual, individual",
            "b) Many, individual",
            "c) Individual, many",
            "d) Many, many"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency division multiple access (FDMA) assigns individual channels to individual users. Each user is allocated a unique frequency band or channel. These channels are assigned on demand to users who request service."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "The FDMA channel carries ____________ phone circuit at a time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ten",
            "b) Two",
            "c) One",
            "d) Several"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In FDMA systems, no other user can share the same channel during the period of call. In FDD systems, the users are assigned a channel as a pair of frequencies; one is used for the forward channel while the other frequency is used for the reverse channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "The bandwidth of FDMA channel is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wide",
            "b) Narrow",
            "c) Large",
            "d) Zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The FDMA channel carries one phone circuit at a time. Each individual band or channel is wide enough to accommodate the signal spectra of the transmissions to be propagated."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "The symbol time in FDMA systems is _________ thus intersymbol interference is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large, high",
            "b) Small, low",
            "c) Small, high",
            "d) Large, low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If an FDMA channel is not in use, it sits idle and cannot be used by other users to increase or share capacity. It is essentially a wasted resource."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Due to _________ transmission scheme __________ bits are needed for overhead in FDMA systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous, few",
            "b) Discontinuous, few",
            "c) Continuous, many",
            "d) Discontinuous, many"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bandwidth of FDMA channels is relatively narrow as each channel supports only one circuit per carrier. That is, FDMA is usually implemented in narrow band systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for FDMA systems as compared to TDMA systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low complexity",
            "b) Lower cell site system cost",
            "c) Tight RF filtering",
            "d) Narrow bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The symbol time of a narrowband signal is large as compared to the average delay spread. This implies that the amount of intersymbol interference is low and, thus, little or no equalization is required in FDMA narrowband systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "__________ is undesired RF radiation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermodulation frequency",
            "b) Intermediate frequency",
            "c) Instantaneous frequency",
            "d) Instrumental frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since FDMA is a continuous transmission scheme, fewer bits are needed for overhead purposes (such as synchronization and framing bits) as compared to TDMA."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "__________ is based on FDMA/FDD.",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) W-CDMA",
            "c) Cordless telephone",
            "d) AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FDMA systems have higher cell site system costs as compared to TDMA systems. It is due to single channel per carrier design, and the need to use costly bandpass filters to eliminate spurious radiation at the base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "In US AMPS, 416 channels are allocated to various operators with 10 kHz guard band and channel between them is 30 kHz. What is the spectrum allocation given to each operator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12.5 kHz",
            "b) 30 kHz",
            "c) 12.5 MHz",
            "d) 30 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Intermodulation (IM) frequency is undesired RF radiation which can interfere with other channels in the FDMA systems. The nonlinearities cause signal spreading in the frequency domain and generate IM frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Preamble contains __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Address",
            "b) Data",
            "c) Guard bits",
            "d) Trail bits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TDMA systems transmit data in a buffer and burst method. Thus, the transmission for any user is not continuous. "
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "__________ are utilized to allow synchronization of the receivers between different slots and frames.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preamble",
            "b) Data",
            "c) Guard bits",
            "d) Trail bits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TDMA frame is made up of a preamble, an information message and the trail bits. In a TDMA frame, the preamble contains the address and synchronization information that both the base station and the subscribers use to identify each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for TDMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single carrier frequency for single user",
            "b) Discontinuous data transmission",
            "c) No requirement of duplexers",
            "d) High transmission rates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Guard times are utilized to allow synchronization of the receivers between different slots and frames. TDMA/FDD systems intentionally induce several time slots of delay between the forward and reverse time slots for a particular user."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Because of _______ transmissions in TDMA, the handoff process in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous, complex",
            "b) Continuous, simple",
            "c) Discontinuous, complex",
            "d) Discontinuous, simple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TDMA share a single carrier frequency with several users, where each user makes use of non-overlapping time slots. The number of time slots per frame depends on several factors, such as modulation technique, available bandwidth etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "__________ synchronization overhead is required in TDMA due to _______ transmission.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High, burst",
            "b) High, continuous",
            "c) Low, burst",
            "d) No, burst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Because of discontinuous transmissions in TDMA, the handoff process is much simpler for a subscriber unit, since it is able to listen for other base stations during idle time slots."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "___________ of TDMA system is a measure of the percentage of transmitted data that contains information as opposed to providing overhead for the access scheme.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency",
            "b) Figure of merit",
            "c) Signal to noise ratio",
            "d) Mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High synchronization overhead is required in TDMA systems because of burst transmissions. TDMA transmissions are slotted, and this requires the receivers to be synchronized for each data burst."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "A TDMA system uses 25 MHz for the forward link, which is broken into radio channels of 200 kHz. If 8 speech channels are supported on a single radio channel, how many simultaneous users can be accommodated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 200",
            "c) 1600",
            "d) 1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TDMA has an advantage that it can allocate different numbers of time slots per frame to different users. Thus, bandwidth can be supplied on demand to different users by concatenating or reassigning time slots based on priority."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "What is the time duration of a bit if data is transmitted at 270.833 kbps in the channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 270.833 s",
            "b) 3 μs",
            "c) 3.692 μs",
            "d) 3.692 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Efficiency of TDMA system is a measure of the percentage of transmitted data that contains information as opposed to providing overhead for the access scheme. The frame efficiency is the percentage of bits per frame which contain transmitted data."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "PN sequence converts _______ signal to ______ signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrowband, wideband",
            "b) Wideband, narrowband",
            "c) Unmodulated, modulated",
            "d) Low frequency, high frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spread spectrum multiple access (SSMA) uses signals which have a transmission bandwidth that is several orders of magnitude greater than the minimum required RF bandwidth."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "___________ is a digital multiple access system in which carrier frequencies are varied in pseudorandom order.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CDMA",
            "b) FCDMA",
            "c) FHMA",
            "d) SDMA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A pseudo-noise (PN) sequence converts a narrowband signal to a wideband noise like signal before transmission. SSMA provides immunity to multipath interference and robust multiple access capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "If the rate of change of the carrier frequency is greater than the symbol rate, then the system is referred as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast frequency hopping system",
            "b) Slow frequency hopping system",
            "c) Time division frequency hopping system",
            "d) Code division multiple access system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SSMA is not very bandwidth efficient when used by a single user. However, since many users can share the same spread spectrum bandwidth without interfering with one another, spread spectrum systems become bandwidth efficient in a multiple user environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "All users in CDMA system uses __________ carrier frequency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Different",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Ten",
            "d) Same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Frequency hopped multiple access (FHMA) is a digital multiple access system in which the carrier frequencies of the individual users are varied in a pseudorandom fashion within a wideband channel. "
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "___________ problem occurs when many mobile users share the same channel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Near-far",
            "b) Activation",
            "c) Line of sight",
            "d) Windowing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the rate of change of the carrier frequency is greater than the symbol rate, then the system is referred as a fast frequency hopping system. If the channel changes at a rate less than or equal to the symbol rate, it is called slow frequency hopping."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "In CDMA, symbol duration is ___________ than channel delay spread.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Greater",
            "c) Slightly greater",
            "d) Much less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A frequency hopped system provides a level of security, especially when a large number of channels are used. Since, an unintended receiver that does not know the pseudorandom sequence of frequency slots must retune rapidly to search for the signal it wishes to intercept."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "____________ is used to improve reception by collecting time delayed versions of the required signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAKE receiver",
            "b) Equalizer",
            "c) Frequency modulator",
            "d) High pass filter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All users in CDMA system use the same carrier frequency and may transmit simultaneously. Each user has its own pseudorandom codeword which is approximately orthogonal to all other codewords."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "____________ arises from the fact that the spreading sequences of different users are not orthogonal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Near-far problem",
            "b) Line of sight",
            "c) Windowing",
            "d) Self jamming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The near far problem occurs when many mobile users share the same channel. In general, the strongest received mobile signal will capture the demodulator at a base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "In ___________ technique, many subscribers attempt to access a single channel in an uncoordinated manner.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Packet radio",
            "b) Multiple access",
            "c) Modulation",
            "d) Spread spectrum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In packet radio (PR) access techniques, many subscribers attempt to access a single channel in an uncoordinated (or minimally coordinated) manner. Transmission is done by using bursts of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Packet radio uses _________ and __________ signals for perfect feedback.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward, reverse",
            "b) ACK, NACK",
            "c) Active, passive",
            "d) Linear, non linear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Packet radio uses ACK and NACK signals for perfect feedback. The ACK signal indicates an acknowledgment of a received burst and NACK indicates that the previous burst was not received correctly by base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "___________ is defined as average number of messages successfully transmitted per unit time in packet radio multiple access technique.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average delay",
            "b) Figure of merit",
            "c) Throughput",
            "d) Efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Packet radio multiple access is very easy to implement, but has low spectral efficiency and may induce delays. The subscriber uses a contention technique to transmit on a common channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "What is the time period during which the packets are susceptible to collisions with transmissions from other users?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay time",
            "b) Latency period",
            "c) Average delay time",
            "d) Vulnerable period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The performance of contention technique can be evaluated by the throughput (T), which is defined as the average number of messages successfully transmitted per unit time, and the average delay experienced by a typical message burst."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "For a PR multiple access technique, packet transmissions occur with __________ distribution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poisson",
            "b) Gaussian",
            "c) Pearson",
            "d) Rayleigh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vulnerable period is the time period during which the packets are susceptible to collisions with transmissions from other users. It is used in order to determine the throughput."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "If λ is mean arrival rate and τ is the packet duration, then traffic occupancy of a packet radio network is equal to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) λτ",
            "b) λ/τ",
            "c) λ-τ",
            "d) λτ2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a PR multiple access technique, packet transmissions occur with Poisson distribution. To study packet radio protocols, it is assumed that all packets sent by all users have a constant packet length and fixed channel rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Pure ALOHA is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulation technique",
            "b) Multiple access technique",
            "c) Random access technique",
            "d) Spread spectrum technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If λ is mean arrival rate and τ is the packet duration, then traffic occupancy or throughput of a packet radio network is equal to λτ. The unit of R is in Erlangs."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "For pure ALOHA protocol, the vulnerable period is ___________ the packet duration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double",
            "b) Equal",
            "c) Ten times",
            "d) Not equal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pure ALOHA protocol is a random access protocol used for data transfer. A user accesses a channel as soon as a message is ready to be transmitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "The vulnerable period of slotted ALOHA is _________ packet duration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two",
            "b) Ten",
            "c) One",
            "d) Three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the pure ALOHA protocol, the vulnerable period is double the packet duration. After a transmission, the user waits for an acknowledgement on either the same channel or a separate feedback channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "CSMA stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carrier sense multiple access",
            "b) Code sense multiple access",
            "c) Carrier sense modulation access",
            "d) Carry sense multiple access"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The vulnerable period of slotted ALOHA is one packet duration. Since, partial collisions are prevented through synchronization."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "__________ is the time required for a terminal to sense whether or not the channel is idle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propagation delay",
            "b) Average delay",
            "c) Detection delay",
            "d) Time delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In slotted ALOHA, time is divided into equal time slots of length greater than the packet duration. The subscribers each have synchronized clocks and transmit a message only at the beginning of a new time slot."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Which of the following is based on time division multiplexing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slotted ALOHA",
            "b) Pure ALOHA",
            "c) CSMA",
            "d) Reservation ALOHA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CSMA stands for carrier sense multiple access. CSMA protocol is based on the fact that each terminal on the network is able to monitor the status of the channel before transmitting information."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Discrete packet time technique, PRMA stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Packet reservation multiple access",
            "b) Photo reflector multiple access",
            "c) Proton reflector modulating access",
            "d) Packet reflection multiple access"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In CSMA protocols, detection delay and propagation delay are two important parameters. Detection delay is a function of the receiver hardware and is the time required for a terminal to sense whether or not the channel is idle."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "____________ is the maximum number of channels that can be provided in a fixed frequency band.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Channel capacity",
            "b) Radio capacity",
            "c) Spectral capacity",
            "d) Carrier capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Channel capacity for a radio system can be defined as the maximum number of channels or users that can be provided in a fixed frequency band. It is useful in computer science, in electrical engineering, and in other disciplines evaluating the capacity of a channel or conduit."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Which of the following measures spectrum efficiency of a wireless system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Channel capacity",
            "b) Radio capacity",
            "c) Spectral capacity",
            "d) Carrier capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Radio capacity is a parameter which measures spectrum efficiency of a wireless system. This parameter is determined by the required carrier to interference ratio and the channel bandwidth."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "If D is the distance between co-channel cells and R be the cell radius, co-channel reuse ratio is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) D*R",
            "b) D2/R",
            "c) D/R",
            "d) D/R2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Let, D is the distance between co-channel cells and R be the cell radius. Then the minimum ratio of D/R that is required to provide a tolerable level of co-channel interference is called the co-channel reuse ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "__________ is the interference at a base station receiver that comes from the subscriber units in the surrounding cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward channel interference",
            "b) Carrier interference",
            "c) Receiver interference",
            "d) Reverse channel interference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a cellular system, the interference at a base station receiver will come from the subscriber units in the surrounding cells. This is called reverse channel interference. "
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "In practice, TDMA systems improve capacity by ____________ compared to analog cellular systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three to six times",
            "b) Equal capacity",
            "c) Two time",
            "d) Ten to twenty times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In practice, TDMA systems improve capacity by a factor of three to six times as compared to analog cellular radio systems. Powerful error control and speech coding enable better link performance in high interference environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "__________ allows subscribers to monitor neighbouring base stations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) TDMA",
            "b) MAHO",
            "c) FDMA",
            "d) ACA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mobile assisted handoff (MAHO) allows subscribers to monitor the neighbouring base stations, and the best base station choice may be made by each subscriber. MAHO allows deployment of densely packed microcells, thus giving substantial capacity gains in a system."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "Time division multiple access introduces ACA, which stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acute carrier allocation",
            "b) Adaptive carrier allocation",
            "c) Adaptive channel allocation",
            "d) Acute channel allocation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: TDMA makes it possible to introduce adaptive channel allocation (ACA). ACA eliminates system planning since it is not required to plan frequencies for cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "Which of the following standard had not adopted digital TDMA for high capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) USDC",
            "b) GSM",
            "c) PDC",
            "d) IS-95"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Various proposed standards such as the GSM, US digital cellular (USDC), and Pacific Digital Cellular (PDC) have adopted digital TDMA for high capacity. IS-95 does not use TDMA."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "In a CDMA system, link performance for each user __________ as the number of users _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase, decrease",
            "b) Increase, increase",
            "c) Decrease, increase",
            "d) Decrease, decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacity of CDMA systems is interference limited. It is bandwidth limited in FDMA and TDMA. Therefore, any reduction in the interference will cause a linear increase in the capacity of CDMA."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Capacity of CDMA can be increased by operating in DTX, which stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discrete transmission mode",
            "b) Discrete transmission modulation",
            "c) Discontinuous transmission mode",
            "d) Digital transmission mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a CDMA system, the link performance for each user increases as the number of users decreases. A straightforward way to reduce interference is to use multisectorized antennas, which results in spatial isolation of users."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Frequency reuse factor for CDMA system is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) Ten"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Capacity of CDMA can be increased by operating in DTX, which stands for Discontinuous transmission mode. It takes advantage of the intermittent nature of speech. In DTX, the transmiiter is turned off during the periods of silence in speech."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "In a wireless communication, base station is connected to central hub called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) PSTN",
            "b) MSC",
            "c) CO",
            "d) PBX"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To provide wireless communication within a particular geographic region, an integrated network of base stations must be deployed to provide sufficient radio coverage to all mobile users. The base station, in turn must be connected to a central hub called MSC (mobile switching center)."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "PSTN stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Public switched telephone network",
            "b) Personal switched telephone network",
            "c) Personal switched telephone node",
            "d) Public switched telephone node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PSTN stands for public switched telephone network. The PSTN forms the global telecommunication grid which connects conventional telephone centers with MSCs throughout the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Communication protocol, CAI stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Common air interchange",
            "b) Control air interchange",
            "c) Common air interface",
            "d) Control air interchange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The MSC provide connectivity between the public switched telephone network (PSTN) and the numerous base stations. It ultimately provides connectivity between all of the wireless subscribers in the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "PSTN is ___________ and wireless networks are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highly dynamic, virtually static",
            "b) Static, virtually static",
            "c) Highly dynamic, virtually dynamic",
            "d) Virtually static, highly dynamic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To connect mobile subscribers to the base stations, radio links are established using a carefully defined communication protocol called common air interface (CAI) which in essence is a precisely defined handshake communication protocol."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "In public switched telephone network, LATA stands for ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local access and transport area",
            "b) Land area and transport area",
            "c) Local access and telephone access",
            "d) Local area and telephone access"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At the base station, the air interface portion (i.e., signalling and synchronization data) of the mobile transmission is discarded, and the remaining voice traffic is paased along to the MSC on fixed networks."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "LATAs are connected by a company called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Land exchange carrier",
            "b) Local exchange carrier",
            "c) Local control exchange",
            "d) Land area exchange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The network configurations in the PSTN are virtually static, since the network connections may only be changed when a subscriber changes residence. Wireless networks are highly dynamic with the network configuration being rearranged everytime a new subscriber moves into the coverage region of a different base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "A long distance telephone company that collects toll is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LATA",
            "b) LEC",
            "c) PSTN",
            "d) IXC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In public switched telephone network, LATA stands for Local access and transport area. LATA is a city or a geographic grouping of towns in PSTN."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "The technique for separate but parallel signalling channel is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Common channel signalling",
            "b) Forward channel signalling",
            "c) Reverse channel signalling",
            "d) Separate channel signalling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surrounding LATAs are connected by a company called a local exchange carrier (LEC). A LEC is a company that provides telephone services and may be a local telephone company."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "In North America, the cellular telephone signalling network uses _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) SS7",
            "b) IXC",
            "c) IS-41",
            "d) PSTN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A long distance telephone company collects toll fees to provide connections between different LATAs over its long distance network. These companies are referred to as interexchange carriers (IXCs)."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "First generation cellular and cordless telephone networks are based on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analog technology",
            "b) Digital technology",
            "c) Active technology",
            "d) Passive technology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: First generation cellular and cordless telephone networks are based on analog technology. All first generation cellular systems use FM modulation, and cordless telephones use a single base station to communicate with a single portable terminal."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for first generation wireless systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficient",
            "b) Digital technology",
            "c) High data rate",
            "d) Low rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: First generation wireless systems provide analog speech and inefficient, low rate, data transmission between the base station and mobile user."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Which of the following network protocol is used by US cellular carriers to automatically accommodate subscribers who roam into their coverage regions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-36",
            "b) IS-121",
            "c) IS-41",
            "d) IS-14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: US cellular carriers implemented the network protocol standard IS-41 to allow different cellular systems to automatically accommodate subscribers who roam into their coverage region."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "The visited system creates a __________ record for each roamer and notifies home system to update __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HLR, VLR",
            "b) VLR, MIN",
            "c) MIN, ESN",
            "d) VLR, HLR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS-41 relies on a feature of AMPS called autonomous registration. Autonomous registration is a process by which a mobile notifies a serving MSC of its presence and location."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of second generation wireless networks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) CT2",
            "c) AMPS",
            "d) PACS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The MSC is able to distinguish home users from roaming users based on the MIN of each active user, and maintains a real time user list in the home location register (HLR) and visitor location register (VLR)."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "In second generation wireless networks, the handoff process is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAHO",
            "b) Soft handoff",
            "c) Hard handoff",
            "d) Inter system handoff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The visited system creates a VLR record for each new roamer and notifies the home system via IS-41 so it can update its own HLR. IS-41 allows the MSCs of neighboring systems to automatically handle the registration and location validation of roamers so that users no longer need to manually register as they travel."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "__________ is an example of second generation cordless telephone standard which allows each cordless phone to communicate with any number of base stations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PACS",
            "b) CT2",
            "c) GSM",
            "d) DECT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: AMPS is an example of first generation wireless networks. Second generation wireless systems employ digital modulation and advanced call processing capabilities. Example includes GSM, CT2, PACS and DECT."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "In PACS/ WACS, the BSC is called a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radio port control unit",
            "b) HLR",
            "c) VLR",
            "d) MIN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In second generation wireless networks, the handoff process is mobile controlled and is known as mobile assisted handoff (MAHO). The mobile units in these networks perform several other functions not performed by first generation subscriber units."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "FPLMTS is recently known by the name _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) ISDN",
            "c) IMTS-2000",
            "d) DECT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DECT is an example of second generation cordless telephone standard which allows each cordless phone to communicate with any number of base stations. In DECT, the base stations have greater control in terms of switching, signalling, and controlling handoffs."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Connection oriented services are also called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Datagram services",
            "b) Virtual circuit routing",
            "c) Connectionless services",
            "d) Routing service"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The type of traffic carried by a network determines the routing services. It also determines protocols, and call handling techniques which must be employed."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Connectionless services are also called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Datagram services",
            "b) Virtual circuit routing",
            "c) Connection oriented services",
            "d) Routing service"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Connection oriented services are also called virtual circuit routing. In connection oriented routing, the communications path between the message source and destination is fixed for the entire duration of the message."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Wireless data networks are not well supported by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Datagram services",
            "b) Circuit switching",
            "c) Connectionless services",
            "d) Routing service"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Connectionless services are also called datagram services. In a connectionless service, a call set up procedure is not required at the beginning of a call, and each message burst is treated independently by the network."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Header specifies the ___________ of a new packet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ending",
            "b) Middle part",
            "c) Beginning",
            "d) Data information"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: First generation cellular systems provide connection oriented services for each voice user. Voice channels are dedicated for users at the serving base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "The control field contains the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CRC",
            "b) User data",
            "c) Address",
            "d) ARQ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wireless data networks are not supported by circuit switching. It is due to their short, bursty transmissions which are often followed by periods of inactivity. Circuit switching is best suited for dedicated voice only traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "__________ was developed by CCITT to provide standard connectionless network access protocols for three layers of OSI model.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Packet switching",
            "b) Datagram routing",
            "c) X.25",
            "d) CDPD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Packet switching breaks each message into smaller units for transmission and recovery. When a message is broken into packets, a certain amount of control information is added to each packet to provide source and destination identification, as well as error recovery provisions."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "US cellular standard CDPD stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellular Digital Packet Data",
            "b) Cellular Digital Packet Data",
            "c) Cellular Digital Pocket Data",
            "d) Cellular Discrete Pocket Data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: US cellular standard CDPD stands for Cellular Digital Packet Data. In 1993, US cellular industry developed CDPD to coexist with the conventional voice only cellular system."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for CDPD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expensive to install",
            "b) Uses different infrastructure",
            "c) Complex",
            "d) Inexpensive to install"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CDPD is a data service for first and second generation US cellular systems and uses a full 30 kHz AMPS channel on a shared basis. CDPD provides mobile packet data connectivity to existing data networks."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "CDPD channel is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simplex",
            "b) Complex",
            "c) Duplex",
            "d) Expensive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CDPD directly overlays with existing cellular infrastructure and uses existing base station equipment, making it simple and inexpensive to install. CDPD does not use the MSC, but rather has its own traffic routing capabilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "CDPD transmissions are carried out using ________ blocks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed length",
            "b) Variable length",
            "c) Long",
            "d) Short"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Each CDPD channel is duplex in nature. The forward channel serves as a beacon and transmits data from the PSTN side of the network, while the reverse channel links all mobile users to the CDPD network and serves as the access channel for each subscriber."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "MDLP is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Layer protocol used in CDPD",
            "b) Layer protocol used in GSM",
            "c) Layer protocol used in ARDIS",
            "d) Layer protocol used in CDMA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CDPD transmissions are carried out using fixed length blocks. User data is protected using a Reed-Solomon (63, 47) block code with 6 bit symbols."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "The layer protocol, RRMP stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radio Resource Management Protocol",
            "b) Radio Resource Mobile Protocol",
            "c) Radio Rate Management Protocol",
            "d) Radio Rate Mobile Protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MDLP (Mobile data link protocol) is a lower layer protocol of CDPD. It is used to convey information between data link layer entities (layer 2 devices) across the CDPD air interface."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "RMD is a _______ and ________ data service.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Private, two way",
            "b) Public, one way",
            "c) Public, two way",
            "d) Private, one way"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The radio resource management protocol (RRMP) is a higher, layer 3 protocol used to manage the radio channel resources of the CDPD system and enables an M-ES to find and utilize a duplex radio channel without interfering with standard voice services."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "The MSC provides subscriber access to the PSTN via the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signalling transfer points",
            "b) Service management system",
            "c) Database service management system",
            "d) Switching end points"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ARDIS (Advanced Radio Data Information Systems) is a private network service provided by Motorola and IBM. It is based on MDC 4800 and RD-LAP protocols developed at Motorola."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "________ controls the switching of messages between nodes in the CCS network.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signalling transfer points",
            "b) Service management system",
            "c) Database service management system",
            "d) Switching end points"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RAM Mobile Data (RMD) is a public, two way data service based upon the Mobitex protocol developed by Ericsson. RAM provides street level coverage for short and long messages for users moving in an urban environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "ISDN stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrated Services Digital Network",
            "b) Integrated Services Discrete Network",
            "c) Integrated Services Digital Node",
            "d) Integrated Services Discrete Node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ISDN stands for integrated services digital network. It defines the dedicated signalling network that has been created to complement the PSTN for more flexible and efficient network access and signalling."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "ISDN is based on the concept of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SS7",
            "b) CCS",
            "c) ARDIS",
            "d) CDPD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ISDN is a complete network framework designed around the concept of common channel signalling. While telephone users throughout the world rely on the PSTN to carry conventional voice traffic, new end-user data and signalling services can be provided with a parallel, dedicated signalling network."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Signalling component that supports traffic between the end-user and network is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Network signalling",
            "b) Digital subscriber signalling",
            "c) Access signalling",
            "d) Subscriber system signalling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Access signalling supports traffic between the end user and the network. It defines how end users obtain access to the PSTN and the ISDN for communication or services."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Information bearing channels in ISDN are called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) D channels",
            "b) Data channels",
            "c) B channels",
            "d) Voice channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The second signalling component of ISDN, network signalling is governed by the SS7 suite of protocols. For wireless communication systems, the SS7 protocols within ISDN are critical to providing backbone network connectivity between MSCs throughout the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Which of the following is based on ATM technology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SS7",
            "b) CCS",
            "c) ARDIS",
            "d) B-ISDN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ISDN interface is divided into three different types of channels. Information bearing channels called bearer channels (B channels) are used exclusively for end user traffic (voice, data and video)."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for ATM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circuit switched",
            "b) Multiple access technique",
            "c) Multiplexing technique",
            "d) Handle only voice users"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ISDN provides integrated end-user access to both circuit switched and packet switched networks with digital end-to-end connectivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "The data unit of ATM is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell",
            "b) Atom",
            "c) Molecule",
            "d) Packet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ISDN end users may select between two different interfaces. The BRI (basic rate interface) is intended to serve small capacity terminals while the PRI (primary rate interface) is intended for large capacity terminals."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "ATM cells have fixed length of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48 bytes",
            "b) 47 bytes",
            "c) 5 bytes",
            "d) 53 bytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Emerging networking technique, broadband ISDN (B-ISDN) is based on asynchronous transfer mode (ATM) technology. It allows packet switching rates up to 2.4 Gbps and total switching capacities as high as 100 Gbps."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a service offered by SS7?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Touchstar",
            "b) 800 services",
            "c) Alternate billing services",
            "d) 400 services"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are three main types of services offered by the SS7 network. They are the Touchstar, 800 services, and alternate billing services."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Which of the following service is called CLASS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Touchstar",
            "b) 800 services",
            "c) Alternate billing services",
            "d) 400 services"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Touchstar is also known as CLASS. It is a group of switch controlled services that provide its users with certain call management capabilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Which of the following service of SS& provides call return, call forwarding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Touchstar",
            "b) 800 services",
            "c) Alternate billing services",
            "d) 400 services"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Touchstar is one of the three main type of services offered by SS7. It provides services such as call return, call forwarding, repeat dialling, call block, call tracing and caller ID."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "SS7 was first developed by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ITU",
            "b) Ericsson",
            "c) CCITT",
            "d) Motorola"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alternate billing service and line information database use the CCS network to enable the calling party to bill a call to a personal number (third party number, calling card, or collect etc.) from any number."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Which of the layer of OSI is associated with NSP of SS7?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All layers",
            "b) Upper three",
            "c) Lowest three",
            "d) Middle two"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SS7 is an outgrowth of the out of band signalling first developed by the CCITT under common channel signalling standard, CCS no. 6."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "The function of _______ is to transfer and deliver signalling network.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MTP",
            "b) CCS",
            "c) ARDIS",
            "d) CDPD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lowest three layers of the OSI model are handled in SS7 by the network service part (NSP) of the protocol. NSP is made up of three message transfer parts (MTPs) and the signalling connection control part (SCCP) of the SS7 protocol."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Signalling data functions are provided by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MTP level 1",
            "b) MTP level 2",
            "c) MTP level 3",
            "d) TCAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The function of the MTP is to ensure that signalling traffic can be transferred and delivered reliably between the end users and the network. MTP is provided at three levels."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Signalling data functions are provided by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MTP level 1",
            "b) MTP level 2",
            "c) MTP level 3",
            "d) TCAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Signalling data link functions (MTP level 1) provide an interface to the actual physical channel over which communication takes place. Physical channels may include copper wire, twisted pair, fibre, mobile radio and are transparent to the higher layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "_________ provide procedures that transfer messages between signalling nodes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MTP level 1",
            "b) MTP level 2",
            "c) MTP level 3",
            "d) TCAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Signalling data link functions are provided by MTP level 2. They correspond to the second layer in the OSI reference model and provide a reliable link for the transfer of traffic between two directly connected signalling points."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not include in SS7 user part?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MTP",
            "b) ISUP",
            "c) TCAP",
            "d) OMAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Signalling network functions (MTP level 3) provide procedures that ransfer messages between signalling nodes. As in ISDN, there are two types of MTP level 3 functions: signalling message handling and signalling network management."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "The TCAP part in SS7 refers to ________ layer of OSI.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical",
            "b) Network",
            "c) Data Link",
            "d) Application"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The SS7 user part includes the ISDN user part (ISUP), the transaction capabilities application part (TCAP) and operations maintenance and administration part (OMAP). The telephone user part (TUP) and the data user part (DUP) are included in the ISUP."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Concept of PCS/PCN is based on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Advanced intelligent network",
            "b) Artificial intelligent network",
            "c) CDPD",
            "d) SS7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The objective of personal communication systems (PCS) or personal communication networks (PCNs) is to provide ubiquitous wireless communications coverage, enabling users to access telephone network and Internet."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "______ is used for transmission of packets in the cellular switched architecture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Packet switching techniques",
            "b) Circuit switching techniques",
            "c) Packet and circuit switched technique",
            "d) Datagram technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The concept of PCS/PCN is based on an advanced intelligent network (AIN). The mobile and fixed networks will be integrated to provide universal access to the network and its databases."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the function to accept information from PSTN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TIU",
            "b) WIU",
            "c) BIU",
            "d) CIU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: AIN (advanced intelligent network) allow its users to have a single telephone number to be used for both wireless and wireline services. "
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "PTI is the address of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) TIU",
            "b) WIU",
            "c) BIU",
            "d) CIU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Packet switching technology will have more advantages for PCS/PCN than circuit switching. PCS is required to serve a wide range of services including voice, data, e-mail and digital video."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "_______ is the information contained in the packet header of TIU.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PTI",
            "b) VCI",
            "c) PRMA",
            "d) CDPD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Packet switching techniques are used for transmission of packets in the cellular switched architecture. Packet switching is attractive for wireless networks because the addresses and other information in packet headers make it possible for dispersed network elements to respond to a mobile user without intervention central controllers."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "Transmission protocol, PRMA stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pocket reservation multiple access",
            "b) Packet register multiple access",
            "c) Pocket register multiple access",
            "d) Packet reservation multiple access"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The function of TIU (Trunk interface unit) is to accept information from the PSTN. TIU acts as the physical layer and transforms the standard format of the PSTN into the wireless access physical layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "UMTS stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Universal mobile telecommunication system",
            "b) Universal mobile telephone system",
            "c) United multiplex telecommunication system",
            "d) Universal mobile telecommunication system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PTI (Permanent terminal identifier) is the address of TIU. It is the address from where he call is originated."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "US cellular telephone system, AMPS stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analog Mobile Phone System",
            "b) Analog Modulation Packet System",
            "c) Analog Machine Precision System",
            "d) Analog Mobile Precision System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: AMPS stands for Analog Mobile Phone System. It was first deployed in late 1983 in urban and suburban areas of Chicago by Ameritech. "
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Who developed the first US cellular telephone system called AMPS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motorola",
            "b) Ericsson",
            "c) AT & T Bell Laboratories",
            "d) ETSI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the late 1970s, AT & T Bell Laboratories developed the first US cellular telephone system called the Advanced Mobile Phone System (AMPS). In 1983, a total of 40 MHz of spectrum in the 800 MHz band was located by the Federal Communication Commission for AMPS. "
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "The AMPS system uses a ___________ cell reuse pattern.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Five",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Seven"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The AMPS system uses a seven cell reuse pattern. It also provides sectoring and cell splitting to increase capacity when needed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Which of the following is virtually identical to AMPS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ETACS",
            "b) GSM",
            "c) CDMA",
            "d) IS-54"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ETACS is virtually identical to AMPS. It was developed in middle 1980s and stands for European Total Access Communication System.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "AMPS and ETACS use ___________ and _____ for radio transmission.",
        "Options": [
            "a) FM, TDD",
            "b) FM, FDD",
            "c) AM, TDD",
            "d) FM, FDD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Like all other first generation, analog, cellular systems, AMPS and ETACS use frequency modulation (FM) and frequency division duplex (FDD) for radio transmission.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "ETACS use ___________ instead of SID (system identification number).",
        "Options": [
            "a) Area identification number",
            "b) Analog identification number",
            "c) Digital identification number",
            "d) Dual identification number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the US AMPS system, there are twenty one control channels for each of the two service providers in each market. However, ETACS supports forty two control channels for a single provider. "
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "_________ allows base and mobile to distinguish each other from co-channel users located in different cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SAT",
            "b) VMAC",
            "c) MAC",
            "d) FVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In each cellular market, the non wireline service provider (the ‘A’ provider) is assigned an odd SID (system identification number). The wireline provider (the ‘B’ provider) is assigned an even SID. "
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "To increase the capacity of AMPS, Motorola developed ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P-AMPS",
            "b) N-AMPS",
            "c) H-APMS",
            "d) R-AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For ETACS, area identification numbers (AIDs) are used instead of SIDs. ETACS subscriber units are able to access any control or voice channel in the standard. "
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "The dual mode USDC/AMPS system was standardized as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-54",
            "b) IS-136",
            "c) PSTN",
            "d) GSM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dual mode USDC/AMPS system was standardized as Interim Standard 54 (IS 54). It was standardized by Electron Industries Association and Telecommunication Industry Association (EIA/TIA) in 1990. It was later upgraded to IS-136."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "USDC is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SADC",
            "b) NADC",
            "c) PADC",
            "d) N-AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: USDC is also known as North American Digital Cellular (NADC). It has been installed in North America in the countries like Canada and Mexico."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Because of the compatibility with AMPS, USDC is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SADC",
            "b) PADC",
            "c) D-AMPS",
            "d) K-AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The USDC system was designed to share the same frequencies, frequency reuse plan, and base stations as AMPS, so that base stations and subscriber units could be equipped with both AMPS and USDC channels within the same piece of equipment."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "USDC has ___________ as many control channels as AMPS.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same",
            "b) Three times",
            "c) Twice",
            "d) Four times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: USDC (United States Digital Cellular System) maintains compatibility with AMPS in a number of ways. Therefore, USDC is also known as D-AMPS (digital AMPS)."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Which of the following data channels of USDC carries the user information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DTC",
            "b) CVDCC",
            "c) SACCH",
            "d) FACCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To maintain compatibility with AMPS phones, USDC forward and reverse control channels use exactly the same signalling techniques as AMPS. USDC voice channels use 4-ary π/4 DQPSK modulation with a channel rate of 48.6 kbps."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Which of the following channel is similar in functionality to the SAT used in AMPS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DTC",
            "b) CDVCC",
            "c) SACCH",
            "d) FACCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: USDC has twice as many control channels as AMPS. In addition to the forty two primary AMPS control channels, USDC specifies forty two additional control channels called the secondary control channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Which of the following channel in USDC provides a signalling channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DTC",
            "b) CVDCC",
            "c) SACCH",
            "d) FACCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DTC (data traffic channel) is the most important data channel as far as the end user is concerned. It carries user information (i.e. speech or user data)."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Which of the following channel in USDC is used to send important control or specialized traffic data between the base station and mobile units?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DTC",
            "b) CVDCC",
            "c) SACCH",
            "d) FACCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CDVCC (Code Digital Verification Color Code) is a 12 bit message sent in every time slot and is similar in functionality to the SAT used in AMPS. The CDVCC is an 8 bit number ranging between 1 and 255, which is protected with four additional channel coding bits from a shortened Hamming code."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Which of the following speech coder is used in USDC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vector Sum Excited Linear Predictive coder",
            "b) Formant Vocoder",
            "c) Multipulse Excited Linear Predictive coder",
            "d) Residual Excited Linear Predictive coder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The SACCH (slow associated control channel) is sent in every time slot and provides a signalling channel in parallel with the digital speech. The SACCH carries various control and supervisory messages between the subscriber unit and the base station."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the world’s first cellular system to specify digital modulation and network level architecture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GSM",
            "b) AMPS",
            "c) CDMA",
            "d) IS-54"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GSM was the world’s first cellular system to specify digital modulation and level architectures and services. It is the world’s most popular 2G technology. It was developed to solve the fragmentation problems of the first cellular systems in Europe."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Previously in 1980s, GSM stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Global system for mobile",
            "b) Groupe special mobile",
            "c) Global special mobile",
            "d) Groupe system mobile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the mid-1980s GSM was called by the name Groupe special mobile. In 1992, GSM changed its name to Global System for Mobile Communication for marketing reasons."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Who sets the standards of GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ITU",
            "b) AT & T",
            "c) ETSI",
            "d) USDC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The setting of standards for GSM is under the aegis of the European Technical Standards Institute (ETSI). GSM task was to specify a common mobile communication system for Europe in the 900 MHZ band."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not come under the teleservices of GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard mobile telephony",
            "b) Mobile originated traffic",
            "c) Base originated traffic",
            "d) Packet switched traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GSM services follow ISDN guidelines and are classified as either teleservices or data services. Teleservices include standard mobile telephony and mobile originated or base originated traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Which of the following comes under supplementary ISDN services?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emergency calling",
            "b) Packet switched protocols",
            "c) Call diversion",
            "d) Standard mobile telephony"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Supplementary ISDN services are digital in nature. They include call diversion, closed user groups, and caller identification, and are not available in analog mobile networks. Supplementary services also include short messaging service (SMS)."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "Which of the following memory device stores information such as subscriber’s identification number in GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Register",
            "b) Flip flop",
            "c) SIM",
            "d) SMS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SIM (subscriber identity module) is a memory device that stores information such as the subscriber’s identification number, the networks and countries where the subscriber is entitled to service, privacy keys, and other user specific information."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Which of the following feature makes impossible to eavesdrop on GSM radio transmission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SIM",
            "b) On the air privacy",
            "c) SMS",
            "d) Packet switched traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The on the air privacy feature of GSM makes impossible to eavesdrop on a GSM radio transmission. The privacy is made possible by encrypting the digital bit stream sent by a GSM transmitter, according to a specific secret cryptographic key that is known only to the cellular carrier."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not come under subsystem of GSM architecture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BSS",
            "b) NSS",
            "c) OSS",
            "d) Channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The GSM architecture consists of three major interconnected subsystems that interact between themselves and with the users through certain network interfaces. The subsystems are BSS (Base Station Subsystem), NSS (Network and Switching Subsystem) and OSS (Operation Support Subsystem)."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of the following subsystem provides radio transmission between mobile station and MSC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BSS",
            "b) NSS",
            "c) OSS",
            "d) BSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The BSS provides and manages radio transmission paths between the mobile stations and the Mobile Switching Center (MSC). It also manages the radio interface between the mobile stations and all other subsystems of GSM."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "___________ manages the switching function in GSM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) BSS",
            "b) NSS",
            "c) OSS",
            "d) MSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: NSS (Network and Switching Subsystem) manages the switching functions of the system. It allows the MSCs to communicate with other networks such as PSTN and ISDN."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "__________ supports the operation and maintenance of GSM.",
        "Options": [
            "a) BSS",
            "b) NSS",
            "c) OSS",
            "d) MSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The OSS (Operation Support Subsystem) supports the operation and maintenance of GSM. It allows system engineers to monitor, diagnose, and troubleshoot all aspects of GSM."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "__________ carries digitally encoded user data.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic channels",
            "b) Control channels",
            "c) Signalling channels",
            "d) Forward channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Traffic channels carry digitally encoded user speech or user data. It has identical functions and formats on both the forward and reverse links."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "____________ carries signalling and synchronizing commands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic channels",
            "b) Control channels",
            "c) Signalling channels",
            "d) Forward channels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Control channels carry signalling and synchronizing commands between the base station and mobile station. Certain types of control channels are defined for just the forward or reverse link."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a control channel of GSM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BCH",
            "b) CCCH",
            "c) DCCH",
            "d) TCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are three main control channels in the GSM system. These are the broadcast channel (BCH), the common control channel (CCCH) and the dedicated control channel (DCCH). Each control channel consists of several logical channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the forward control channel that is used to broadcast information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BCCH",
            "b) CCCH",
            "c) DCCH",
            "d) TCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The broadcast control channel (BCCH) is a forward channel that is used to broadcast information such as cell and network identity, and operating characteristics of the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which of the following channel does not come under CCCH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCH",
            "b) RACH",
            "c) DCCH",
            "d) AGCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CCCH consists of three different channels. They are paging channel (PCH), which is a forward link channel, the random access channel (RACH) which is a reverse link channel, and the access grant channel (AGCH) which is a forward link channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Which of the following channel provides paging signals from base station to all mobiles in the cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RACH",
            "b) AGCH",
            "c) DCCH",
            "d) PCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The PCH provides paging signals from the base station to all mobiles in the cell. It notifies a specific mobile of an incoming call which originates from the PSTN."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "___________ is a reverse link channel used by a subscriber unit to acknowledge.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RACH",
            "b) AGCH",
            "c) DCCH",
            "d) PCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The RACH (Random Access Channel) is a reverse link channel used by a subscriber unit to acknowledge a page from the PCH. It is also used by mobiles to originate a call."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "Which of the following channel is used by base station to provide forward link communication to mobile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RACH",
            "b) AGCH",
            "c) DCCH",
            "d) PCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The AGCH (Access Grant Channel) is used by the base station to provide forward link communication to the mobile. It carries data which instructs the mobile to operate in a particular physical channel with particular dedicated control channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Which of the following burst is used to broadcast the frequency and time synchronization control messages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FCCH and SCH",
            "b) TCH and DCCH",
            "c) RACH and TCH",
            "d) FCCH and DCCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FCCH and SCH burst are used to broadcast the frequency and time synchronization control messages. They are used in TS0 of specific frames."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "Which of the following burst is used to access service from any base station?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TCH",
            "b) RACH",
            "c) SCH",
            "d) FCCH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Each user transmits a burst of data during the time slot assigned to it. The RACH burst is used by all mobiles to access service from any base station, and dummy burst is used as filter information for unused timeslots on forward link."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "US digital cellular system based on CDMA was standardized as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IS-54",
            "b) IS-136",
            "c) IS-95",
            "d) IS-76"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A US digital cellular system based on CDMA was standardized as Interim Standard 95 (IS-95). It was standardized by US Telecommunication Industry Association (TIA) and promised increased capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used by IS-95?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DSSS",
            "b) FHSS",
            "c) THSS",
            "d) Hybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Like IS-136, IS-95 system was designed to be compatible with the existing US analog cellular system (AMPS) frequency band. Hence, mobile and base stations can be economically produced for dual mode operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Each IS-95 channel occupies ___________ of spectrum on each one way link.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.25 MHz",
            "b) 1.25 kHz",
            "c) 200 kHz",
            "d) 125 kHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IS-95 uses a direct sequence spread spectrum CDMA system. It allows each user within a cell to use the same radio channel, and users in adjacent cell also use the same radio channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "IS-95 is specified for reverse link operation in _________ band.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 869-894 MHz",
            "b) 849-894 MHz",
            "c) 849-869 MHz",
            "d) 824-849 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To facilitate graceful transition from AMPS to CDMA, each IS-95 channel occupies 1.25 MHz of spectrum on each one way link, or 10% of the available cellular spectrum for a US cellular provider."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "User data in IS-95 is spread to a channel chip rate of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2288 Mchip/s",
            "b) 9.6 Mchip/s",
            "c) 12.288 Mchip/s",
            "d) 0.96 Mchip/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IS-95 uses different modulation and spreading technique for the forward and reverse links. On the forward link, the base station simultaneously transmits the user data for all mobiles in the cell by using different spreading sequence for each mobile."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "__________ are used to resolve and combine multipath components.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equalizer",
            "b) Registers",
            "c) RAKE receiver",
            "d) Frequency divider"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IS-95 is specified for reverse link operation in the 824-849 MHz band and 869-894 MHz for the forward link. The PCS version of IS-95 has also been designed for international use in the 1800-2000 MHz bands."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Cordless telephone standard, DECT stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discrete European Cordless Telephone",
            "b) Digital European Cellular Telephone",
            "c) Discrete European Cellular Telephone",
            "d) Digital European Cordless Telephone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Digital European Cordless Telephone (DECT) is a universal cordless telephone standard. It was developed by the European Telecommunications Standard Institute (ETSI)."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for DECT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High traffic density",
            "b) Long range telecommunication",
            "c) Broad range of application",
            "d) First pan European standard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DECT provides a cordless communication framework for high traffic density, short range telecommunications. It covers a broad range of applications and environments."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "The DECT system is based on __________ principles.",
        "Options": [
            "a) TCP",
            "b) IP",
            "c) OSI",
            "d) AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main function of DECT is to provide local mobility to portable users in an in-building Private Branch Exchange (PBX). It provides excellent quality and services for voice and data applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Which of the following layer consists of paging channel and control channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical layer",
            "b) Network layer",
            "c) Data link layer",
            "d) MAC layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DECT system is based on OSI (Open System Interconnection) principles in a manner similar to ISDN. A control plane (C-plane) and a user plane (U-plane) use the services provided by the lower layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Which of the following layer is responsible for providing reliable data links?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical layer",
            "b) Network layer",
            "c) Data link control layer",
            "d) MAC layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The MAC (Medium Access Control) layer consists of a paging channel and a control channel for the transfer of signalling information to the C-plane. The U-plane is served with channels for the transfer of user information."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "__________ is the main signalling layer of DECT.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical layer",
            "b) Network layer",
            "c) Data link layer",
            "d) MAC layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DLC (data link control) layer is responsible for providing reliable data links to the network layer. It divides up the logical and physical channels into time slots for each user."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Which of the following supports the physical layer of DECT common air interface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Portable Handset",
            "b) Network specific Interface Unit",
            "c) Radio Fixed Part",
            "d) Cordless controller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The network layer is the main signalling layer of DECT. It is based on GSM and ISDN (layer 3) protocols. It provides call control and circuit switched services selected from one of the DLC services."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "________ supports the call completion facility in a multihandset environment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Portable Handset",
            "b) Network specific Interface Unit",
            "c) Radio Fixed Part",
            "d) Cordless controller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RFP (Radio Fixed Part) supports the physical layer of the DECT common air interface. Every RFP covers one cell in the microcellular system. A full duplex operation is achieved using TDD."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "__________ is a third generation Personal Communication System.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PACS",
            "b) AMPS",
            "c) IS-95",
            "d) GSM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Network specific Interface Unit supports the call completion facility in a multihandset environment. The interface recommended by the CCITT is the G.732 based on ISDN protocols."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "_________ is also known as Japanese Digital Cellular.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PACS",
            "b) AMPS",
            "c) PDC",
            "d) GSM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PACS (Personal Access Communication Systems) is a third generation Personal Communication System. It was originally developed and proposed by Bellcore in 1992."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Several protocols for upper layers in bluetooth use _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UDP",
            "b) HSP",
            "c) ITC",
            "d) L2CAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: L2CAP is Logical Link, Control Adaptation Protocol Layer. The logical unit link control adaptation protocol is equivalent to logical link control sub layer of LAN. The ACL link uses L2CAP for data exchange. The various function of L2CAP is segmentation and reassembly, multiplexing and quality of service."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Protocols are set of rules to govern _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Communication",
            "b) Standard",
            "c) Metropolitan communication",
            "d) Bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A protocol is a set of rules that governs the communications between computers on a network. These rules include guidelines that regulate the characteristics of a network including access method, allowed physical topologies, types of cabling, and speed of data transfer."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "An internet is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collection of WANS",
            "b) Network of networks",
            "c) Collection of LANS",
            "d) Collection of identical LANS and WANS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Internet is a massive network of networks, a networking infrastructure. It connects millions of computers together globally, forming a network in which any computer can communicate with any other computer as long as they are both connected to the Internet."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Checksum is used in Internet by several protocols although not at the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Session layer",
            "b) Transport layer",
            "c) Network layer",
            "d) Data link layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The checksum is used in the Internet by several protocols although not at the data link layer. Like linear and cyclic codes, the checksum is based on the concept of redundancy. Several protocols still use the checksum for error detection."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "In version field of IPv4 header, when machine is using some other version of IPv4 then datagram is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discarded",
            "b) Accepted",
            "c) Interpreted",
            "d) Interpreted incorrectly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A 4 bit field defines the version of IPv4 protocol. This field tells the software running in the processing machine that the datagram has the format of version 4. If the machine is using some other version of IPv4, the datagram is discarded rather than interpreted incorrectly."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Network layer at source is responsible for creating a packet from data coming from another ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Station",
            "b) Link",
            "c) Node",
            "d) Protocol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ‘The network layer at the source is responsible for creating a packet from the data coming from another’ protocol (such as a transport layer protocol or a routing protocol). The network layer is responsible for checking its routing table to find the routing information."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Header of datagram in IPv4 has _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 to 20 bytes",
            "b) 20 to 40 bytes",
            "c) 20 to 60 bytes",
            "d) 20 to 80 bytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IP header length is a minimum of 20 bytes and a maximum of 60 bytes. The minimum value for this field is 5, which is a length of 5×32 = 160 bits = 20 bytes. Being a 4-bit value, the maximum length is 15 words (15×32 bits) or 480 bits = 60 bytes."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "In IPv4 layer, datagram is of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed length",
            "b) Variable length",
            "c) Global length",
            "d) Zero length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ‘IPv4 is a connectionless protocol used for packet switched networks. It operates on best effort delivery model, in which neither delivery is guaranteed, nor proper sequencing or avoidance of duplicate delivery is assured. The size of the datagram header can be of variable length from 20 bytes to 60 bytes.’"
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "In IPv4, service type of service in header field, first 3 bits are called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of service",
            "b) Code bits",
            "c) Sync bits",
            "d) Precedence bits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 8-bit ToS (type of service) in IPv4 uses 3 bits for IP Precedence, 4 bits for ToS with the last bit not being used. The 4-bit ToS field, although defined, has never been used."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Which is a link layer protocol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARP",
            "b) TCP",
            "c) UDP",
            "d) HTTP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ‘In computer networking, the link layer is the lowest layer in the Internet Protocol Suite. It is commonly known as TCP/IP, the networking architecture of the Internet. It is described in RFC 1122 and RFC 1123.’"
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Which protocol is commonly used to retrieve email from a mail server?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FTP",
            "b) IMAP",
            "c) HTML",
            "d) TELNET"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ‘The Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) is a mail protocol used for accessing email on a remote web server from a local client. IMAP is the most commonly used Internet mail protocols for retrieving emails. It is supported by all modern email clients and web servers.’"
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "What layer in the TCP/IP stack is equivalent to the Transport layer of the OSI model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Application",
            "b) Host to host",
            "c) Internet",
            "d) Network Access"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The four layers of the TCP/IP stack (also called the DoD model) are Application/Process, Host-to-Host, Internet, and Network Access. The Host-to-Host layer is equivalent to the Transport layer of the OSI model."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "You want to implement a mechanism that automates the IP configuration, including IP address, subnet mask, default gateway, and DNS information. Which protocol will you use to accomplish this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SMTP",
            "b) SNMP",
            "c) DHCP",
            "d) ARP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) is used to provide IP information to hosts on your network. DHCP can provide a lot of information, but the most common is the IP address, subnet mask, default gateway, and DNS information. "
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "The DoD model (also called the TCP/IP stack) has four layers. Which layer of the DoD model is equivalent to the Network layer of the OSI model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Application",
            "b) Host to Host",
            "c) Internet",
            "d) Network Access"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The four layers of the DoD model are Application/Process, Host-to-Host, Internet, and Network Access. The Internet layer is equivalent to the Network layer of the OSI model."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "Which of the following protocols uses both TCP and UDP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FTP",
            "b) SMTP",
            "c) Telnet",
            "d) DNS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNS and some other services work on both TCP and the UDP protocols. DNS uses TCP for zone exchanges between servers and UDP when a client is trying to resolve a hostname to an IP address."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "Length of Port address in TCP/IP is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4bit long",
            "b) 16bit long",
            "c) 32bit long",
            "d) 8 bit long"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TCP and UDP port numbers are 16 bits in length. So, valid port numbers can theoretically take on values from 0 to 65,535. These values are divided into ranges for different purposes, with certain ports reserved for particular uses."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "TCP/IP layer is equivalent to combined Session, Presentation and _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Network layer",
            "b) Application layer",
            "c) Transport layer",
            "d) Physical layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TCP/IP network model is a hierarchical protocol made up of interactive modules, each of which provides a specific functionality; however, the modules are not necessarily interdependent. It is equivalent to combined session, presentation and application layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "How many levels of addressing is provided in TCP/IP protocol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Four levels of addresses are used in the internet employing the TCP/IP protocols. They are physical (link) addresses, logical (IP) addresses, port addresses, and specific addresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Virtual terminal protocol is an example of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Network layer",
            "b) Application layer",
            "c) Transport layer",
            "d) Physical layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In open systems, a virtual terminal (VT) is an application service. It allows host terminals on a multi-user network to interact with other hosts regardless of terminal type and characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "TCP/IP is related to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARPANET",
            "b) OSI",
            "c) DECNET",
            "d) ALOHA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1983, TCP/IP protocols replaced NCP (Network Control Program) as the ARPANET’s principal protocol. And ARPANET then became one component of the early Internet. The starting point for host-to-host communication on the ARPANET in 1969 was the 1822 protocol, which defined the transmission of messages to an IMP."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "A device operating at network layer is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Router",
            "b) Equalizer",
            "c) Bridge",
            "d) Repeater"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A router is a networking device that forwards data packets between computer networks. Routers perform the traffic directing functions on the Internet. It supports different network layer transmission standards. Each network interface is used to enable data packets to be forwarded from one transmission system to another."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "A device operating at physical layer is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Router",
            "b) Equalizer",
            "c) Bridge",
            "d) Repeater"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A repeater connects two segments of your network cable. It retimes and regenerates the signals to proper amplitudes and sends them to the other segments. Repeaters work only at the physical layer of the OSI network model."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "A packet in Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) is called a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmittable slots",
            "b) Packet",
            "c) Segment",
            "d) Source Slots"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Applications working at the Application Layer transfers a contiguous stream of bytes to the bottom layers. It is the duty of TCP to pack this byte stream to packets, known as TCP segments, which are passed to the IP layer for transmission to the destination device."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Cable TV and DSL are examples of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interconnection of network",
            "b) LAN",
            "c) MAN",
            "d) WAN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A MAN often acts as a high speed network to allow sharing of regional resources. It typically covers an area of between 5 and 50 km diameter. Examples of MAN are telephone company network that provides a high speed DSL to customers and cable TV network."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Station on a wireless ALOHA network is maximum of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400 Km",
            "b) 500 Km",
            "c) 600 Km",
            "d) 700 Km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stations on wireless ALOHA networks are a maximum of 600 km apart. It was designed for a radio (wireless) LAN, but it can be used on any shared medium. It is obvious that there are potential collisions in this arrangement. The medium is shared between the stations."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "IEEE 802.11 defines basic service set as building block of a wireless ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LAN",
            "b) WAN protocol",
            "c) MAN",
            "d) ALOHA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The IEEE 802.11 topology consists of components interacting to provide a wireless LAN. It enables station mobility transparent to higher protocol layers, such as the LLC. "
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "In wireless LAN, there are many hidden stations so that __________ cannot be detected.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frames",
            "b) Collision",
            "c) Signal",
            "d) Data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In wireless networking, the hidden node problem or hidden terminal problem occurs when a node is visible from a wireless access point (AP), but not from other nodes communicating with said AP. This leads to difficulties in media access control and collisions could not be detected."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "A set that makes stationary or mobile wireless station and also have optional central base station is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basic service set",
            "b) Extended service set",
            "c) Network point set",
            "d) Access point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A set that makes stationary or mobile wireless station and also have optional central base station is known as a basic service set. BSS is made of stationary or mobile wireless stations and an optional central base station, known as the access point (AP)."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Wireless communication started in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1869",
            "b) 1895",
            "c) 1879",
            "d) 1885"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In England, Guglielmo Marconi began his wireless experiments in 1895. On 2 June 1896, he filed his provisional specification of a patent for wireless telegraphy. He demonstrated the system to the British Post Office in July."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "Wireless transmission is divided into ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 broad groups",
            "b) 6 broad groups",
            "c) 9 broad groups",
            "d) 8 broad groups"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We can divide wireless transmission into three broad groups: radio waves, microwaves, and infrared waves. Radio waves are used for multicast communications, such as AM and FM radio, television, maritime radio, cordless phones and paging systems. Microwave propagation is line-of-sight."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "Transmission Control Protocol/Internet Networking Protocol have ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Four Layers",
            "b) Five Layers",
            "c) Six Layers",
            "d) Seven Layers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TCP/IP functionality is divided into four layers, each with its own set of agreed-upon protocols: The datalink layer consists of methods and protocols that operate only on a link. The Internet layer connects independent networks to transport the packets. The Transport layer handles communications between. The Application layer standardizes data exchange for applications. "
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "Packets of data that is transported by IP is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Datagrams",
            "b) Frames",
            "c) Segments",
            "d) Encapsulate message"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The format of data that can be recognized by IP is called an IP datagram. It consists of two components, the header and data, which need to be transmitted. The fields in the datagram, except the data, have specific roles to perform in the transmission of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "Parameter that is normally achieved through a trailer added to end of frame is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Access Control",
            "b) Flow Control",
            "c) Error Control",
            "d) Physical addressing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The data link layer adds reliability to the physical layer by adding mechanisms to detect and retransmit damaged or lost frames. It also uses a mechanism to recognize duplicate frames. Error control is normally achieved through a trailer added to the end of the frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "IPv6 has a larger address space of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 216",
            "b) 2128",
            "c) 232",
            "d) 28"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main advantage of IPv6 over IPv4 is its larger address space. The length of an IPv6 address is 128 bits, compared with 32 bits in IPv4. The address space therefore has 2128 or approximately 3.4×1038 addresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Three strategies used to handle transition from version 4 to version 6 are dual-stack, tunneling and ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Header Switching",
            "b) Header Translation",
            "c) Header Transfer",
            "d) Header Transmission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Three strategies used to handle transition from version 4 to version 6 are dual-stack, tunneling and header translation. Header translation techniques are more complicated than IPv4 NAT because the protocols have different header formats. "
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "MTU stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum Transfer Unit",
            "b) Maximum Transfer Unit",
            "c) Maximum Transport Unit",
            "d) Maximum Transmission Unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In computer networking, the maximum transmission unit (MTU) is the size of the largest network layer protocol data unit that can be communicated in a single network transaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "In IPv6, real-time audio or video, particularly in digital form, requires resources such as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed Bandwidth",
            "b) Variable Bandwidth",
            "c) High Bandwidth",
            "d) Low Bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In IPv6, real-time audio or video, particularly in digital form, requires resources such as high bandwidth, large buffers, long processing times, and so on. A process can make a reservation for these resources beforehand to guarantee that real time data will not be delayed."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "In practical IPv6 application, a technology encapsulates IPv6 packets inside IPv4 packets, this technology is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tunneling",
            "b) Hashing",
            "c) Routing",
            "d) NAT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IPv6 tunneling enables IPv6 hosts and routers to connect with other IPv6 hosts and routers over the existing IPv4 Internet. The main purpose of IPv6 tunneling is to deploy IPv6 as well as maintain compatibility with large existing base of IPv4 hosts and routers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Which one of the following descriptions about IPv6 is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addresses are not hierarchical and are assigned at random",
            "b) Broadcasts have been eliminated and replaced with multicasts",
            "c) There are 2.7 billion available addresses",
            "d) An interface can only be configured with one IPv6 address"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In IPv6, there’s no longer any broadcast, sending one packet to a large number of unspecified hosts. There’s only multicast, unicast and anycast. In IPv6 all nodes are required to support multicast."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "The header length of an IPv6 datagram is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10bytes",
            "b) 25bytes",
            "c) 30bytes",
            "d) 40bytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IPv6 datagram has fixed header length of 40bytes. It results in faster processing of the datagram. Fixed length IPv6 header allows the routers to process the IPv6 datagram packets more efficiently."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "In the IPv6 header, the traffic class field is similar to which field in the IPv4 header?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fragmentation field",
            "b) Fast switching",
            "c) TOS field",
            "d) Option field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This field enables to have different types of IP datagram. In an IPv6 packet, the Traffic Class byte is used in the same way as the ToS byte in an IPv4 packet. A ToS/Traffic Class byte includes a DSCP (Differentiated Services Codepoint) and precedence bits."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Which are the features present in IPv4 but not in IPv6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fragmentation",
            "b) Header checksum",
            "c) Options",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the features are only present in IPv4 and not IPv6. IPv6 no longer has a header checksum to protect the IP header, meaning that when a packet header is corrupted by transmission errors, the packet is very likely to be delivered incorrectly."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "IPv6 is designed to allow extension of the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protocol",
            "b) Dataset",
            "c) Headers",
            "d) Routes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IPv6 is designed to allow the extension of the protocol if required by new technologies or applications. IPv6 uses a new header format in which options are separated from the base header and inserted, when needed, between the base header and upper-layer data."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "In IPv6, base header can be followed by, up to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Six Extension Layers",
            "b) Six Extension Headers",
            "c) Eight Extension headers",
            "d) Eight Extension layers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The length of the base header is 40 bytes. However, to give more functionality to the IP datagram, the base header can be followed by up to six extension headers."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "In an IPv6 datagram, M bit is 0, value of HLEN is 5, value of total length is 200 and offset value is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400",
            "b) 350",
            "c) 300",
            "d) 200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In an IPv6 datagram, M bit is 0, value of HLEN is 5, the value of total length is 200 and offset value is 200. If the M bit is 0, it means there are no more fragments, the fragment is the last name."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "A helical antenna is used for satellite tracking because of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular polarization",
            "b) Maneuverability",
            "c) Beamwidth",
            "d) Gain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In helical antenna, the diameter and pitch of the helix are comparable to a wavelength. The antenna functions as a directional antenna radiating a beam off the ends of the helix. It radiates circularly polarized radio waves. These are used for satellite communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Repeaters inside communications satellites are known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transceivers",
            "b) Transponders",
            "c) Transducers",
            "d) TWT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A communications satellite’s transponder is the series of interconnected units that form a communications channel between the receiving and the transmitting antennas. It is mainly used in satellite communication to transfer the received signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "___________ is the geographical representation of a satellite antenna radiation pattern.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Footprint",
            "b) Spot",
            "c) Earth",
            "d) Region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The geographical representation of a satellite’s antenna radiation pattern is called a footprint or footprint map. In essence, a footprint of a satellite is the area on Earth’s surface that the satellite can receive from or transmit to."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "The smallest beam of a satellite antenna radiation pattern is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zone beam",
            "b) Hemispheric beam",
            "c) Spot beam",
            "d) Global beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The size of the antenna that generates these beams on earth is related directly to the peak gain at the center of the spot beams and the smallest spot beam size. The spot beams are typically defined by the contours at 3 or 4 dB down from the peak power at the center of the beam. "
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "_________ detects the satellite signal relayed from the feed and converts it to an electric current, amplifies and lowers its frequency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horn antenna",
            "b) LNA",
            "c) Satellite receiver",
            "d) Satellite dish"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LNA detects the satellite signal relayed from the feed and converts it to an electric current, amplifies and lower its frequency. The most common device used as an LNA is tunnel diode."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "A satellite signal transmitted from a satellite transponder to earth’s station is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uplink",
            "b) Downlink",
            "c) Terrestrial",
            "d) Earthbound"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In satellite telecommunication, a downlink is the link from a satellite down to one or more ground stations or receivers, and an uplink is the link from a ground station up to a satellite. "
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "__________ is a loss of power of a satellite downlink signal due to earth’s atmosphere.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atmospheric loss",
            "b) Path loss",
            "c) Radiation loss",
            "d) RFI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The path loss is the loss in signal strength of a signal as it travels through free space. This value is usually calculated by discounting any obstacles or reflections that might occur in its path."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the point on the satellite orbits closest to the Earth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Apogee",
            "b) Perigee",
            "c) Prograde",
            "d) Zenith"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The point where satellite is closest to the Earth is known as the perigee. Here, the satellite moves at its fastest. The high point of the orbit, when the satellite is moving the slowest is called the apogee."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "What kind of battery panels are used in some advanced satellites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Germanium based panels",
            "b) Silicon based panel",
            "c) Gallium Phosphate solar panel array",
            "d) Gallium Arsenide solar panel array"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gallium Arsenide solar panel arrays are used for battery panels in some advanced satellites. These new types of cells allow smaller solar arrays to be used on future space missions."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "A satellite battery has more power but lighter _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lithium",
            "b) Leclanche",
            "c) Hydrogen",
            "d) Magnesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lithium batteries have more power and are lighter in weight. Any mass that could be saved by the use of lighter batteries would allow a corresponding increase in the amount of useful payload equipment."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "INTELSAT stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intel Satellite",
            "b) International Telephone Satellite",
            "c) International Telecommunications Satellite",
            "d) International Satellite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: INTELSAT is a communications satellite services provider. INTELSAT operates a fleet of 52 communications satellites, which is one of the world’s largest fleet of commercial satellites."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "The frequency of Ku band for satellite communications is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6/4 GHz",
            "b) 14/11 GHz",
            "c) 12/14 GHz",
            "d) 4/8 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Ku band is a portion of the electromagnetic spectrum in the microwave range of frequencies ranging from 11.7 to 12.7GHz. (downlink frequencies) and 14 to 14.5GHz (uplink frequencies)."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "The most common device used as an LNA is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zener diode",
            "b) Tunnel diode",
            "c) IMPATT",
            "d) Shockley diode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The LNA must provide a relatively flat response for the frequency range of interest, preferably with less than 1 dB of gain variation. The most common device used as an LNA (low noise amplifier) is tunnel diode. It is a highly sensitive, low-noise device. "
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Which of the following technology is mainly designed for indoor coverage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Femtocell network",
            "b) 3GPP",
            "c) LTE",
            "d) AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Femtocell Network is a small-size Macro cell network designed for better indoor coverage. It began attracting attention from both industry and academy in late 2007."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of Femtocell network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F-BS",
            "b) Internet link",
            "c) FGW",
            "d) BSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The “femto” means 10-15. Coverage of Femtocell Network is much smaller than a regular Macro cell Network that is why this name is given. Femtocell Network, installed by end users at home or in an office environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for Femtocell base stations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short range",
            "b) Low power",
            "c) High cost",
            "d) Wireless handsets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Similar to UMTS Terrestrial Radio Access Network (UTRAN) architecture, the Femtocell Network consists of three components: Femtocell Base Stations (F-BS), Internet Link, and Femtocell Gateway (FGW)."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "________ acts as a gateway between the Internet and communication network.",
        "Options": [
            "a) F-BS",
            "b) Internet link",
            "c) FGW",
            "d) BSC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Femtocell Base Stations (F-BSs) are short-range, low-cost, low-power indoor devices to provide service for wireless handsets. F-BS, which looks like WLAN Access Point (AP), is a small device with at least two wireless and internet interfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "In _________ all cellular users belong to open subscribers group (OSG) and can access F-BS unconditionally.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Closed access mode",
            "b) Open access mode",
            "c) Hybrid Access mode",
            "d) Zero access mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wireless interface provides wireless radio access to Femtocell MSs. Any existing wireless telecommunication standard, such as UMTS/ CDMA200/ WIMAX/ LTE/ EV-DO, can be used at the F-BS wireless interfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "In _______ a closed subscribers group (CSG) is set by F-BS owner to allow only small portion of cellular users to be served in the Femtocell Network.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Closed access mode",
            "b) Open access mode",
            "c) Hybrid Access mode",
            "d) Zero access mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Femtocell Gateway (FGW) is a service provider’s device that acts as a gateway between the Internet and the communication network. One side of FGW connects a large number of F-BSs via broadband Internet, and the other side of FGW is connected to the telephony core network."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "_________ also known as impulse or zero-carrier radio technology.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultra wideband technology",
            "b) Femtocell technology",
            "c) Multicasting",
            "d) Multiplexing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ultra-wideband (UWB) technology is also known as impulse or zero-carrier radio technology. It appears to be one of the most promising wireless radio communication technologies of recent time."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "In TM–UWB, the system uses a modulation technique called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse width modulation",
            "b) Pulse code modulation",
            "c) Pulse position modulation",
            "d) Pulse amplitude modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Unlike conventional radio systems, which operate within a relatively narrow bandwidth, the UWB radio system operates across a wide range of the frequency spectrum by transmitting a series of extremely narrow (10–1000 per second) and low-power pulses."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "DSC-UWB uses _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse width modulation",
            "b) Pulse code modulation",
            "c) Pulse position modulation",
            "d) Direct sequence modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The basic element in TM–UWB technology is the monocycle wavelet. Typically, wavelet pulse widths are between 0.2 and 1.5 nanoseconds, corresponding to center frequencies between 600 MHz and 5 GHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "The coherent interaction of signals in UWB arriving by many paths causes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ricean fading",
            "b) Nakagami fading",
            "c) Rayleigh fading",
            "d) Multicast fading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In TM–UWB, the system uses a modulation technique called pulse position modulation. The TM–UWB transmitter emits ultra-short monocycle wavelets with tightly controlled pulse-to-pulse intervals, which are varied on a pulse-by-pulse basis in accordance with an information signal and a channel code."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for UWB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large spectrum",
            "b) Lower price",
            "c) Pulse data",
            "d) Large interference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In DSC-UWB, the signal is spread by direct sequence modulating a wavelet pulse trains at duty cycles approaching that of a sine wave carrier. The spectrum spreading, channelization, and modulation are provided by a PN (pseudo noise) sequence, and the chipping rate is maintained as some fraction of the carrier center frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a drawback of UWB technology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Not appropriate for WAN",
            "b) Power limited",
            "c) Small spectrum",
            "d) Limited jitter requirements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The coherent interaction of signals arriving by many paths causes the Rayleigh or multipath fading in RF communications. Inside buildings, when continuous sine waves are transmitted wherein the channels exhibit multipath differential delays in the nanosecond range, the multipath fading occurs naturally."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "_______ is responsible for tunneling multicast packets to the MS’s currently subscribed FA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multicast home agent",
            "b) Mobile multicast",
            "c) Mobile station",
            "d) Base station"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Multicast home agent (MHA) is responsible for tunneling multicast packets to the MS’s currently subscribed FA. MHA serves MSs that are roaming around the foreign networks and are within its service range."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "_______ provides a fast and efficient handoff for MSs in foreign networks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MHA",
            "b) MMP",
            "c) CBT",
            "d) MS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Every MS can have only one MHA, which dynamically changes based on the location of the MS, whereas a HA of an MS never changes. The protocol requires that each MHA must be a multicast group member."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "MMP combines the concepts of _______ and ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mobile IPs, GSM",
            "b) Core based trees, GSM",
            "c) Mobile IPs, core based trees",
            "d) Core based trees, LTE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MMP provides a fast and efficient handoff for MSs in foreign networks. It also enables location-independent addressing."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "________ designed for an Internet work environment with small wireless cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMP",
            "b) RMDP",
            "c) RM2",
            "d) Mobicast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MMP combines the concepts of Mobile IP and core-based trees (CBT). Here the former controls communication up to the foreign network, and the latter manages movement of the MSs inside them."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "________ serve as multicast forwarding agents and are meant to isolate the mobility of the mobile host from the main multicast delivery tree.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DFA",
            "b) MHA",
            "c) FA",
            "d) MMP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mobicast is designed for an Internet work environment with small wireless cells. It assumes that a set of cells are grouped together and are served by a domain foreign agent (DFA)."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "_______ is meant to be implemented for use on the MBONE.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMP",
            "b) RMDP",
            "c) RM2",
            "d) Mobicast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DFAs serve as multicast forwarding agents and are meant to isolate the mobility of the mobile host from the main multicast delivery tree. This hierarchical mobility management approach tries to isolate the mobility of the FAs from the main multicast delivery tree."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "__________ is a reliable multicast protocol and is used for both wired and wireless environments.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMP",
            "b) RMDP",
            "c) RM2",
            "d) Mobicast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mobicast is based on a method proposed by the IETF to support multicast over Mobile-IP. To handle the case when an MS is both the source and recipient of a multicast session, one needs to minimize the possibility of rebuilding the complete multicast tree at each foreign domain the MS visits."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "____________ relies on IGMP.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMP",
            "b) RMDP",
            "c) RM2",
            "d) Mobicast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reliable multicast data distribution protocol (RMDP) is meant to be implemented for use on the MBONE. It relies on the use of FEC and ARQ information to provide reliable multicast service."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Which UE category supports 64 QAM on the uplink?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only category 5",
            "b) Only category 4",
            "c) Only category 3",
            "d) Category 3,4 and 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Category information is used to allow the eNB to communicate effectively with all the UEs connected to it. The UE-category defines a combined uplink and downlink capability. Only UE category 5 supports 64 QAM on the uplink. "
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "What type of handovers is supported by LTE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hard handover only",
            "b) Soft handover only",
            "c) Hard and soft handover",
            "d) Hard, soft and softest handover"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LTE supports only hard handover. It does not receive data from two frequencies at the same time because switching between different carrier frequencies is very fast so soft handover is not required."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "What is the minimum amount of RF spectrum needed for an FDD LTE radio channel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.4 MHz",
            "b) 2.8 MHz",
            "c) 5 MHz",
            "d) 20 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In telecommunication, Long-Term Evolution (LTE) is a standard for high-speed wireless communication for mobile devices and data terminals, based on the GSM/EDGE and UMTS/HSPA technologies. The minimum amount of RF spectrum needed for an FDD LTE radio channel is 2.8 MHz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "Which organization is responsible for developing LTE standards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UMTS",
            "b) 3GPP",
            "c) 3GPP2",
            "d) ISO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) is a collaboration between groups of telecommunications standards associations, known as the Organizational Partners. LTE (Long Term Evolution) introduced in 3GPP R8, is the access part of the Evolved Packet System (EPS)."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Which channel indicates the number of symbols used by the PDCCH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PHICH",
            "b) PDCCH",
            "c) PBCH",
            "d) PCFICH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCFIH channel indicates the number of symbols used by the PDCCH. The actual number of OFDM symbols occupied in any given subframe is indicated in the PCFICH (Physical Control Format Indicator Channel), which is located in the first OFDM symbol of each subframe."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "How often can resources be allocated to the UE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Every symbol",
            "b) Every slot",
            "c) Every subframe",
            "d) Every frame"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Resources can be located to the UE every subframe. CCE Index is the CCE number at which the control channel data (PDCCH) is allocated. Normally this index changes for each subframe, i.e. even the same PDCCH data (e.g, a PDCCH for the same UE) allocated in each subframe changes subframe by subframe."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "What is the largest channel bandwidth a UE is required to support in LTE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 MHz",
            "b) 20 MHz",
            "c) 1.4 MHz",
            "d) 5 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The LTE format was first proposed by NTT DoCoMo of Japan and has been adopted as the international standard. LTE-Advanced accommodates the geographically available spectrum for channels above 20 MHz. "
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "In LTE, what is the benefit of PAPR reduction in the uplink?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improved uplink coverage",
            "b) Lower UE power consumption",
            "c) Reduced equalizer complexity",
            "d) Improved uplink coverage, lower UE power consumption and reduced equalizer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PAPR is the relation between the maximum power of a sample in a given OFDM transmit symbol divided by the average power of that OFDM symbol. PAPR reduction in the uplink leads to improved uplink coverage, lower UE power consumption and reduced equalizer complexity."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Which RLC mode adds the least amount of delay to user traffic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unacknowledged mode (UM)",
            "b) Acknowledged mode (AM)",
            "c) Low latency mode (LM)",
            "d) Transparent mode (TM)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transparent mode entity in RLC does not add any overhead to the upper layer SDUs. The entity just transmits the SDUs coming from upper layer to MAC."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "How much bandwidth is required to transmit the primary and secondary synchronization signals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.08 MHz",
            "b) 1.4 MHz",
            "c) 930 kHz",
            "d) 20 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell synchronization is the very first step when UE wants to camp on any cell. 1.08 MHZ is required to transmit the primary and secondary synchronization signals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Which type of cell provides the best level of service for average subscribers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance cell",
            "b) Barred cell",
            "c) Reserved cell",
            "d) Suitable cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A suitable cell is a cell on which the UE may camp on to obtain normal service. The UE shall have a valid USIM and such a cell shall fulfil all the following requirements. It provides the best level of service for average subscribers."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "With the normal cyclic prefix, how many symbols are contained in 1 frame?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7",
            "b) 140",
            "c) 12",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two different type of Cyclic Prefix. One is normal Cyclic Prefix and the other is ‘Extended Cyclic Prefix’ which is longer than the Normal Cyclic Prefix. Normal cyclic prefix contains 140 symbols in 1 frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "What is the PBCH scrambled with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Current frame number",
            "b) Physical cell ID",
            "c) UE’s CRNTI",
            "d) Not scrambled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The PBCH is scrambled prior to modulation with a cell-specific sequence that depends on the cells’ identity. In contrast to the synchronization signals, the PBCH is transmitted on the 72 reserved subcarriers, which are QPSK-modulated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "What is the length of the shortest possible PDCCH in bits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 144",
            "b) 288",
            "c) 72",
            "d) 576"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PDCCH is a physical channel that carries downlink control information (DCI). Shortest possible PDCCH is 72 bits."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "What is the average uploading speed of 4G LTE network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-3 Gbps",
            "b) 2-5 Gbps",
            "c) 1-3 Mbps",
            "d) 2-5 Mbps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Verizon 4G LTE wireless broadband is 10 times faster than 3G able to handle download speeds between 5 and 12 Mbps (Megabits per second) and upload speeds between 2 and 5 Mbps."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of the characteristic of 4G network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multirate management",
            "b) Fully converged services",
            "c) Software dependency",
            "d) Diverse user devices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 4G is the fourth generation of broadband cellular network technology, succeeding 3G. Its characteristics include fully converged services, software dependency and diverse user devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "What does SGSN stands for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serving GPRS Support Node",
            "b) Supporting GGSN Support Node",
            "c) Supporting GPRS Support Node",
            "d) Supporting Gateway Support Node"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Serving GPRS Support Node (SGSN) is a main component of the GPRS network, which handles all packet switched data within the network, e.g. the mobility management and authentication of the users. The SGSN performs the same functions as the MSC for voice traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "What location management feature is supported by 4G?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concatenated Location Registration",
            "b) Concurrent Location Register",
            "c) Concatenated Management",
            "d) Collated Location Registration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 4G supports concatenated location registration. Concatenated location registration reports to the network that they are concatenated to a common object. "
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "In 2007 ____________ announced its plan to transmit its network to 4G standard LTE with joint efforts of Vodafone group.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verizon Wireless",
            "b) AirTouch",
            "c) Netflix",
            "d) V Cast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 2007, Verizon announced plans to develop and deploy its fourth generation mobile broadband network using LTE, the technology developed within the Third Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) standards organization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "Hybrid ARQ is part of the ____________ layer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PDCP",
            "b) RLC",
            "c) MAC",
            "d) PHY"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hybrid automatic repeat request (hybrid ARQ or HARQ) is a combination of high-rate forward error-correcting coding and ARQ error-control. It is part of the MAC layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "OFDMA stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) omnidirectional frequency division multiple access",
            "b) orthogonal frequency duplex multiple access",
            "c) orthogonal frequency divider multiple access",
            "d) orthogonal frequency division multiple access"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Orthogonal frequency-division multiple access (OFDMA) is a multi-user version of the popular orthogonal frequency-division multiplexing (OFDM) digital modulation scheme. Multiple access is achieved in OFDMA by assigning subsets of subcarriers to individual users."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Why is a cyclic prefix required in an OFDMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To ensure symbol time is an integer number",
            "b) To help overcome multipath and ISI",
            "c) To maintain orthogonality",
            "d) To make OFDMA scalable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Use of cyclic prefix is a key element of enabling the OFDM signal to operate reliably. The cyclic prefix acts as a buffer region or guard interval to protect the OFDM signals from intersymbol interference."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "What does the DC subcarrier indicate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Identity of the cell",
            "b) Antenna configuration",
            "c) Center of OFDM channel",
            "d) Format of data channel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All the subcarriers of an OFDM symbol do not carry useful data. In OFDM and OFDMA PHY layers, the DC subcarrier is the subcarrier whose frequency is equal to the RF centre frequency of the transmitting station. "
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "What processing step combines multiple OFDM subcarriers into a single signal for transmission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FFT",
            "b) IFFT",
            "c) RF combining",
            "d) Channel mapping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IFFT combines multiple OFDM subcarriers into a single signal for transmission. These transforms are important from the OFDM perspective because they can be viewed as mapping digitally modulated input data (data symbols) onto orthogonal subcarriers."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "Which property of OFDMA system allows adjacent subcarriers to be used without interference?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orthogonality",
            "b) Orthodoxy",
            "c) Octagonality",
            "d) Originality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Orthogonality of sub-carriers simply means their correlation is zero. Orthogonality in OFDMA system allows adjacent subcarriers to be used without interference. "
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "In OFDMA, what is the relationship between the subcarrier spacing f and symbol time t?",
        "Options": [
            "a) f=t",
            "b) f=1/2t",
            "c) f=1/t",
            "d) no relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In OFDMA, the relationship between the subcarrier spacing f and symbol time t is f=1/t. They are inversely proportional."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "When we divide band of Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing (OFDM) into sub bands, it diminishes effects of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) noise",
            "b) collision",
            "c) interference",
            "d) signals absence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: OFDM has developed into a popular scheme for wideband digital communication, used in applications such as digital television and audio broadcasting, DSL internet access, wireless networks, power line networks, and 4G mobile communications."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Common data rates of IEEE 802.11 OFDM are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18 Mbps",
            "b) 200 Mbps",
            "c) 50 Mbps",
            "d) 54 Mbps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ODMA does not use complex equalizers. In OFDM, the equalizer only has to multiply each detected sub-carrier (each Fourier coefficient) in each OFDM symbol by a constant complex number, or a rarely changed value."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "MIMO stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Many input many output",
            "b) Multiple input multiple output",
            "c) Major input minor output",
            "d) Minor input minor output"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MIMO stands for Multiple Input and Multiple Output. It refers to the technology where there are multiple antennas at the base station and multiple antennas at the mobile device."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "In MIMO, which factor has the greatest influence on data rates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The size of antenna",
            "b) The height of the antenna",
            "c) The number of transmit antennas",
            "d) The area of receive antennas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By increasing the number of receiving and transmitting antennas, it is possible to linearly increase the throughput of the channel with every pair of antennas added to the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "MIMO was initially developed in the year __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1980",
            "b) 1990",
            "c) 1980",
            "d) 1975"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the initial development in the year 1990, MIMO Wireless Communications have become integral part of the most forthcoming commercial and next generation wireless data communication systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "MIMO technology makes advantage of a natural radio wave phenomenon called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflection",
            "b) Multipath",
            "c) Refraction",
            "d) Diffraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MIMO is one of several forms of smart antenna technology, the others being MISO (multiple input, single output) and SIMO (single input, multiple output). It is an antenna technology for wireless communications in which multiple antennas are used at both the source and the destination."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Which of the following technology does not use MIMO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4G",
            "b) Wifi",
            "c) WiMax",
            "d) AMPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MIMO technology makes use of multipath phenomenon to maximize transmission by receiving bounced signals from obstructions. Multipath is a phenomenon in wave propagation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "_______ is a technique of transmit diversity used in UMTSS third-generation cellular systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) STTD",
            "b) SM",
            "c) Collaborative Uplink MIMO",
            "d) MU-MIMO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: MIMO is used in mobile radio telephone standards such as recent 3GPP and 3GPP2. In 3GPP, High-Speed Packet Access plus (HSPA+) and Long Term Evolution (LTE) standards take MIMO into account. Moreover, MIMO is also used in Wifi and WiMax."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "_______ is a transmission method used in MIMO wireless communications to transmit encoded data signals independently.",
        "Options": [
            "a) STTD",
            "b) SM",
            "c) Collaborative Uplink MIMO",
            "d) MU-MIMO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MIMO provides a way of utilising the multiple signal paths that exist between a transmitter and receiver to significantly improve the data throughput available on a given channel with its defined bandwidth. It uses multiple antennas at the transmitter and receiver along with some complex digital signal processing."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "_______ is an additional open-loop MIMO technique considered by the WiMAX vendors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) STTD",
            "b) SM",
            "c) Collaborative Uplink MIMO",
            "d) MU-MIMO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Space Time Transmit Diversity (STTD) is a technique of transmit diversity used in UMTSS third-generation cellular systems. Space Time Transmit Diversity is optional in the UTRANN air interface, but compulsory for user equipment."
    }
]